1 Samuel 26

26

^1And the Ziphites came unto Saul to Gibeah, saying, Doth not David hide himself in the hill of Hachilah, which is before the desert? ^2Then Saul arose, and went down to the wilderness of Ziph, having three thousand chosen men of Israel with him, to seek David in the wilderness of Ziph. ^3And Saul encamped in the hill of Hachilah, which is before the desert, by the way. But David abode in the wilderness, and he saw that Saul came after him into the wilderness. ^4David therefore sent out spies, and understood that Saul was come of a certainty. ^5And David arose, and came to the place where Saul had encamped; and David beheld the place where Saul lay, and Abner the son of Ner, the captain of his host: and Saul lay within the place of the wagons, and the people were encamped round about him.

^6Then answered David and said to Ahimelech the Hittite, and to Abishai the son of Zeruiah, brother to Joab, saying, Who will go down with me to Saul to the camp? And Abishai said, I will go down with thee. ^7So David and Abishai came to the people by night: and, behold, Saul lay sleeping within the place of the wagons, with his spear stuck in the ground at his head; and Abner and the people lay round about him. ^8Then said Abishai to David, God hath delivered up thine enemy into thy hand this day: now therefore let me smite him, I pray thee, with the spear to the earth at one stroke, and I will not smite him the second time. ^9And David said to Abishai, Destroy him not; for who can put forth his hand against Jehovah's anointed, and be guiltless? ^10And David said, As Jehovah liveth, Jehovah will smite him; or his day shall come to die; or he shall go down into battle and perish. ^11Jehovah forbid that I should put forth my hand against Jehovah's anointed: but now take, I pray thee, the spear that is at his head, and the cruse of water, and let us go. ^12So David took the spear and the cruse of water from Saul's head; and they gat them away: and no man saw it, nor knew it, neither did any awake; for they were all asleep, because a deep sleep from Jehovah was fallen upon them.

^13Then David went over to the other side, and stood on the top of the mountain afar off; a great space being between them; ^14and David cried to the people, and to Abner the son of Ner, saying, Answerest thou not, Abner? Then Abner answered and said, Who art thou that criest to the king? ^15And David said to Abner, Art not thou a valiant man? and who is like to thee in Israel? wherefore then hast thou not kept watch over thy lord the king? for there came one of the people in to destroy the king thy lord. ^16This thing is not good that thou hast done. As Jehovah liveth, ye are worthy to die, because ye have not kept watch over your lord, Jehovah's anointed. And now see where the king's spear is, and the cruse of water that was at his head.

^17And Saul knew David's voice, and said, Is this thy voice, my son David? And David said, It is my voice, my lord, O king. ^18And he said, Wherefore doth my lord pursue after his servant? for what have I done? or what evil is in my hand? ^19Now therefore, I pray thee, let my lord the king hear the words of his servant. If it be Jehovah that hath stirred thee up against me, let him accept an offering: but if it be the children of men, cursed be they before Jehovah: for they have driven me out this day that I should not cleave unto the inheritance of Jehovah, saying, Go, serve other gods. ^20Now therefore, let not my blood fall to the earth away from the presence of Jehovah: for the king of Israel is come out to seek a flea, as when one doth hunt a partridge in the mountains.

^21Then said Saul, I have sinned: return, my son David; for I will no more do thee harm, because my life was precious in thine eyes this day: behold, I have played the fool, and have erred exceedingly. ^22And David answered and said, Behold the spear, O king! let then one of the young men come over and fetch it. ^23And Jehovah will render to every man his righteousness and his faithfulness; forasmuch as Jehovah delivered thee into my hand to-day, and I would not put forth my hand against Jehovah's anointed. ^24And, behold, as thy life was much set by this day in mine eyes, so let my life be much set by in the eyes of Jehovah, and let him deliver me out of all tribulation. ^25Then Saul said to David, Blessed be thou, my son David: thou shalt both do mightily, and shalt surely prevail. So David went his way, and Saul returned to his place.

1 Samuel 27

27

^1And David said in his heart, I shall now perish one day by the hand of Saul: there is nothing better for me than that I should escape into the land of the Philistines; and Saul will despair of me, to seek me any more in all the borders of Israel: so shall I escape out of his hand. ^2And David arose, and passed over, he and the six hundred men that were with him, unto Achish the son of Maoch, king of Gath. ^3And David dwelt with Achish at Gath, he and his men, every man with his household, even David with his two wives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the Carmelitess, Nabal's wife. ^4And it was told Saul that David was fled to Gath: and he sought no more again for him.

^5And David said unto Achish, If now I have found favor in thine eyes, let them give me a place in one of the cities in the country, that I may dwell there: for why should thy servant dwell in the royal city with thee? ^6Then Achish gave him Ziklag that day: wherefore Ziklag pertaineth unto the kings of Judah unto this day. ^7And the number of the days that David dwelt in the country of the Philistines was a full year and four months.

^8And David and his men went up, and made a raid upon the Geshurites, and the Girzites, and the Amalekites; for those nations were the inhabitants of the land, who were of old, as thou goest to Shur, even unto the land of Egypt. ^9And David smote the land, and saved neither man nor woman alive, and took away the sheep, and the oxen, and the asses, and the camels, and the apparel; and he returned, and came to Achish. ^10And Achish said, Against whom have ye made a raid to-day? And David said, Against the South of Judah, and against the South of the Jerahmeelites, and against the South of the Kenites. ^11And David saved neither man nor woman alive, to bring them to Gath, saying, Lest they should tell of us, saying, So did David, and so hath been his manner all the while he hath dwelt in the country of the Philistines. ^12And Achish believed David, saying, He hath made his people Israel utterly to abhor him; therefore he shall be my servant for ever.

1 Samuel 28

28

^1And it came to pass in those days, that the Philistines gathered their hosts together for warfare, to fight with Israel. And Achish said unto David, Know thou assuredly, that thou shalt go out with me in the host, thou and thy men. ^2And David said to Achish, Therefore thou shalt know what thy servant will do. And Achish said to David, Therefore will I make thee keeper of my head for ever.

^3Now Samuel was dead, and all Israel had lamented him, and buried him in Ramah, even in his own city. And Saul had put away those that had familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land. ^4And the Philistines gathered themselves together, and came and encamped in Shunem: and Saul gathered all Israel together, and they encamped in Gilboa. ^5And when Saul saw the host of the Philistines, he was afraid, and his heart trembled greatly. ^6And when Saul inquired of Jehovah, Jehovah answered him not, neither by dreams, nor by Urim, nor by prophets. ^7Then said Saul unto his servants, Seek me a woman that hath a familiar spirit, that I may go to her, and inquire of her. And his servants said to him, Behold, there is a woman that hath a familiar spirit at En-dor.

^8And Saul disguised himself, and put on other raiment, and went, he and two men with him, and they came to the woman by night: and he said, Divine unto me, I pray thee, by the familiar spirit, and bring me up whomsoever I shall name unto thee. ^9And the woman said unto him, Behold, thou knowest what Saul hath done, how he hath cut off those that have familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land: wherefore then layest thou a snare for my life, to cause me to die? ^10And Saul sware to her by Jehovah, saying, As Jehovah liveth, there shall no punishment happen to thee for this thing. ^11Then said the woman, Whom shall I bring up unto thee? And he said, Bring me up Samuel. ^12And when the woman saw Samuel, she cried with a loud voice; and the woman spake to Saul, saying, Why hast thou deceived me? for thou art Saul. ^13And the king said unto her, Be not afraid: for what seest thou? And the woman said unto Saul, I see a god coming up out of the earth. ^14And he said unto her, What form is he of? And she said, An old man cometh up; and he is covered with a robe. And Saul perceived that it was Samuel, and he bowed with his face to the ground, and did obeisance.

^15And Samuel said to Saul, Why hast thou disquieted me, to bring me up? And Saul answered, I am sore distressed; for the Philistines make war against me, and God is departed from me, and answereth me no more, neither by prophets, nor by dreams: therefore I have called thee, that thou mayest make known unto me what I shall do. ^16And Samuel said, Wherefore then dost thou ask of me, seeing Jehovah is departed from thee, and is become thine adversary? ^17And Jehovah hath done unto thee, as he spake by me: and Jehovah hath rent the kingdom out of thy hand, and given it to thy neighbor, even to David. ^18Because thou obeyedst not the voice of Jehovah, and didst not execute his fierce wrath upon Amalek, therefore hath Jehovah done this thing unto thee this day. ^19Moreover Jehovah will deliver Israel also with thee into the hand of the Philistines; and to-morrow shalt thou and thy sons be with me: Jehovah will deliver the host of Israel also into the hand of the Philistines.

^20Then Saul fell straightway his full length upon the earth, and was sore afraid, because of the words of Samuel: and there was no strength in him; for he had eaten no bread all the day, nor all the night. ^21And the woman came unto Saul, and saw that he was sore troubled, and said unto him, Behold, thy handmaid hath hearkened unto thy voice, and I have put my life in my hand, and have hearkened unto thy words which thou spakest unto me. ^22Now therefore, I pray thee, hearken thou also unto the voice of thy handmaid, and let me set a morsel of bread before thee; and eat, that thou mayest have strength, when thou goest on thy way. ^23But he refused, and said, I will not eat. But his servants, together with the woman, constrained him; and he hearkened unto their voice. So he arose from the earth, and sat upon the bed. ^24And the woman had a fatted calf in the house; and she hasted, and killed it; and she took flour, and kneaded it, and did bake unleavened bread thereof: ^25and she brought it before Saul, and before his servants; and they did eat. Then they rose up, and went away that night.

1 Samuel 29

29

^1Now the Philistines gathered together all their hosts to Aphek: and the Israelites encamped by the fountain which is in Jezreel. ^2And the lords of the Philistines passed on by hundreds, and by thousands; and David and his men passed on in the rearward with Achish. ^3Then said the princes of the Philistines, What do these Hebrews here? And Achish said unto the princes of the Philistines, Is not this David, the servant of Saul the king of Israel, who hath been with me these days, or rather these years, and I have found no fault in him since he fell away unto me unto this day? ^4But he princes of the Philistines were wroth with him; and the princes of the Philistines said unto him, Make the man return, that he may go back to his place where thou hast appointed him, and let him not go down with us to battle, lest in the battle he become an adversary to us: for wherewith should this fellow reconcile himself unto his lord? should it not be with the heads of these men? ^5Is not this David, of whom they sang one to another in dances, saying,

Saul hath slain his thousands,

And David his ten thousands?

^6Then Achish called David, and said unto him, As Jehovah liveth, thou hast been upright, and thy going out and thy coming in with me in the host is good in my sight; for I have not found evil in thee since the day of thy coming unto me unto this day: nevertheless the lords favor thee not. ^7Wherefore now return, and go in peace, that thou displease not the lords of the Philistines. ^8And David said unto Achish, But what have I done? and what hast thou found in thy servant so long as I have been before thee unto this day, that I may not go and fight against the enemies of my lord the king? ^9And Achish answered and said to David, I know that thou art good in my sight, as an angel of God: notwithstanding the princes of the Philistines have said, He shall not go up with us to the battle. ^10Wherefore now rise up early in the morning with the servants of thy lord that are come with thee; and as soon as ye are up early in the morning, and have light, depart. ^11So David rose up early, he and his men, to depart in the morning, to return into the land of the Philistines. And the Philistines went up to Jezreel.

1 Samuel 30

30

^1And it came to pass, when David and his men were come to Ziklag on the third day, that the Amalekites had made a raid upon the South, and upon Ziklag, and had smitten Ziklag, and burned it with fire, ^2and had taken captive the women and all that were therein, both small and great: they slew not any, but carried them off, and went their way. ^3And when David and his men came to the city, behold, it was burned with fire; and their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, were taken captive. ^4Then David and the people that were with him lifted up their voice and wept, until they had no more power to weep. ^5And David's two wives were taken captive, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite. ^6And David was greatly distressed; for the people spake of stoning him, because the soul of all the people was grieved, every man for his sons and for his daughters: but David strengthened himself in Jehovah his God.

^7And David said to Abiathar the priest, the son of Ahimelech, I pray thee, bring me hither the ephod. And Abiathar brought thither the ephod to David. ^8And David inquired of Jehovah, saying, If I pursue after this troop, shall I overtake them? And he answered him, Pursue; for thou shalt surely overtake them, and shalt without fail recover all. ^9So David went, he and the six hundred men that were with him, and came to the brook Besor, where those that were left behind stayed. ^10But David pursued, he and four hundred men; for two hundred stayed behind, who were so faint that they could not go over the brook Besor.

^11And they found an Egyptian in the field, and brought him to David, and gave him bread, and he did eat; and they gave him water to drink. ^12And they gave him a piece of a cake of figs, and two clusters of raisins: and when he had eaten, his spirit came again to him; for he had eaten no bread, nor drunk any water, three days and three nights. ^13And David said unto him, To whom belongest thou? and whence art thou? And he said, I am a young man of Egypt, servant to an Amalekite; and my master left me, because three days ago I fell sick. ^14We made a raid upon the South of the Cherethites, and upon that which belongeth to Judah, and upon the South of Caleb; and we burned Ziklag with fire. ^15And David said to him, Wilt thou bring me down to this troop? And he said, Swear unto me by God, that thou wilt neither kill me, nor deliver me up into the hands of my master, and I will bring thee down to this troop.

^16And when he had brought him down, behold, they were spread abroad over all the ground, eating and drinking, and dancing, because of all the great spoil that they had taken out of the land of the Philistines, and out of the land of Judah. ^17And David smote them from the twilight even unto the evening of the next day: and there escaped not a man of them, save four hundred young men, who rode upon camels and fled. ^18And David recovered all that the Amalekites had taken; and David rescued his two wives. ^19And there was nothing lacking to them, neither small nor great, neither sons nor daughters, neither spoil, nor anything that they had taken to them: David brought back all. ^20And David took all the flocks and the herds, which they drove before those other cattle, and said, This is David's spoil.

^21And David came to the two hundred men, who were so faint that they could not follow David, whom also they had made to abide at the brook Besor; and they went forth to meet David, and to meet the people that were with him: and when David came near to the people, he saluted them. ^22Then answered all the wicked men and base fellows, of those that went with David, and said, Because they went not with us, we will not give them aught of the spoil that we have recovered, save to every man his wife and his children, that he may lead them away, and depart. ^23Then said David, Ye shall not do so, my brethren, with that which Jehovah hath given unto us, who hath preserved us, and delivered the troop that came against us into our hand. ^24And who will hearken unto you in this matter? for as his share is that goeth down to the battle, so shall his share be that tarrieth by the baggage: they shall share alike. ^25And it was so from that day forward, that he made it a statute and an ordinance for Israel unto this day.

^26And when David came to Ziklag, he sent of the spoil unto the elders of Judah, even to his friends, saying, Behold, a present for you of the spoil of the enemies of Jehovah: ^27To them that were in Beth-el, and to them that were in Ramoth of the South, and to them that were in Jattir, ^28and to them that were in Aroer, and to them that were in Siphmoth, and to them that were in Eshtemoa, ^29and to them that were in Racal, and to them that were in the cities of the Jerahmeelites, and to them that were in the cities of the Kenites, ^30and to them that were in Hormah, and to them that were in Bor-ashan, and to them that were in Athach, ^31and to them that were in Hebron, and to all the places where David himself and his men were wont to haunt.

1 Samuel 31

31

^1Now the Philistines fought against Israel: and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain in mount Gilboa. ^2And the Philistines followed hard upon Saul and upon his sons; and the Philistines slew Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Malchishua, the sons of Saul. ^3And the battle went sore against Saul, and the archers overtook him; and he was greatly distressed by reason of the archers. ^4Then said Saul to his armorbearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through therewith, lest these uncircumcised come and thrust me through, and abuse me. But his armorbearer would not; for he was sore afraid. Therefore Saul took his sword, and fell upon it. ^5And when his armorbearer saw that Saul was dead, he likewise fell upon his sword, and died with him. ^6So Saul died, and his three sons, and his armorbearer, and all his men, that same day together.

^7And when the men of Israel that were on the other side of the valley, and they that were beyond the Jordan, saw that the men of Israel fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they forsook the cities, and fled; and the Philistines came and dwelt in them. ^8And it came to pass on the morrow, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his three sons fallen in mount Gilboa. ^9And they cut off his head, and stripped off his armor, and sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to carry the tidings unto the house of their idols, and to the people. ^10And they put his armor in the house of the Ashtaroth; and they fastened his body to the wall of Beth-shan. ^11And when the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead heard concerning him that which the Philistines had done to Saul, ^12all the valiant men arose, and went all night, and took the body of Saul and the bodies of his sons from the wall of Beth-shan; and they came to Jabesh, and burnt them there. ^13And they took their bones, and buried them under the tamarisk-tree in Jabesh, and fasted seven days.

1 Thessalonians 2

2

^1For yourselves, brethren, know our entering in unto you, that it hath not been found vain: ^2but having suffered before and been shamefully treated, as ye know, at Philippi, we waxed bold in our God to speak unto you the gospel of God in much conflict. ^3For our exhortation is not of error, nor of uncleanness, nor in guile: ^4but even as we have been approved of God to be intrusted with the gospel, so we speak; not as pleasing men, but God who proveth our hearts. ^5For neither at any time were we found using words of flattery, as ye know, nor a cloak of covetousness, God is witness; ^6nor seeking glory of men, neither from you nor from others, when we might have claimed authority as apostles of Christ. ^7But we were gentle in the midst of you, as when a nurse cherisheth her own children: ^8even so, being affectionately desirous of you, we were well pleased to impart unto you, not the gospel of God only, but also our own souls, because ye were become very dear to us. ^9For ye remember, brethren, our labor and travail: working night and day, that we might not burden any of you, we preached unto you the gospel of God. ^10Ye are witnesses, and God also, how holily and righteously and unblameably we behaved ourselves toward you that believe: ^11as ye know how we dealt with each one of you, as a father with his own children, exhorting you, and encouraging you, and testifying, ^12to the end that ye should walk worthily of God, who calleth you into his own kingdom and glory. ^13And for this cause we also thank God without ceasing, that, when ye received from us the word of the message, even the word of God, ye accepted it not as the word of men, but, as it is in truth, the word of God, which also worketh in you that believe. ^14For ye, brethren, became imitators of the churches of God which are in Judaea in Christ Jesus: for ye also suffered the same things of your own countrymen, even as they did of the Jews; ^15who both killed the Lord Jesus and the prophets, and drove out us, and pleased not God, and are contrary to all men; ^16forbidding us to speak to the Gentiles that they may be saved; to fill up their sins always: but the wrath is come upon them to the uttermost. ^17But we, brethren, being bereaved of you for a short season, in presence not in heart, endeavored the more exceedingly to see your face with great desire: ^18because we would fain have come unto you, I Paul once and again; and Satan hindered us. ^19For what is our hope, or joy, or crown of glorying? Are not even ye, before our Lord Jesus at his coming? ^20For ye are our glory and our joy.

1 Thessalonians 4

4

^1Finally then, brethren, we beseech and exhort you in the Lord Jesus, that, as ye received of us how ye ought to walk and to please God, even as ye do walk, --that ye abound more and more. ^2For ye know what charge we gave you through the Lord Jesus. ^3For this is the will of God, even your sanctification, that ye abstain from fornication; ^4that each one of you know how to possess himself of his own vessel in sanctification and honor, ^5not in the passion of lust, even as the Gentiles who know not God; ^6that no man transgress, and wrong his brother in the matter: because the Lord is an avenger in all these things, as also we forewarned you and testified. ^7For God called us not for uncleanness, but in sanctification. ^8Therefore he that rejecteth, rejecteth not man, but God, who giveth his Holy Spirit unto you. ^9But concerning love of the brethren ye have no need that one write unto you: for ye yourselves are taught of God to love one another; ^10for indeed ye do it toward all the brethren that are in all Macedonia. But we exhort you, brethren, that ye abound more and more; ^11and that ye study to be quiet, and to do your own business, and to work with your hands, even as we charged you; ^12that ye may walk becomingly toward them that are without, and may have need of nothing. ^13But we would not have you ignorant, brethren, concerning them that fall asleep; that ye sorrow not, even as the rest, who have no hope. ^14For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again, even so them also that are fallen asleep in Jesus will God bring with him. ^15For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord, that we that are alive, that are left unto the coming of the Lord, shall in no wise precede them that are fallen asleep. ^16For the Lord himself shall descend from heaven, with a shout, with the voice of the archangel, and with the trump of God: and the dead in Christ shall rise first; ^17then we that are alive, that are left, shall together with them be caught up in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air: and so shall we ever be with the Lord. ^18Wherefore comfort one another with these words.

1 Timothy 4

4

^1But the Spirit saith expressly, that in later times some shall fall away from the faith, giving heed to seducing spirits and doctrines of demons, ^2through the hypocrisy of men that speak lies, branded in their own conscience as with a hot iron; ^3forbidding to marry, and commanding to abstain from meats, which God created to be received with thanksgiving by them that believe and know the truth. ^4For every creature of God is good, and nothing is to be rejected, if it be received with thanksgiving: ^5for it is sanctified through the word of God and prayer. ^6If thou put the brethren in mind of these things, thou shalt be a good minister of Christ Jesus, nourished in the words of the faith, and of the good doctrine which thou hast followed until now: ^7but refuse profane and old wives' fables. And exercise thyself unto godliness: ^8for bodily exercise is profitable for a little; but godliness is profitable for all things, having promise of the life which now is, and of that which is to come. ^9Faithful is the saying, and worthy of all acceptation. ^10For to this end we labor and strive, because we have our hope set on the living God, who is the Saviour of all men, specially of them that believe. ^11These things command and teach. ^12Let no man despise thy youth; but be thou an ensample to them that believe, in word, in manner of life, in love, in faith, in purity. ^13Till I come, give heed to reading, to exhortation, to teaching. ^14Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by prophecy, with the laying on of the hands of the presbytery. ^15Be diligent in these things; give thyself wholly to them; that thy progress may be manifest unto all. ^16Take heed to thyself, and to thy teaching. Continue in these things; for in doing this thou shalt save both thyself and them that hear thee.

1 Timothy 5

5

^1Rebuke not an elder, but exhort him as a father; the younger men as brethren: ^2the elder women as mothers; the younger as sisters, in all purity. ^3Honor widows that are widows indeed. ^4But if any widow hath children or grandchildren, let them learn first to show piety towards their own family, and to requite their parents: for this is acceptable in the sight of God. ^5Now she that is a widow indeed, and desolate, hath her hope set on God, and continueth in supplications and prayers night and day. ^6But she that giveth herself to pleasure is dead while she liveth. ^7These things also command, that they may be without reproach. ^8But if any provideth not for his own, and specially his own household, he hath denied the faith, and is worse than an unbeliever. ^9Let none be enrolled as a widow under threescore years old, having been the wife of one man, ^10well reported of for good works; if she hath brought up children, if she hath used hospitality to strangers, if she hath washed the saints' feet, if she hath relieved the afflicted, if she hath diligently followed every good work. ^11But younger widows refuse: for when they have waxed wanton against Christ, they desire to marry; ^12having condemnation, because they have rejected their first pledge. ^13And withal they learn also to be idle, going about from house to house; and not only idle, but tattlers also and busybodies, speaking things which they ought not. ^14I desire therefore that the younger widows marry, bear children, rule the household, give no occasion to the adversary for reviling: ^15for already some are turned aside after Satan. ^16If any woman that believeth hath widows, let her relieve them, and let not the church be burdened; that it may relieve them that are widows indeed. ^17Let the elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honor, especially those who labor in the word and in teaching. ^18For the span saith, Thou shalt not muzzle the ox when he treadeth out the corn. And, The laborer is worthy of his hire. ^19Against an elder receive not an accusation, except at the mouth of two or three witnesses. ^20Them that sin reprove in the sight of all, that the rest also may be in fear. ^21I charge thee in the sight of God, and Christ Jesus, and the elect angels, that thou observe these things without prejudice, doing nothing by partiality. ^22Lay hands hastily on no man, neither be partaker of other men's sins: keep thyself pure. ^23Be no longer a drinker of water, but use a little wine for thy stomach's sake and thine often infirmities. ^24Some men's sins are evident, going before unto judgment; and some men also they follow after. ^25In like manner also there are good works that are evident; and such as are otherwise cannot be hid.

1 Timothy 6

6

^1Let as many as are servants under the yoke count their own masters worthy of all honor, that the name of God and the doctrine be not blasphemed. ^2And they that have believing masters, let them not despise them, because they are brethren; but let them serve them the rather, because they that partake of the benefit are believing and beloved. These things teach and exhort. ^3If any man teacheth a different doctrine, and consenteth not to sound words, even the words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to the doctrine which is according to godliness; ^4he is puffed up, knowing nothing, but doting about questionings and disputes of words, whereof cometh envy, strife, railings, evil surmisings, ^5wranglings of men corrupted in mind and bereft of the truth, supposing that godliness is a way of gain. ^6But godliness with contentment is great gain: ^7for we brought nothing into the world, for neither can we carry anything out; ^8but having food and covering we shall be therewith content. ^9But they that are minded to be rich fall into a temptation and a snare and many foolish and hurtful lusts, such as drown men in destruction and perdition. ^10For the love of money is a root of all kinds of evil: which some reaching after have been led astray from the faith, and have pierced themselves through with many sorrows. ^11But thou, O man of God, flee these things; and follow after righteousness, godliness, faith, love, patience, meekness. ^12Fight the good fight of the faith, lay hold on the life eternal, whereunto thou wast called, and didst confess the good confession in the sight of many witnesses. ^13I charge thee in the sight of God, who giveth life to all things, and of Christ Jesus, who before Pontius Pilate witnessed the good confession; ^14that thou keep the commandment, without spot, without reproach, until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ: ^15which in its own times he shall show, who is the blessed and only Potentate, the King of kings, and Lord of lords; ^16who only hath immortality, dwelling in light unapproachable; whom no man hath seen, nor can see: to whom be honor and power eternal. Amen. ^17Charge them that are rich in this present world, that they be not highminded, nor have their hope set on the uncertainty of riches, but on God, who giveth us richly all things to enjoy; ^18that they do good, that they be rich in good works, that they be ready to distribute, willing to communicate; ^19laying up in store for themselves a good foundation against the time to come, that they may lay hold on the life which is life indeed. ^20O Timothy, guard that which is committed unto thee, turning away from the profane babblings and oppositions of the knowledge which is falsely so called; ^21which some professing have erred concerning the faith. Grace be with you.

James 2

2

^1My brethren, hold not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord of glory, with respect of persons. ^2For if there come into your synagogue a man with a gold ring, in fine clothing, and there come in also a poor man in vile clothing; ^3and ye have regard to him that weareth the fine clothing, and say, Sit thou here in a good place; and ye say to the poor man, Stand thou there, or sit under my footstool; ^4Do ye not make distinctions among yourselves, and become judges with evil thoughts? ^5Hearken, my beloved brethren; did not God choose them that are poor as to the world to be rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom which he promised to them that love him? ^6But ye have dishonored the poor man. Do not the rich oppress you, and themselves drag you before the judgment-seats? ^7Do not they blaspheme the honorable name by which ye are called? ^8Howbeit if ye fulfil the royal law, according to the span, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself, ye do well: ^9but if ye have respect of persons, ye commit sin, being convicted by the law as transgressors. ^10For whosoever shall keep the whole law, and yet stumble in one point, he is become guilty of all. ^11For he that said, Do not commit adultery, said also, Do not kill. Now if thou dost not commit adultery, but killest, thou art become a transgressor of the law. ^12So speak ye, and so do, as men that are to be judged by a law of liberty. ^13For judgment is without mercy to him that hath showed no mercy: mercy glorieth against judgment. ^14What doth it profit, my brethren, if a man say he hath faith, but have not works? can that faith save him? ^15If a brother or sister be naked and in lack of daily food, ^16and one of you say unto them, Go in peace, be ye warmed and filled; and yet ye give them not the things needful to the body; what doth it profit? ^17Even so faith, if it have not works, is dead in itself. ^18Yea, a man will say, Thou hast faith, and I have works: show me thy faith apart from thy works, and I by my works will show thee my faith. ^19Thou believest that God is one; thou doest well: the demons also believe, and shudder. ^20But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith apart from works is barren? ^21Was not Abraham our father justified by works, in that he offered up Isaac his son upon the altar? ^22Thou seest that faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made perfect; ^23and the span was fulfilled which saith, And Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned unto him for righteousness; and he was called the friend of God. ^24Ye see that by works a man is justified, and not only by faith. ^25And in like manner was not also Rahab the harlot justified by works, in that she received the messengers, and sent them out another way? ^26For as the body apart from the spirit is dead, even so faith apart from works is dead.

James 3

3

^1Be not many of you teachers, my brethren, knowing that we shall receive heavier judgment. ^2For in many things we all stumble. If any stumbleth not in word, the same is a perfect man, able to bridle the whole body also. ^3Now if we put the horses' bridles into their mouths that they may obey us, we turn about their whole body also. ^4Behold, the ships also, though they are so great and are driven by rough winds, are yet turned about by a very small rudder, whither the impulse of the steersman willeth. ^5So the tongue also is a little member, and boasteth great things. Behold, how much wood is kindled by how small a fire! ^6And the tongue is a fire: the world of iniquity among our members is the tongue, which defileth the whole body, and setteth on fire the wheel of nature, and is set on fire by hell. ^7For every kind of beasts and birds, of creeping things and things in the sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed by mankind. ^8But the tongue can no man tame; it is a restless evil, it is full of deadly poison. ^9Therewith bless we the Lord and Father; and therewith curse we men, who are made after the likeness of God: ^10out of the same mouth cometh forth blessing and cursing. My brethren, these things ought not so to be. ^11Doth the fountain send forth from the same opening sweet water and bitter? ^12Can a fig tree, my brethren, yield olives, or a vine figs? Neither can salt water yield sweet. ^13Who is wise and understanding among you? let him show by his good life his works in meekness of wisdom. ^14But if ye have bitter jealousy and faction in your heart, glory not and lie not against the truth. ^15This wisdom is not a wisdom that cometh down from above, but is earthly, sensual, devilish. ^16For where jealousy and faction are, there is confusion and every vile deed. ^17But the wisdom that is from above is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, easy to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without variance, without hypocrisy. ^18And the fruit of righteousness is sown in peace for them that make peace.

James 4

4

^1Whence come wars and whence come fightings among you? come they not hence, even of your pleasures that war in your members? ^2Ye lust, and have not: ye kill, and covet, and cannot obtain: ye fight and war; ye have not, because ye ask not. ^3Ye ask, and receive not, because ye ask amiss, that ye may spend it in your pleasures. ^4Ye adulteresses, know ye not that the friendship of the world is enmity with God? Whosoever therefore would be a friend of the world maketh himself an enemy of God. ^5Or think ye that the span speaketh in vain? Doth the spirit which he made to dwell in us long unto envying? ^6But he giveth more grace. Wherefore the span saith, God resisteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble. ^7Be subject therefore unto God; but resist the devil, and he will flee from you. ^8Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you. Cleanse your hands, ye sinners; and purify your hearts, ye doubleminded. ^9Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep: let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your joy to heaviness. ^10Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord, and he shall exalt you. ^11Speak not one against another, brethren. He that speaketh against a brother, or judgeth his brother, speaketh against the law, and judgeth the law: but if thou judgest the law, thou art not a doer of the law, but a judge. ^12One only is the lawgiver and judge, even he who is able to save and to destroy: but who art thou that judgest thy neighbor? ^13Come now, ye that say, To-day or to-morrow we will go into this city, and spend a year there, and trade, and get gain: ^14whereas ye know not what shall be on the morrow. What is your life? For ye are a vapor, that appeareth for a little time, and then vanisheth away. ^15For that ye ought to say, If the Lord will, we shall both live, and do this or that. ^16But now ye glory in your vauntings: all such glorying is evil. ^17To him therefore that knoweth to do good, and doeth it not, to him it is sin.

James 5

5

^1Come now, ye rich, weep and howl for your miseries that are coming upon you. ^2Your riches are corrupted, and your garments are moth-eaten. ^3Your gold and your silver are rusted; and their rust shall be for a testimony against you, and shall eat your flesh as fire. Ye have laid up your treasure in the last days. ^4Behold, the hire of the laborers who mowed your fields, which is of you kept back by fraud, crieth out: and the cries of them that reaped have entered into the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth. ^5Ye have lived delicately on the earth, and taken your pleasure; ye have nourished your hearts in a day of slaughter. ^6Ye have condemned, ye have killed the righteous one; he doth not resist you. ^7Be patient therefore, brethren, until the coming of the Lord. Behold, the husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, being patient over it, until it receive the early and latter rain. ^8Be ye also patient; establish your hearts: for the coming of the Lord is at hand. ^9Murmur not, brethren, one against another, that ye be not judged: behold, the judge standeth before the doors. ^10Take, brethren, for an example of suffering and of patience, the prophets who spake in the name of the Lord. ^11Behold, we call them blessed that endured: ye have heard of the patience of Job, and have seen the end of the Lord, how that the Lord is full of pity, and merciful. ^12But above all things, my brethren, swear not, neither by the heaven, nor by the earth, nor by any other oath: but let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay; that ye fall not under judgment. ^13Is any among you suffering? Let him pray. Is any cheerful? Let him sing praise. ^14Is any among you sick? Let him call for the elders of the church; and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord: ^15and the prayer of faith shall save him that is sick, and the Lord shall raise him up; and if he have committed sins, it shall be forgiven him. ^16Confess therefore your sins one to another, and pray one for another, that ye may be healed. The supplication of a righteous man availeth much in its working. ^17Elijah was a man of like passions with us, and he prayed fervently that it might not rain; and it rained not on the earth for three years and six months. ^18And he prayed again; and the heaven gave rain, and the earth brought forth her fruit. ^19My brethren, if any among you err from the truth, and one convert him; ^20let him know, that he who converteth a sinner from the error of his way shall save a soul from death, and shall cover a multitude of sins.

Jeremiah 2

2

^1And the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, ^2Go, and cry in the ears of Jerusalem, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, I remember for thee the kindness of thy youth, the love of thine espousals; how thou wentest after me in the wilderness, in a land that was not sown. ^3Israel was holiness unto Jehovah, the first-fruits of his increase: all that devour him shall be held guilty; evil shall come upon them, saith Jehovah. ^4Hear ye the word of Jehovah, O house of Jacob, and all the families of the house of Israel: ^5thus saith Jehovah, What unrighteousness have your fathers found in me, that they are gone far from me, and have walked after vanity, and are become vain? ^6Neither said they, Where is Jehovah that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, that led us through the wilderness, through a land of deserts and of pits, through a land of drought and of the shadow of death, through a land that none passed through, and where no man dwelt? ^7And I brought you into a plentiful land, to eat the fruit thereof and the goodness thereof; but when ye entered, ye defiled my land, and made my heritage an abomination. ^8The priests said not, Where is Jehovah? and they that handle the law knew me not: the rulers also transgressed against me, and the prophets prophesied by Baal, and walked after things that do not profit. ^9Wherefore I will yet contend with you, saith Jehovah, and with your children's children will I contend. ^10For pass over to the isles of Kittim, and see; and send unto Kedar, and consider diligently; and see if there hath been such a thing. ^11Hath a nation changed its gods, which yet are no gods? but my people have changed their glory for that which doth not profit. ^12Be astonished, O ye heavens, at this, and be horribly afraid, be ye very desolate, saith Jehovah. ^13For my people have committed two evils: they have forsaken me, the fountain of living waters, and hewed them out cisterns, broken cisterns, that can hold no water. ^14Is Israel a servant? is he a home-born slave? why is he become a prey? ^15The young lions have roared upon him, and yelled; and they have made his land waste: his cities are burned up, without inhabitant. ^16The children also of Memphis and Tahpanhes have broken the crown of thy head. ^17Hast thou not procured this unto thyself, in that thou hast forsaken Jehovah thy God, when he led thee by the way? ^18And now what hast thou to do in the way to Egypt, to drink the waters of the Shihor? or what hast thou to do in the way to Assyria, to drink the waters of the River? ^19Thine own wickedness shall correct thee, and thy backslidings shall reprove thee: know therefore and see that it is an evil thing and a bitter, that thou hast forsaken Jehovah thy God, and that my fear is not in thee, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts. ^20For of old time I have broken thy yoke, and burst thy bonds; and thou saidst, I will not serve; for upon every high hill and under every green tree thou didst bow thyself, playing the harlot. ^21Yet I had planted thee a noble vine, wholly a right seed: how then art thou turned into the degenerate branches of a foreign vine unto me? ^22For though thou wash thee with lye, and take thee much soap, yet thine iniquity is marked before me, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^23How canst thou say, I am not defiled, I have not gone after the Baalim? see thy way in the valley, know what thou hast done: thou art a swift dromedary traversing her ways; ^24a wild ass used to the wilderness, that snuffeth up the wind in her desire; in her occasion who can turn her away? all they that seek her will not weary themselves; in her month they shall find her. ^25Withhold thy foot from being unshod, and thy throat from thirst: but thou saidst, It is in vain; no, for I have loved strangers, and after them will I go. ^26As the thief is ashamed when he is found, so is the house of Israel ashamed; they, their kings, their princes, and their priests, and their prophets; ^27who say to a stock, Thou art my father; and to a stone, Thou hast brought me forth: for they have turned their back unto me, and not their face; but in the time of their trouble they will say, Arise, and save us. ^28But where are thy gods that thou hast made thee? let them arise, if they can save thee in the time of thy trouble: for according to the number of thy cities are thy gods, O Judah. ^29Wherefore will ye contend with me? ye all have transgressed against me, saith Jehovah. ^30In vain have I smitten your children; they received no correction: your own sword hath devoured your prophets, like a destroying lion. ^31O generation, see ye the word of Jehovah. Have I been a wilderness unto Israel? or a land of thick darkness? wherefore say my people, We are broken loose; we will come no more unto thee? ^32Can a virgin forget her ornaments, or a bride her attire? yet my people have forgotten me days without number. ^33How trimmest thou thy way to seek love! therefore even the wicked women hast thou taught thy ways. ^34Also in thy skirts is found the blood of the souls of the innocent poor: thou didst not find them breaking in; but it is because of all these things. ^35Yet thou saidst, I am innocent; surely his anger is turned away from me. Behold, I will enter into judgment with thee, because thou sayest, I have not sinned. ^36Why gaddest thou about so much to change thy way? thou shalt be ashamed of Egypt also, as thou wast ashamed of Assyria. ^37From thence also shalt thou go forth, with thy hands upon thy head: for Jehovah hath rejected those in whom thou trustest, and thou shalt not prosper with them.

Jeremiah 3

3

^1They say, If a man put away his wife, and she go from him, and become another man's, will he return unto her again? will not that land be greatly polluted? But thou hast played the harlot with many lovers; yet return again to me, saith Jehovah. ^2Lift up thine eyes unto the bare heights, and see; where hast thou not been lain with? By the ways hast thou sat for them, as an Arabian in the wilderness; and thou hast polluted the land with thy whoredoms and with thy wickedness. ^3Therefore the showers have been withholden, and there hath been no latter rain; yet thou hast a harlot's forehead, thou refusedst to be ashamed. ^4Wilt thou not from this time cry unto me, My Father, thou art the guide of my youth? ^5Will he retain his anger for ever? will he keep it to the end? Behold, thou hast spoken and hast done evil things, and hast had thy way. ^6Moreover Jehovah said unto me in the days of Josiah the king, Hast thou seen that which backsliding Israel hath done? she is gone up upon every high mountain and under every green tree, and there hath played the harlot. ^7And I said after she had done all these things, She will return unto me; but she returned not: and her treacherous sister Judah saw it. ^8And I saw, when, for this very cause that backsliding Israel had committed adultery, I had put her away and given her a bill of divorcement, yet treacherous Judah her sister feared not; but she also went and played the harlot. ^9And it came to pass through the lightness of her whoredom, that the land was polluted, and she committed adultery with stones and with stocks. ^10And yet for all this her treacherous sister Judah hath not returned unto me with her whole heart, but feignedly, saith Jehovah. ^11And Jehovah said unto me, Backsliding Israel hath showed herself more righteous than treacherous Judah. ^12Go, and proclaim these words toward the north, and say, Return, thou backsliding Israel, saith Jehovah; I will not look in anger upon you; for I am merciful, saith Jehovah, I will not keep anger for ever. ^13Only acknowledge thine iniquity, that thou hast transgressed against Jehovah thy God, and hast scattered thy ways to the strangers under every green tree, and ye have not obeyed my voice, saith Jehovah. ^14Return, O backsliding children, saith Jehovah; for I am a husband unto you: and I will take you one of a city, and two of a family, and I will bring you to Zion: ^15and I will give you shepherds according to my heart, who shall feed you with knowledge and understanding. ^16And it shall come to pass, when ye are multiplied and increased in the land, in those days, saith Jehovah, they shall say no more, The ark of the covenant of Jehovah; neither shall it come to mind; neither shall they remember it; neither shall they miss it; neither shall it be made any more. ^17At that time they shall call Jerusalem the throne of Jehovah; and all the nations shall be gathered unto it, to the name of Jehovah, to Jerusalem: neither shall they walk any more after the stubbornness of their evil heart. ^18In those days the house of Judah shall walk with the house of Israel, and they shall come together out of the land of the north to the land that I gave for an inheritance unto your fathers. ^19But I said, How I will put thee among the children, and give thee a pleasant land, a goodly heritage of the hosts of the nations! and I said, Ye shall call me My Father, and shall not turn away from following me. ^20Surely as a wife treacherously departeth from her husband, so have ye dealt treacherously with me, O house of Israel, saith Jehovah. ^21A voice is heard upon the bare heights, the weeping and the supplications of the children of Israel; because they have perverted their way, they have forgotten Jehovah their God. ^22Return, ye backsliding children, I will heal your backslidings. Behold, we are come unto thee; for thou art Jehovah our God. ^23Truly in vain is the help that is looked for from the hills, the tumult on the mountains: truly in Jehovah our God is the salvation of Israel. ^24But the shameful thing hath devoured the labor of our fathers from our youth, their flocks and their herds, their sons and their daughters. ^25Let us lie down in our shame, and let our confusion cover us; for we have sinned against Jehovah our God, we and our fathers, from our youth even unto this day; and we have not obeyed the voice of Jehovah our God.

Jeremiah 4

4

^1If thou wilt return, O Israel, saith Jehovah, if thou wilt return unto me, and if thou wilt put away thine abominations out of my sight; then shalt thou not be removed; ^2and thou shalt swear, As Jehovah liveth, in truth, in justice, and in righteousness; and the nations shall bless themselves in him, and in him shall they glory. ^3For thus saith Jehovah to the men of Judah and to Jerusalem, Break up your fallow ground, and sow not among thorns. ^4Circumcise yourselves to Jehovah, and take away the foreskins of your heart, ye men of Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem; lest my wrath go forth like fire, and burn so that none can quench it, because of the evil of your doings. ^5Declare ye in Judah, and publish in Jerusalem; and say, Blow ye the trumpet in the land: cry aloud and say, Assemble yourselves, and let us go into the fortified cities. ^6Set up a standard toward Zion: flee for safety, stay not; for I will bring evil from the north, and a great destruction. ^7A lion is gone up from his thicket, and a destroyer of nations; he is on his way, he is gone forth from his place, to make thy land desolate, that thy cities be laid waste, without inhabitant. ^8For this gird you with sackcloth, lament and wail; for the fierce anger of Jehovah is not turned back from us. ^9And it shall come to pass at that day, saith Jehovah, that the heart of the king shall perish, and the heart of the princes; and the priests shall be astonished, and the prophets shall wonder. ^10Then said I, Ah, Lord Jehovah! surely thou hast greatly deceived this people and Jerusalem, saying, Ye shall have peace; whereas the sword reacheth unto the life. ^11At that time shall it be said to this people and to Jerusalem, A hot wind from the bare heights in the wilderness toward the daughter of my people, not to winnow, nor to cleanse; ^12a full wind from these shall come for me: now will I also utter judgments against them. ^13Behold, he shall come up as clouds, and his chariots shall be as the whirlwind: his horses are swifter than eagles. Woe unto us! for we are ruined. ^14O Jerusalem, wash thy heart from wickedness, that thou mayest be saved. How long shall thine evil thoughts lodge within thee? ^15For a voice declareth from Dan, and publisheth evil from the hills of Ephraim: ^16make ye mention to the nations; behold, publish against Jerusalem, that watchers come from a far country, and give out their voice against the cities of Judah. ^17As keepers of a field are they against her round about, because she hath been rebellious against me, saith Jehovah. ^18Thy way and thy doings have procured these things unto thee; this is thy wickedness; for it is bitter, for it reacheth unto thy heart. ^19My anguish, my anguish! I am pained at my very heart; my heart is disquieted in me; I cannot hold my peace; because thou hast heard, O my soul, the sound of the trumpet, the alarm of war. ^20Destruction upon destruction is cried; for the whole land is laid waste: suddenly are my tents destroyed, and my curtains in a moment. ^21How long shall I see the standard, and hear the sound of the trumpet? ^22For my people are foolish, they know me not; they are sottish children, and they have no understanding; they are wise to do evil, but to do good they have no knowledge. ^23I beheld the earth, and, lo, it was waste and void; and the heavens, and they had no light. ^24I beheld the mountains, and, lo, they trembled, and all the hills moved to and fro. ^25I beheld, and, lo, there was no man, and all the birds of the heavens were fled. ^26I beheld, and, lo, the fruitful field was a wilderness, and all the cities thereof were broken down at the presence of Jehovah, and before his fierce anger. ^27For thus saith Jehovah, The whole land shall be a desolation; yet will I not make a full end. ^28For this shall the earth mourn, and the heavens above be black; because I have spoken it, I have purposed it, and I have not repented, neither will I turn back from it. ^29Every city fleeth for the noise of the horsemen and bowmen; they go into the thickets, and climb up upon the rocks: every city is forsaken, and not a man dwelleth therein. ^30And thou, when thou art made desolate, what wilt thou do? Though thou clothest thyself with scarlet, though thou deckest thee with ornaments of gold, though thou enlargest thine eyes with paint, in vain dost thou make thyself fair; thy lovers despise thee, they seek thy life. ^31For I have heard a voice as of a woman in travail, the anguish as of her that bringeth forth her first child, the voice of the daughter of Zion, that gaspeth for breath, that spreadeth her hands, saying, Woe is me now! for my soul fainteth before the murderers.

Jeremiah 5

5

^1Run ye to and fro through the streets of Jerusalem, and see now, and know, and seek in the broad places thereof, if ye can find a man, if there be any that doeth justly, that seeketh truth; and I will pardon her. ^2And though they say, As Jehovah liveth; surely they swear falsely. ^3O Jehovah, do not thine eyes look upon truth? thou hast stricken them, but they were not grieved; thou hast consumed them, but they have refused to receive correction: they have made their faces harder than a rock; they have refused to return. ^4Then I said, Surely these are poor; they are foolish; for they know not the way of Jehovah, nor the law of their God: ^5I will get me unto the great men, and will speak unto them; for they know the way of Jehovah, and the law of their God. But these with one accord have broken the yoke, and burst the bonds. ^6Wherefore a lion out of the forest shall slay them, a wolf of the evenings shall destroy them, a leopard shall watch against their cities; every one that goeth out thence shall be torn in pieces; because their transgressions are many, and their backslidings are increased. ^7How can I pardon thee? thy children have forsaken me, and sworn by them that are no gods: when I had fed them to the full, they committed adultery, and assembled themselves in troops at the harlots' houses. ^8They were as fed horses roaming at large; every one neighed after his neighbor's wife. ^9Shall I not visit for these things? saith Jehovah; and shall not my soul be avenged on such a nation as this? ^10Go ye up upon her walls, and destroy; but make not a full end: take away her branches; for they are not Jehovah's. ^11For the house of Israel and the house of Judah have dealt very treacherously against me, saith Jehovah. ^12They have denied Jehovah, and said, It is not he; neither shall evil come upon us; neither shall we see sword nor famine: ^13and the prophets shall become wind, and the word is not in them: thus shall it be done unto them. ^14Wherefore thus saith Jehovah, the God of hosts, Because ye speak this word, behold, I will make my words in thy mouth fire, and this people wood, and it shall devour them. ^15Lo, I will bring a nation upon you from far, O house of Israel, saith Jehovah: it is a mighty nation, it is an ancient nation, a nation whose language thou knowest not, neither understandest what they say. ^16Their quiver is an open sepulchre, they are all mighty men. ^17And they shall eat up thy harvest, and thy bread, which thy sons and thy daughters should eat; they shall eat up thy flocks and thy herds; they shall eat up thy vines and thy fig-trees; they shall beat down thy fortified cities, wherein thou trustest, with the sword. ^18But even in those days, saith Jehovah, I will not make a full end with you. ^19And it shall come to pass, when ye shall say, Wherefore hath Jehovah our God done all these things unto us? then shalt thou say unto them, Like as ye have forsaken me, and served foreign gods in your land, so shall ye serve strangers in a land that is not yours. ^20Declare ye this in the house of Jacob, and publish it in Judah, saying, ^21Hear now this, O foolish people, and without understanding; that have eyes, and see not; that have ears, and hear not: ^22Fear ye not me? saith Jehovah: will ye not tremble at my presence, who have placed the sand for the bound of the sea, by a perpetual decree, that it cannot pass it? and though the waves thereof toss themselves, yet can they not prevail; though they roar, yet can they not pass over it. ^23But this people hath a revolting and a rebellious heart; they are revolted and gone. ^24Neither say they in their heart, Let us now fear Jehovah our God, that giveth rain, both the former and the latter, in its season; that preserveth unto us the appointed weeks of the harvest. ^25Your iniquities have turned away these things, and your sins have withholden good from you. ^26For among my people are found wicked men: they watch, as fowlers lie in wait; they set a trap, they catch men. ^27As a cage is full of birds, so are their houses full of deceit: therefore they are become great, and waxed rich. ^28They are waxed fat, they shine: yea, they overpass in deeds of wickedness; they plead not the cause, the cause of the fatherless, that they may prosper; and the right of the needy do they not judge. ^29Shall I not visit for these things? saith Jehovah; shall not my soul be avenged on such a nation as this? ^30A wonderful and horrible thing is come to pass in the land: ^31the prophets prophesy falsely, and the priests bear rule by their means; and my people love to have it so: and what will ye do in the end thereof?

Jeremiah 6

6

^1Flee for safety, ye children of Benjamin, out of the midst of Jerusalem, and blow the trumpet in Tekoa, and raise up a signal on Beth-haccherem; for evil looketh forth from the north, and a great destruction. ^2The comely and delicate one, the daughter of Zion, will I cut off. ^3Shepherds with their flocks shall come unto her; they shall pitch their tents against her round about; they shall feed every one in his place. ^4Prepare ye war against her; arise, and let us go up at noon. Woe unto us! for the day declineth, for the shadows of the evening are stretched out. ^5Arise, and let us go up by night, and let us destroy her palaces. ^6For thus hath Jehovah of hosts said, Hew ye down trees, and cast up a mound against Jerusalem: this is the city to be visited; she is wholly oppression in the midst of her. ^7As a well casteth forth its waters, so she casteth forth her wickedness: violence and destruction is heard in her; before me continually is sickness and wounds. ^8Be thou instructed, O Jerusalem, lest my soul be alienated from thee; lest I make thee a desolation, a land not inhabited. ^9Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, They shall thoroughly glean the remnant of Israel as a vine: turn again thy hand as a grape-gatherer into the baskets. ^10To whom shall I speak and testify, that they may hear? behold, their ear is uncircumcised, and they cannot hearken: behold, the word of Jehovah is become unto them a reproach; they have no delight in it. ^11Therefore I am full of the wrath of Jehovah; I am weary with holding in: pour it out upon the children in the street, and upon the assembly of young men together; for even the husband with the wife shall be taken, the aged with him that is full of days. ^12And their houses shall be turned unto others, their fields and their wives together; for I will stretch out my hand upon the inhabitants of the land, saith Jehovah. ^13For from the least of them even unto the greatest of them every one is given to covetousness; and from the prophet even unto the priest every one dealeth falsely. ^14They have healed also the hurt of my people slightly, saying, Peace, peace; when there is no peace. ^15Were they ashamed when they had committed abomination? nay, they were not at all ashamed, neither could they blush: therefore they shall fall among them that fall; at the time that I visit them they shall be cast down, saith Jehovah. ^16Thus saith Jehovah, Stand ye in the ways and see, and ask for the old paths, where is the good way; and walk therein, and ye shall find rest for your souls: but they said, We will not walk therein. ^17And I set watchmen over you, saying, Hearken to the sound of the trumpet; but they said, We will not hearken. ^18Therefore hear, ye nations, and know, O congregation, what is among them. ^19Hear, O earth: behold, I will bring evil upon this people, even the fruit of their thoughts, because they have not hearkened unto my words; and as for my law, they have rejected it. ^20To what purpose cometh there to me frankincense from Sheba, and the sweet cane from a far country? your burnt-offerings are not acceptable, nor your sacrifices pleasing unto me. ^21Therefore thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will lay stumbling-blocks before this people; and the fathers and the sons together shall stumble against them; the neighbor and his friend shall perish. ^22Thus saith Jehovah, Behold, a people cometh from the north country; and a great nation shall be stirred up from the uttermost parts of the earth. ^23They lay hold on bow and spear; they are cruel, and have no mercy; their voice roareth like the sea, and they ride upon horses, every one set in array, as a man to the battle, against thee, O daughter of Zion. ^24We have heard the report thereof; our hands wax feeble: anguish hath taken hold of us, and pangs as of a woman in travail. ^25Go not forth into the field, nor walk by the way; for the sword of the enemy, and terror, are on every side. ^26O daughter of my people, gird thee with sackcloth, and wallow thyself in ashes: make thee mourning, as for an only son, most bitter lamentation; for the destroyer shall suddenly come upon us. ^27I have made thee a trier and a fortress among my people; that thou mayest know and try their way. ^28They are all grievous revolters, going about with slanders; they are brass and iron: they all of them deal corruptly. ^29The bellows blow fiercely; the lead is consumed of the fire: in vain do they go on refining; for the wicked are not plucked away. ^30Refuse silver shall men them, because Jehovah hath rejected them.

Jeremiah 7

7

^1The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying, ^2Stand in the gate of Jehovah's house, and proclaim there this word, and say, Hear the word of Jehovah, all ye of Judah, that enter in at these gates to worship Jehovah. ^3Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, Amend your ways and your doings, and I will cause you to dwell in this place. ^4Trust ye not in lying words, saying, The temple of Jehovah, the temple of Jehovah, the temple of Jehovah, are these. ^5For if ye thoroughly amend your ways and your doings; if ye thoroughly execute justice between a man and his neighbor; ^6if ye oppress not the sojourner, the fatherless, and the widow, and shed not innocent blood in this place, neither walk after other gods to your own hurt: ^7then will I cause you to dwell in this place, in the land that I gave to your fathers, from of old even for evermore. ^8Behold, ye trust in lying words, that cannot profit. ^9Will ye steal, murder, and commit adultery, and swear falsely, and burn incense unto Baal, and walk after other gods that ye have not known, ^10and come and stand before me in this house, which is called by my name, and say, We are delivered; that ye may do all these abominations? ^11Is this house, which is called by my name, become a den of robbers in your eyes? Behold, I, even I, have seen it, saith Jehovah. ^12But go ye now unto my place which was in Shiloh, where I caused my name to dwell at the first, and see what I did to it for the wickedness of my people Israel. ^13And now, because ye have done all these works, saith Jehovah, and I spake unto you, rising up early and speaking, but ye heard not; and I called you, but ye answered not: ^14therefore will I do unto the house which is called by my name, wherein ye trust, and unto the place which I gave to you and to your fathers, as I did to Shiloh. ^15And I will cast you out of my sight, as I have cast out all your brethren, even the whole seed of Ephraim. ^16Therefore pray not thou for this people, neither lift up cry nor prayer for them, neither make intercession to me; for I will not hear thee. ^17Seest thou not what they do in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem? ^18The children gather wood, and the fathers kindle the fire, and the women knead the dough, to make cakes to the queen of heaven, and to pour out drink-offerings unto other gods, that they may provoke me to anger. ^19Do they provoke me to anger? saith Jehovah; do they not provoke themselves, to the confusion of their own faces? ^20Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, mine anger and my wrath shall be poured out upon this place, upon man, and upon beast, and upon the trees of the field, and upon the fruit of the ground; and it shall burn, and shall not be quenched. ^21Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Add your burnt-offerings unto your sacrifices, and eat ye flesh. ^22For I spake not unto your fathers, nor commanded them in the day that I brought them out of the land of Egypt, concerning burnt-offerings or sacrifices: ^23but this thing I commanded them, saying, Hearken unto my voice, and I will be your God, and ye shall be my people; and walk ye in all the way that I command you, that it may be well with you. ^24But they hearkened not, nor inclined their ear, but walked in their own counsels and in the stubbornness of their evil heart, and went backward, and not forward. ^25Since the day that your fathers came forth out of the land of Egypt unto this day, I have sent unto you all my servants the prophets, daily rising up early and sending them: ^26yet they hearkened not unto me, nor inclined their ear, but made their neck stiff: they did worse than their fathers. ^27And thou shalt speak all these words unto them; but they will not hearken to thee: thou shalt also call unto them; but they will not answer thee. ^28And thou shalt say unto them, This is the nation that hath not hearkened to the voice of Jehovah their God, nor received instruction: truth is perished, and is cut off from their mouth. ^29Cut off thy hair, O Jerusalem, and cast it away, and take up a lamentation on the bare heights; for Jehovah hath rejected and forsaken the generation of his wrath. ^30For the children of Judah have done that which is evil in my sight, saith Jehovah: they have set their abominations in the house which is called by my name, to defile it. ^31And they have built the high places of Topheth, which is in the valley of the son of Hinnom, to burn their sons and their daughters in the fire; which I commanded not, neither came it into my mind. ^32Therefore, behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that it shall no more be called Topheth, nor The valley of the son of Hinnom, but The valley of Slaughter: for they shall bury in Topheth, till there be no place to bury. ^33And the dead bodies of this people shall be food for the birds of the heavens, and for the beasts of the earth; and none shall frighten them away. ^34Then will I cause to cease from the cities of Judah, and from the streets of Jerusalem, the voice of mirth and the voice of gladness, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride; for the land shall become a waste.

Jeremiah 8

8

^1At that time, saith Jehovah, they shall bring out the bones of the kings of Judah, and the bones of his princes, and the bones of the priests, and the bones of the prophets, and the bones of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, out of their graves; ^2and they shall spread them before the sun, and the moon, and all the host of heaven, which they have loved, and which they have served, and after which they have walked, and which they have sought, and which they have worshipped: they shall not be gathered, nor be buried, they shall be for dung upon the face of the earth. ^3And death shall be chosen rather than life by all the residue that remain of this evil family, that remain in all the places whither I have driven them, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^4Moreover thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith Jehovah: Shall men fall, and not rise up again? Shall one turn away, and not return? ^5Why then is this people of Jerusalem slidden back by a perpetual backsliding? they hold fast deceit, they refuse to return. ^6I hearkened and heard, but they spake not aright: no man repenteth him of his wickedness, saying, What have I done? every one turneth to his course, as a horse that rusheth headlong in the battle. ^7Yea, the stork in the heavens knoweth her appointed times; and the turtle-dove and the swallow and the crane observe the time of their coming; but my people know not the law of Jehovah. ^8How do ye say, We are wise, and the law of Jehovah is with us? But, behold, the false pen of the scribes hath wrought falsely. ^9The wise men are put to shame, they are dismayed and taken: lo, they have rejected the word of Jehovah; and what manner of wisdom is in them? ^10Therefore will I give their wives unto others, and their fields to them that shall possess them: for every one from the least even unto the greatest is given to covetousness; from the prophet even unto the priest every one dealeth falsely. ^11And they have healed the hurt of the daughter of my people slightly, saying, Peace, peace; when there is no peace. ^12Were they ashamed when they had committed abomination? nay, they were not at all ashamed, neither could they blush: therefore shall they fall among them that fall; in the time of their visitation they shall be cast down, saith Jehovah. ^13I will utterly consume them, saith Jehovah: there shall be no grapes on the vine, nor figs on the fig-tree, and the leaf shall fade; and the things that I have given them shall pass away from them. ^14Why do we sit still? assemble yourselves, and let us enter into the fortified cities, and let us be silent there; for Jehovah our God hath put us to silence, and given us water of gall to drink, because we have sinned against Jehovah. ^15We looked for peace, but no good came; and for a time of healing, and, behold, dismay! ^16The snorting of his horses is heard from Dan: at the sound of the neighing of his strong ones the whole land trembleth; for they are come, and have devoured the land and all that is in it; the city and those that dwell therein. ^17For, behold, I will send serpents, adders, among you, which will not be charmed; and they shall bite you, saith Jehovah. ^18Oh that I could comfort myself against sorrow! my heart is faint within me. ^19Behold, the voice of the cry of the daughter of my people from a land that is very far off: is not Jehovah in Zion? is not her King in her? Why have they provoked me to anger with their graven images, and with foreign vanities? ^20The harvest is past, the summer is ended, and we are not saved. ^21For the hurt of the daughter of my people am I hurt: I mourn; dismay hath taken hold on me. ^22Is there no balm in Gilead? is there no physician there? why then is not the health of the daughter of my people recovered?

Jeremiah 9

9

^1Oh that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for the slain of the daughter of my people! ^2Oh that I had in the wilderness a lodging-place of wayfaring men; that I might leave my people, and go from them! for they are all adulterers, an assembly of treacherous men. ^3And they bend their tongue, as it were their bow, for falsehood; and they are grown strong in the land, but not for truth: for they proceed from evil to evil, and they know not me, saith Jehovah. ^4Take ye heed every one of his neighbor, and trust ye not in any brother; for every brother will utterly supplant, and every neighbor will go about with slanders. ^5And they will deceive every one his neighbor, and will not speak the truth: they have taught their tongue to speak lies; they weary themselves to commit iniquity. ^6Thy habitation is in the midst of deceit; through deceit they refuse to know me, saith Jehovah. ^7Therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts, Behold, I will melt them, and try them; for how else should I do, because of the daughter of my people? ^8Their tongue is a deadly arrow; it speaketh deceit: one speaketh peaceably to his neighbor with his mouth, but in his heart he layeth wait for him. ^9Shall I not visit them for these things? saith Jehovah; shall not my soul be avenged on such a nation as this? ^10For the mountains will I take up a weeping and wailing, and for the pastures of the wilderness a lamentation, because they are burned up, so that none passeth through; neither can men hear the voice of the cattle; both the birds of the heavens and the beasts are fled, they are gone. ^11And I will make Jerusalem heaps, a dwelling-place of jackals; and I will make the cities of Judah a desolation, without inhabitant. ^12Who is the wise man, that may understand this? and who is he to whom the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken, that he may declare it? wherefore is the land perished and burned up like a wilderness, so that none passeth through? ^13And Jehovah saith, Because they have forsaken my law which I set before them, and have not obeyed my voice, neither walked therein, ^14but have walked after the stubbornness of their own heart, and after the Baalim, which their fathers taught them; ^15therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, Behold, I will feed them, even this people, with wormwood, and give them water of gall to drink. ^16I will scatter them also among the nations, whom neither they nor their fathers have known; and I will send the sword after them, till I have consumed them. ^17Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, Consider ye, and call for the mourning women, that they may come; and send for the skilful women, that they may come: ^18and let them make haste, and take up a wailing for us, that our eyes may run down with tears, and our eyelids gush out with waters. ^19For a voice of wailing is heard out of Zion, How are we ruined! we are greatly confounded, because we have forsaken the land, because they have cast down our dwellings. ^20Yet hear the word of Jehovah, O ye women, and let your ear receive the word of his mouth; and teach your daughters wailing, and every one her neighbor lamentation. ^21For death is come up into our windows, it is entered into our palaces; to cut off the children from without, and the young men from the streets. ^22Speak, Thus saith Jehovah, The dead bodies of men shall fall as dung upon the open field, and as the handful after the harvestman; and none shall gather them. ^23Thus saith Jehovah, Let not the wise man glory in his wisdom, neither let the mighty man glory in his might, let not the rich man glory in his riches; ^24but let him that glorieth glory in this, that he hath understanding, and knoweth me, that I am Jehovah who exerciseth lovingkindness, justice, and righteousness, in the earth: for in these things I delight, saith Jehovah. ^25Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will punish all them that are circumcised in their uncircumcision: ^26Egypt, and Judah, and Edom, and the children of Ammon, and Moab, and all that have the corners of their hair cut off, that dwell in the wilderness; for all the nations are uncircumcised, and all the house of Israel are uncircumcised in heart.

Jeremiah 10

10

^1Hear ye the word which Jehovah speaketh unto you, O house of Israel: ^2thus saith Jehovah, Learn not the way of the nations, and be not dismayed at the signs of heaven; for the nations are dismayed at them. ^3For the customs of the peoples are vanity; for one cutteth a tree out of the forest, the work of the hands of the workman with the axe. ^4They deck it with silver and with gold; they fasten it with nails and with hammers, that it move not. ^5They are like a palm-tree, of turned work, and speak not: they must needs be borne, because they cannot go. Be not afraid of them; for they cannot do evil, neither is it in them to do good. ^6There is none like unto thee, O Jehovah; thou art great, and thy name is great in might. ^7Who should not fear thee, O King of the nations? for to thee doth it appertain; forasmuch as among all the wise men of the nations, and in all their royal estate, there is none like unto thee. ^8But they are together brutish and foolish: the instruction of idols! it is but a stock. ^9There is silver beaten into plates, which is brought from Tarshish, and gold from Uphaz, the work of the artificer and of the hands of the goldsmith; blue and purple for their clothing; they are all the work of skilful men. ^10But Jehovah is the true God; he is the living God, and an everlasting King: at his wrath the earth trembleth, and the nations are not able to abide his indignation. ^11Thus shall ye say unto them, The gods that have not made the heavens and the earth, these shall perish from the earth, and from under the heavens. ^12He hath made the earth by his power, he hath established the world by his wisdom, and by his understanding hath he stretched out the heavens: ^13when he uttereth his voice, there is a tumult of waters in the heavens, and he causeth the vapors to ascend from the ends of the earth; he maketh lightnings for the rain, and bringeth forth the wind out of his treasuries. ^14Every man is become brutish and is without knowledge; every goldsmith is put to shame by his graven image; for his molten image is falsehood, and there is no breath in them. ^15They are vanity, a work of delusion: in the time of their visitation they shall perish. ^16The portion of Jacob is not like these; for he is the former of all things; and Israel is the tribe of his inheritance: Jehovah of hosts is his name. ^17Gather up thy wares out of the land, O thou that abidest in the siege. ^18For thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will sling out the inhabitants of the land at this time, and will distress them, that they may feel it. ^19Woe is me because of my hurt! my wound is grievous: but I said, Truly this is my grief, and I must bear it. ^20My tent is destroyed, and all my cords are broken: my children are gone forth from me, and they are not: there is none to spread my tent any more, and to set up my curtains. ^21For the shepherds are become brutish, and have not inquired of Jehovah: therefore they have not prospered, and all their flocks are scattered. ^22The voice of tidings, behold, it cometh, and a great commotion out of the north country, to make the cities of Judah a desolation, a dwelling-place of jackals. ^23O Jehovah, I know that the way of man is not in himself: it is not in man that walketh to direct his steps. ^24O Jehovah, correct me, but in measure: not in thine anger, lest thou bring me to nothing. ^25Pour out thy wrath upon the nations that know thee not, and upon the families that call not on thy name: for they have devoured Jacob, yea, they have devoured him and consumed him, and have laid waste his habitation.

Jeremiah 11

11

^1The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying, ^2Hear ye the words of this covenant, and speak unto the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem; ^3and say thou unto them, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel: Cursed be the man that heareth not the words of this covenant, ^4which I commanded your fathers in the day that I brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, out of the iron furnace, saying, Obey my voice, and do them, according to all which I command you: so shall ye be my people, and I will be your God; ^5that I may establish the oath which I sware unto your fathers, to give them a land flowing with milk and honey, as at this day. Then answered I, and said, Amen, O Jehovah. ^6And Jehovah said unto me, Proclaim all these words in the cities of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem, saying, Hear ye the words of this covenant, and do them. ^7For I earnestly protested unto your fathers in the day that I brought them up out of the land of Egypt, even unto this day, rising early and protesting, saying, Obey my voice. ^8Yet they obeyed not, nor inclined their ear, but walked every one in the stubbornness of their evil heart: therefore I brought upon them all the words of this covenant, which I commanded them to do, but they did them not. ^9And Jehovah said unto me, A conspiracy is found among the men of Judah, and among the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^10They are turned back to the iniquities of their forefathers, who refused to hear my words; and they are gone after other gods to serve them: the house of Israel and the house of Judah have broken my covenant which I made with their fathers. ^11Therefore thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will bring evil upon them, which they shall not be able to escape; and they shall cry unto me, but I will not hearken unto them. ^12Then shall the cities of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem go and cry unto the gods unto which they offer incense: but they will not save them at all in the time of their trouble. ^13For according to the number of thy cities are thy gods, O Judah; and according to the number of the streets of Jerusalem have ye set up altars to the shameful thing, even altars to burn incense unto Baal. ^14Therefore pray not thou for this people, neither lift up cry nor prayer for them; for I will not hear them in the time that they cry unto me because of their trouble. ^15What hath my beloved to do in my house, seeing she hath wrought lewdness with many, and the holy flesh is passed from thee? when thou doest evil, then thou rejoicest. ^16Jehovah called thy name, A green olive-tree, fair with goodly fruit: with the noise of a great tumult he hath kindled fire upon it, and the branches of it are broken. ^17For Jehovah of hosts, who planted thee, hath pronounced evil against thee, because of the evil of the house of Israel and of the house of Judah, which they have wrought for themselves in provoking me to anger by offering incense unto Baal. ^18And Jehovah gave me knowledge of it, and I knew it: then thou showedst me their doings. ^19But I was like a gentle lamb that is led to the slaughter; and I knew not that they had devised devices against me, saying, Let us destroy the tree with the fruit thereof, and let us cut him off from the land of the living, that his name may be no more remembered. ^20But, O Jehovah of hosts, who judgest righteously, who triest the heart and the mind, I shall see thy vengeance on them; for unto thee have I revealed my cause. ^21Therefore thus saith Jehovah concerning the men of Anathoth, that seek thy life, saying, Thou shalt not prophesy in the name of Jehovah, that thou die not by our hand; ^22therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts, Behold, I will punish them: the young men shall die by the sword; their sons and their daughters shall die by famine; ^23and there shall be no remnant unto them: for I will bring evil upon the men of Anathoth, even the year of their visitation.

Jeremiah 12

12

^1Righteous art thou, O Jehovah, when I contend with thee; yet would I reason the cause with thee: wherefore doth the way of the wicked prosper? wherefore are all they at ease that deal very treacherously? ^2Thou hast planted them, yea, they have taken root; they grow, yea, they bring forth fruit: thou art near in their mouth, and far from their heart. ^3But thou, O Jehovah, knowest me; thou seest me, and triest my heart toward thee: pull them out like sheep for the slaughter, and prepare them for the day of slaughter. ^4How long shall the land mourn, and the herbs of the whole country wither? for the wickedness of them that dwell therein, the beasts are consumed, and the birds; because they said, He shall not see our latter end. ^5If thou hast run with the footmen, and they have wearied thee, then how canst thou contend with horses? and though in a land of peace thou art secure, yet how wilt thou do in the pride of the Jordan? ^6For even thy brethren, and the house of thy father, even they have dealt treacherously with thee; even they have cried aloud after thee: believe them not, though they speak fair words unto thee. ^7I have forsaken my house, I have cast off my heritage; I have given the dearly beloved of my soul into the hand of her enemies. ^8My heritage is become unto me as a lion in the forest: she hath uttered her voice against me; therefore I have hated her. ^9Is my heritage unto me as a speckled bird of prey? are the birds of prey against her round about? go ye, assemble all the beasts of the field, bring them to devour. ^10Many shepherds have destroyed my vineyard, they have trodden my portion under foot, they have made my pleasant portion a desolate wilderness. ^11They have made it a desolation; it mourneth unto me, being desolate; the whole land is made desolate, because no man layeth it to heart. ^12Destroyers are come upon all the bare heights in the wilderness; for the sword of Jehovah devoureth from the one end of the land even to the other end of the land: no flesh hath peace. ^13They have sown wheat, and have reaped thorns; they have put themselves to pain, and profit nothing: and ye shall be ashamed of your fruits, because of the fierce anger of Jehovah. ^14Thus saith Jehovah against all mine evil neighbors, that touch the inheritance which I have caused my people Israel to inherit: behold, I will pluck them up from off their land, and will pluck up the house of Judah from among them. ^15And it shall come to pass, after that I have plucked them up, I will return and have compassion on them; and I will bring them again, every man to his heritage, and every man to his land. ^16And it shall come to pass, if they will diligently learn the ways of my people, to swear by my name, As Jehovah liveth; even as they taught my people to swear by Baal; then shall they be built up in the midst of my people. ^17But if they will not hear, then will I pluck up that nation, plucking up and destroying it, saith Jehovah.

Jeremiah 13

13

^1Thus saith Jehovah unto me, Go, and buy thee a linen girdle, and put it upon thy loins, and put it not in water. ^2So I bought a girdle according to the word of Jehovah, and put it upon my loins. ^3And the word of Jehovah came unto me the second time, saying, ^4Take the girdle that thou hast bought, which is upon thy loins, and arise, go to the Euphrates, and hide it there in a cleft of the rock. ^5So I went, and hid it by the Euphrates, as Jehovah commanded me. ^6And it came to pass after many days, that Jehovah said unto me, Arise, go to the Euphrates, and take the girdle from thence, which I commanded thee to hide there. ^7Then I went to the Euphrates, and digged, and took the girdle from the place where I had hid it; and, behold, the girdle was marred, it was profitable for nothing. ^8Then the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^9Thus saith Jehovah, After this manner will I mar the pride of Judah, and the great pride of Jerusalem. ^10This evil people, that refuse to hear my words, that walk in the stubbornness of their heart, and are gone after other gods to serve them, and to worship them, shall even be as this girdle, which is profitable for nothing. ^11For as the girdle cleaveth to the loins of a man, so have I caused to cleave unto me the whole house of Israel and the whole house of Judah, saith Jehovah; that they may be unto me for a people, and for a name, and for a praise, and for a glory: but they would not hear. ^12Therefore thou shalt speak unto them this word: Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Every bottle shall be filled with wine: and they shall say unto thee, Do we not certainly know that every bottle shall be filled with wine? ^13Then shalt thou say unto them, Thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will fill all the inhabitants of this land, even the kings that sit upon David's throne, and the priests, and the prophets, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, with drunkenness. ^14And I will dash them one against another, even the fathers and the sons together, saith Jehovah: I will not pity, nor spare, nor have compassion, that I should not destroy them. ^15Hear ye, and give ear; be not proud; for Jehovah hath spoken. ^16Give glory to Jehovah your God, before he cause darkness, and before your feet stumble upon the dark mountains, and, while ye look for light, he turn it into the shadow of death, and make it gross darkness. ^17But if ye will not hear it, my soul shall weep in secret for your pride; and mine eye shall weep sore, and run down with tears, because Jehovah's flock is taken captive. ^18Say thou unto the king and to the queen-mother, Humble yourselves, sit down; for your headtires are come down, even the crown of your glory. ^19The cities of the South are shut up, and there is none to open them: Judah is carried away captive, all of it; it is wholly carried away captive. ^20Lift up your eyes, and behold them that come from the north: where is the flock that was given thee, thy beautiful flock? ^21What wilt thou say, when he shall set over thee as head those whom thou hast thyself taught to be friends to thee? shall not sorrows take hold of thee, as of a woman in travail? ^22And if thou say in thy heart, Wherefore are these things come upon me? for the greatness of thine iniquity are thy skirts uncovered, and thy heels suffer violence. ^23Can the Ethiopian change his skin, or the leopard his spots? then may ye also do good, that are accustomed to do evil. ^24Therefore will I scatter them, as the stubble that passeth away, by the wind of the wilderness. ^25This is thy lot, the portion measured unto thee from me, saith Jehovah; because thou hast forgotten me, and trusted in falsehood. ^26Therefore will I also uncover thy skirts upon thy face, and thy shame shall appear. ^27I have seen thine abominations, even thine adulteries, and thy neighings, the lewdness of thy whoredom, on the hills in the field. Woe unto thee, O Jerusalem! thou wilt not be made clean; how long shall it yet be?

Jeremiah 14

14

^1The word of Jehovah that came to Jeremiah concerning the drought. ^2Judah mourneth, and the gates thereof languish, they sit in black upon the ground; and the cry of Jerusalem is gone up. ^3And their nobles send their little ones to the waters: they come to the cisterns, and find no water; they return with their vessels empty; they are put to shame and confounded, and cover their heads. ^4Because of the ground which is cracked, for that no rain hath been in the land, the plowmen are put to shame, they cover their heads. ^5Yea, the hind also in the field calveth, and forsaketh her young, because there is no grass. ^6And the wild asses stand on the bare heights, they pant for air like jackals; their eyes fail, because there is no herbage. ^7Though our iniquities testify against us, work thou for thy name's sake, O Jehovah; for our backslidings are many; we have sinned against thee. ^8O thou hope of Israel, the Saviour thereof in the time of trouble, why shouldest thou be as a sojourner in the land, and as a wayfaring man that turneth aside to tarry for a night? ^9Why shouldest thou be as a man affrighted, as a mighty man that cannot save? yet thou, O Jehovah, art in the midst of us, and we are called by thy name; leave us not. ^10Thus saith Jehovah unto this people, Even so have they loved to wander; they have not refrained their feet: therefore Jehovah doth not accept them; now will he remember their iniquity, and visit their sins. ^11And Jehovah said unto me, Pray not for this people for their good. ^12When they fast, I will not hear their cry; and when they offer burnt-offering and meal-offering, I will not accept them; but I will consume them by the sword, and by the famine, and by the pestilence. ^13Then said I, Ah, Lord Jehovah! behold, the prophets say unto them, Ye shall not see the sword, neither shall ye have famine; but I will give you assured peace in this place. ^14Then Jehovah said unto me, The prophets prophesy lies in my name; I sent them not, neither have I commanded them, neither spake I unto them: they prophesy unto you a lying vision, and divination, and a thing of nought, and the deceit of their own heart. ^15Therefore thus saith Jehovah concerning the prophets that prophesy in my name, and I sent them not, yet they say, Sword and famine shall not be in this land: By sword and famine shall those prophets be consumed. ^16And the people to whom they prophesy shall be cast out in the streets of Jerusalem because of the famine and the sword; and they shall have none to bury them-them, their wives, nor their sons, nor their daughters: for I will pour their wickedness upon them. ^17And thou shalt say this word unto them, Let mine eyes run down with tears night and day, and let them not cease; for the virgin daughter of my people is broken with a great breach, with a very grievous wound. ^18If I go forth into the field, then, behold, the slain with the sword! and if I enter into the city, then, behold, they that are sick with famine! for both the prophet and the priest go about in the land, and have no knowledge. ^19Hast thou utterly rejected Judah? hath thy soul loathed Zion? why hast thou smitten us, and there is no healing for us? We looked for peace, but no good came; and for a time of healing, and, behold, dismay! ^20We acknowledge, O Jehovah, our wickedness, and the iniquity of our fathers; for we have sinned against thee. ^21Do not abhor us, for thy name's sake; do not disgrace the throne of thy glory: remember, break not thy covenant with us. ^22Are there any among the vanities of the nations that can cause rain? or can the heavens give showers? art not thou he, O Jehovah our God? therefore we will wait for thee; for thou hast made all these things.

Jeremiah 15

15

^1Then said Jehovah unto me, Though Moses and Samuel stood before me, yet my mind would not be toward this people: cast them out of my sight, and let them go forth. ^2And it shall come to pass, when they say unto thee, Whither shall we go forth? then thou shalt tell them, Thus saith Jehovah: Such as are for death, to death; and such as are for the sword, to the sword; and such as are for the famine, to the famine; and such as are for captivity, to captivity. ^3And I will appoint over them four kinds, saith Jehovah: the sword to slay, and the dogs to tear, and the birds of the heavens, and the beasts of the earth, to devour and to destroy. ^4And I will cause them to be tossed to and fro among all the kingdoms of the earth, because of Manasseh, the son of Hezekiah, king of Judah, for that which he did in Jerusalem. ^5For who will have pity upon thee, O Jerusalem? or who will bemoan thee? or who will turn aside to ask of thy welfare? ^6Thou hast rejected me, saith Jehovah, thou art gone backward: therefore have I stretched out my hand against thee, and destroyed thee; I am weary with repenting. ^7And I have winnowed them with a fan in the gates of the land; I have bereaved them of children, I have destroyed my people; they returned not from their ways. ^8Their widows are increased to me above the sand of the seas; I have brought upon them against the mother of the young men a destroyer at noonday: I have caused anguish and terrors to fall upon her suddenly. ^9She that hath borne seven languisheth; she hath given up the ghost; her sun is gone down while it was yet day; she hath been put to shame and confounded: and the residue of them will I deliver to the sword before their enemies, saith Jehovah. ^10Woe is me, my mother, that thou hast borne me a man of strife and a man of contention to the whole earth! I have not lent, neither have men lent to me; yet every one of them doth curse me. ^11Jehovah said, Verily I will strengthen thee for good; verily I will cause the enemy to make supplication unto thee in the time of evil and in the time of affliction. ^12Can one break iron, even iron from the north, and brass? ^13Thy substance and thy treasures will I give for a spoil without price, and that for all thy sins, even in all thy borders. ^14And I will make them to pass with thine enemies into a land which thou knowest not; for a fire is kindled in mine anger, which shall burn upon you. ^15O Jehovah, thou knowest; remember me, and visit me, and avenge me of my persecutors; take me not away in thy longsuffering: know that for thy sake I have suffered reproach. ^16Thy words were found, and I did eat them; and thy words were unto me a joy and the rejoicing of my heart: for I am called by thy name, O Jehovah, God of hosts. ^17I sat not in the assembly of them that make merry, nor rejoiced; I sat alone because of thy hand; for thou hast filled me with indignation. ^18Why is my pain perpetual, and my wound incurable, which refuseth to be healed? wilt thou indeed be unto me as a deceitful brook, as waters that fail? ^19Therefore thus saith Jehovah, If thou return, then will I bring thee again, that thou mayest stand before me; and if thou take forth the precious from the vile, thou shalt be as my mouth: they shall return unto thee, but thou shalt not return unto them. ^20And I will make thee unto this people a fortified brazen wall; and they shall fight against thee, but they shall not prevail against thee; for I am with thee to save thee and to deliver thee, saith Jehovah. ^21And I will deliver thee out of the hand of the wicked, and I will redeem thee out of the hand of the terrible.

Jeremiah 16

16

^1The word of Jehovah came also unto me, saying, ^2Thou shalt not take thee a wife, neither shalt thou have sons or daughters, in this place. ^3For thus saith Jehovah concerning the sons and concerning the daughters that are born in this place, and concerning their mothers that bare them, and concerning their fathers that begat them in this land: ^4They shall die grievous deaths: they shall not be lamented, neither shall they be buried; they shall be as dung upon the face of the ground; and they shall be consumed by the sword, and by famine; and their dead bodies shall be food for the birds of the heavens, and for the beasts of the earth. ^5For thus saith Jehovah, Enter not into the house of mourning, neither go to lament, neither bemoan them; for I have taken away my peace from this people, saith Jehovah, even lovingkindness and tender mercies. ^6Both great and small shall die in this land; they shall not be buried, neither shall men lament for them, nor cut themselves, nor make themselves bald for them; ^7neither shall men break bread for them in mourning, to comfort them for the dead; neither shall men give them the cup of consolation to drink for their father or for their mother. ^8And thou shalt not go into the house of feasting to sit with them, to eat and to drink. ^9For thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will cause to cease out of this place, before your eyes and in your days, the voice of mirth and the voice of gladness, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride. ^10And it shall come to pass, when thou shalt show this people all these words, and they shall say unto thee, Wherefore hath Jehovah pronounced all this great evil against us? or what is our iniquity? or what is our sin that we have committed against Jehovah our God? ^11Then shalt thou say unto them, Because your fathers have forsaken me, saith Jehovah, and have walked after other gods, and have served them, and have worshipped them, and have forsaken me, and have not kept my law; ^12and ye have done evil more than your fathers; for, behold, ye walk every one after the stubbornness of his evil heart, so that ye hearken not unto me: ^13therefore will I cast you forth out of this land into the land that ye have not known, neither ye nor your fathers; and there shall ye serve other gods day and night; for I will show you no favor. ^14Therefore, behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that it shall no more be said, As Jehovah liveth, that brought up the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt; ^15but, As Jehovah liveth, that brought up the children of Israel from the land of the north, and from all the countries whither he had driven them. And I will bring them again into their land that I gave unto their fathers. ^16Behold, I will send for many fishers, saith Jehovah, and they shall fish them up; and afterward I will send for many hunters, and they shall hunt them from every mountain, and from every hill, and out of the clefts of the rocks. ^17For mine eyes are upon all their ways; they are not hid from my face, neither is their iniquity concealed from mine eyes. ^18And first I will recompense their iniquity and their sin double, because they have polluted my land with the carcasses of their detestable things, and have filled mine inheritance with their abominations. ^19O Jehovah, my strength, and my stronghold, and my refuge in the day of affliction, unto thee shall the nations come from the ends of the earth, and shall say, Our fathers have inherited nought but lies, even vanity and things wherein there is no profit. ^20Shall a man make unto himself gods, which yet are no gods? ^21Therefore, behold, I will cause them to know, this once will I cause them to know my hand and my might; and they shall know that my name is Jehovah.

Jeremiah 17

17

^1The sin of Judah is written with a pen of iron, and with the point of a diamond: it is graven upon the tablet of their heart, and upon the horns of your altars; ^2whilst their children remember their altars and their Asherim by the green trees upon the high hills. ^3O my mountain in the field, I will give thy substance and all thy treasures for a spoil, and thy high places, because of sin, throughout all thy borders. ^4And thou, even of thyself, shalt discontinue from thy heritage that I gave thee; and I will cause thee to serve thine enemies in the land which thou knowest not: for ye have kindled a fire in mine anger which shall burn for ever. ^5Thus saith Jehovah: Cursed is the man that trusteth in man, and maketh flesh his arm, and whose heart departeth from Jehovah. ^6For he shall be like the heath in the desert, and shall not see when good cometh, but shall inhabit the parched places in the wilderness, a salt land and not inhabited. ^7Blessed is the man that trusteth in Jehovah, and whose trust Jehovah is. ^8For he shall be as a tree planted by the waters, that spreadeth out its roots by the river, and shall not fear when heat cometh, but its leaf shall be green; and shall not be careful in the year of drought, neither shall cease from yielding fruit. ^9The heart is deceitful above all things, and it is exceedingly corrupt: who can know it? ^10I, Jehovah, search the mind, I try the heart, even to give every man according to his ways, according to the fruit of his doings. ^11As the partridge that sitteth on eggs which she hath not laid, so is he that getteth riches, and not by right; in the midst of his days they shall leave him, and at his end he shall be a fool. ^12A glorious throne, set on high from the beginning, is the place of our sanctuary. ^13O Jehovah, the hope of Israel, all that forsake thee shall be put to shame. They that depart from me shall be written in the earth, because they have forsaken Jehovah, the fountain of living waters. ^14Heal me, O Jehovah, and I shall be healed; save me, and I shall be saved: for thou art my praise. ^15Behold, they say unto me, Where is the word of Jehovah? let it come now. ^16As for me, I have not hastened from being a shepherd after thee; neither have I desired the woeful day; thou knowest: that which came out of my lips was before thy face. ^17Be not a terror unto me: thou art my refuge in the day of evil. ^18Let them be put to shame that persecute me, but let not me be put to shame; let them be dismayed, but let not me be dismayed; bring upon them the day of evil, and destroy them with double destruction. ^19Thus said Jehovah unto me: Go, and stand in the gate of the children of the people, whereby the kings of Judah come in, and by which they go out, and in all the gates of Jerusalem; ^20and say unto them, Hear ye the word of Jehovah, ye kings of Judah, and all Judah, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, that enter in by these gates: ^21Thus saith Jehovah, Take heed to yourselves, and bear no burden on the sabbath day, nor bring it in by the gates of Jerusalem; ^22neither carry forth a burden out of your houses on the sabbath day, neither do ye any work: but hallow ye the sabbath day, as I commanded your fathers. ^23But they hearkened not, neither inclined their ear, but made their neck stiff, that they might not hear, and might not receive instruction. ^24And it shall come to pass, if ye diligently hearken unto me, saith Jehovah, to bring in no burden through the gates of this city on the sabbath day, but to hallow the sabbath day, to do no work therein; ^25then shall there enter in by the gates of this city kings and princes sitting upon the throne of David, riding in chariots and on horses, they, and their princes, the men of Judah, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and this city shall remain for ever. ^26And they shall come from the cities of Judah, and from the places round about Jerusalem, and from the land of Benjamin, and from the lowland, and from the hill-country, and from the South, bringing burnt-offerings, and sacrifices, and meal-offerings, and frankincense, and bringing sacrifices of thanksgiving, unto the house of Jehovah. ^27But if ye will not hearken unto me to hallow the sabbath day, and not to bear a burden and enter in at the gates of Jerusalem on the sabbath day; then will I kindle a fire in the gates thereof, and it shall devour the palaces of Jerusalem, and it shall not be quenched.

Jeremiah 18

18

^1The word which came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying, ^2Arise, and go down to the potter's house, and there I will cause thee to hear my words. ^3Then I went down to the potter's house, and, behold, he was making a work on the wheels. ^4And when the vessel that he made of the clay was marred in the hand of the potter, he made it again another vessel, as seemed good to the potter to make it. ^5Then the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, ^6O house of Israel, cannot I do with you as this potter? saith Jehovah. Behold, as the clay in the potter's hand, so are ye in my hand, O house of Israel. ^7At what instant I shall speak concerning a nation, and concerning a kingdom, to pluck up and to break down and to destroy it; ^8if that nation, concerning which I have spoken, turn from their evil, I will repent of the evil that I thought to do unto them. ^9And at what instant I shall speak concerning a nation, and concerning a kingdom, to build and to plant it; ^10if they do that which is evil in my sight, that they obey not my voice, then I will repent of the good, wherewith I said I would benefit them. ^11Now therefore, speak to the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying, Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I frame evil against you, and devise a device against you: return ye now every one from his evil way, and amend your ways and your doings. ^12But they say, It is in vain; for we will walk after our own devices, and we will do every one after the stubbornness of his evil heart. ^13Therefore thus saith Jehovah: Ask ye now among the nations, who hath heard such things; the virgin of Israel hath done a very horrible thing. ^14Shall the snow of Lebanon fail from the rock of the field? or shall the cold waters that flow down from afar be dried up? ^15For my people have forgotten me, they have burned incense to false gods; and they have been made to stumble in their ways, in the ancient paths, to walk in bypaths, in a way not cast up; ^16to make their land an astonishment, and a perpetual hissing; every one that passeth thereby shall be astonished, and shake his head. ^17I will scatter them as with an east wind before the enemy; I will show them the back, and not the face, in the day of their calamity. ^18Then said they, Come, and let us devise devices against Jeremiah; for the law shall not perish from the priest, nor counsel from the wise, nor the word from the prophet. Come, and let us smite him with the tongue, and let us not give heed to any of his words. ^19Give heed to me, O Jehovah, and hearken to the voice of them that contend with me. ^20Shall evil be recompensed for good? for they have digged a pit for my soul. Remember how I stood before thee to speak good for them, to turn away thy wrath from them. ^21Therefore deliver up their children to the famine, and give them over to the power of the sword; and let their wives become childless, and widows; and let their men be slain of death, and their young men smitten of the sword in battle. ^22Let a cry be heard from their houses, when thou shalt bring a troop suddenly upon them; for they have digged a pit to take me, and hid snares for my feet. ^23Yet, Jehovah, thou knowest all their counsel against me to slay me; forgive not their iniquity, neither blot out their sin from thy sight; but let them be overthrown before thee; deal thou with them in the time of thine anger.

Jeremiah 20

20

^1Now Pashhur, the son of Immer the priest, who was chief officer in the house of Jehovah, heard Jeremiah prophesying these things. ^2Then Pashhur smote Jeremiah the prophet, and put him in the stocks that were in the upper gate of Benjamin, which was in the house of Jehovah. ^3And it came to pass on the morrow, that Pashhur brought forth Jeremiah out of the stocks. Then said Jeremiah unto him, Jehovah hath not called thy name Pashhur, but Magor-missabib. ^4For thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will make thee a terror to thyself, and to all thy friends; and they shall fall by the sword of their enemies, and thine eyes shall behold it; and I will give all Judah into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall carry them captive to Babylon, and shall slay them with the sword. ^5Moreover I will give all the riches of this city, and all the gains thereof, and all the precious things thereof, yea, all the treasures of the kings of Judah will I give into the hand of their enemies; and they shall make them a prey, and take them, and carry them to Babylon. ^6And thou, Pashhur, and all that dwell in thy house shall go into captivity; and thou shalt come to Babylon, and there thou shalt die, and there shalt thou be buried, thou, and all thy friends, to whom thou hast prophesied falsely. ^7O Jehovah, thou hast persuaded me, and I was persuaded; thou art stronger than I, and hast prevailed: I am become a laughing-stock all the day, every one mocketh me. ^8For as often as I speak, I cry out; I cry, Violence and destruction! because the word of Jehovah is made a reproach unto me, and a derision, all the day. ^9And if I say, I will not make mention of him, nor speak any more in his name, then there is in my heart as it were a burning fire shut up in my bones, and I am weary with forbearing, and I cannot contain. ^10For I have heard the defaming of many, terror on every side. Denounce, and we will denounce him, say all my familiar friends, they that watch for my fall; peradventure he will be persuaded, and we shall prevail against him, and we shall take our revenge on him. ^11But Jehovah is with me as a mighty one and a terrible: therefore my persecutors shall stumble, and they shall not prevail; they shall be utterly put to shame, because they have not dealt wisely, even with an everlasting dishonor which shall never be forgotten. ^12But, O Jehovah of hosts, that triest the righteous, that seest the heart and the mind, let me see thy vengeance on them; for unto thee have I revealed my cause. ^13Sing unto Jehovah, praise ye Jehovah; for he hath delivered the soul of the needy from the hand of evil-doers. ^14Cursed be the day wherein I was born: let not the day wherein my mother bare me be blessed. ^15Cursed be the man who brought tidings to my father, saying, A man-child is born unto thee; making him very glad. ^16And let that man be as the cities which Jehovah overthrew, and repented not: and let him hear a cry in the morning, and shouting at noontime; ^17because he slew me not from the womb; and so my mother would have been my grave, and her womb always great. ^18Wherefore came I forth out of the womb to see labor and sorrow, that my days should be consumed with shame?

Jeremiah 21

21

^1The word which came unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, when king Zedekiah sent unto him Pashhur the son of Malchijah, and Zephaniah the son of Maaseiah, the priest, saying, ^2Inquire, I pray thee, of Jehovah for us; for Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon maketh war against us: peradventure Jehovah will deal with us according to all his wondrous works, that he may go up from us. ^3Then said Jeremiah unto them, Thus shall ye say to Zedekiah: ^4Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Behold, I will turn back the weapons of war that are in your hands, wherewith ye fight against the king of Babylon, and against the Chaldeans that besiege you, without the walls; and I will gather them into the midst of this city. ^5And I myself will fight against you with an outstretched hand and with a strong arm, even in anger, and in wrath, and in great indignation. ^6And I will smite the inhabitants of this city, both man and beast: they shall die of a great pestilence. ^7And afterward, saith Jehovah, I will deliver Zedekiah king of Judah, and his servants, and the people, even such as are left in this city from the pestilence, from the sword, and from the famine, into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of their enemies, and into the hand of those that seek their life: and he shall smite them with the edge of the sword; he shall not spare them, neither have pity, nor have mercy. ^8And unto this people thou shalt say, Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I set before you the way of life and the way of death. ^9He that abideth in this city shall die by the sword, and by the famine, and by the pestilence; but he that goeth out, and passeth over to the Chaldeans that besiege you, he shall live, and his life shall be unto him for a prey. ^10For I have set my face upon this city for evil, and not for good, saith Jehovah: it shall be given into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall burn it with fire. ^11And touching the house of the king of Judah, hear ye the word of Jehovah: ^12O house of David, thus saith Jehovah, Execute justice in the morning, and deliver him that is robbed out of the hand of the oppressor, lest my wrath go forth like fire, and burn so that none can quench it, because of the evil of your doings. ^13Behold, I am against thee, O inhabitant of the valley, and of the rock of the plain, saith Jehovah; you that say, Who shall come down against us? or who shall enter into our habitations? ^14And I will punish you according to the fruit of your doings, saith Jehovah; and I will kindle a fire in her forest, and it shall devour all that is round about her.

Jeremiah 22

22

^1Thus said Jehovah: Go down to the house of the king of Judah, and speak there this word, ^2And say, Hear the word of Jehovah, O king of Judah, that sittest upon the throne of David, thou, and thy servants, and thy people that enter in by these gates. ^3Thus saith Jehovah: Execute ye justice and righteousness, and deliver him that is robbed out of the hand of the oppressor: and do no wrong, do no violence, to the sojourner, the fatherless, nor the widow; neither shed innocent blood in this place. ^4For if ye do this thing indeed, then shall there enter in by the gates of this house kings sitting upon the throne of David, riding in chariots and on horses, he, and his servants, and his people. ^5But if ye will not hear these words, I swear by myself, saith Jehovah, that this house shall become a desolation. ^6For thus saith Jehovah concerning the house of the king of Judah: Thou art Gilead unto me, and the head of Lebanon; yet surely I will make thee a wilderness, and cities which are not inhabited. ^7And I will prepare destroyers against thee, every one with his weapons; and they shall cut down thy choice cedars, and cast them into the fire. ^8And many nations shall pass by this city, and they shall say every man to his neighbor, Wherefore hath Jehovah done thus unto this great city? ^9Then they shall answer, Because they forsook the covenant of Jehovah their God, and worshipped other gods, and served them. ^10Weep ye not for the dead, neither bemoan him; but weep sore for him that goeth away; for he shall return no more, nor see his native country. ^11For thus saith Jehovah touching Shallum the son of Josiah, king of Judah, who reigned instead of Josiah his father, and who went forth out of this place: He shall not return thither any more. ^12But in the place whither they have led him captive, there shall he die, and he shall see this land no more. ^13Woe unto him that buildeth his house by unrighteousness, and his chambers by injustice; that useth his neighbor's service without wages, and giveth him not his hire; ^14that saith, I will build me a wide house and spacious chambers, and cutteth him out windows; and it is ceiled with cedar, and painted with vermilion. ^15Shalt thou reign, because thou strivest to excel in cedar? Did not thy father eat and drink, and do justice and righteousness? then it was well with him. ^16He judged the cause of the poor and needy; then it was well. Was not this to know me? saith Jehovah. ^17But thine eyes and thy heart are not but for thy covetousness, and for shedding innocent blood, and for oppression, and for violence, to do it. ^18Therefore thus saith Jehovah concerning Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah: they shall not lament for him, saying, Ah my brother! or, Ah sister! They shall not lament for him, saying Ah lord! or, Ah his glory! ^19He shall be buried with the burial of an ass, drawn and cast forth beyond the gates of Jerusalem. ^20Go up to Lebanon, and cry; and lift up thy voice in Bashan, and cry from Abarim; for all thy lovers are destroyed. ^21I spake unto thee in thy prosperity; but thou saidst, I will not hear. This hath been thy manner from thy youth, that thou obeyedst not my voice. ^22The wind shall feed all thy shepherds, and thy lovers shall go into captivity: surely then shalt thou be ashamed and confounded for all thy wickedness. ^23O inhabitant of Lebanon, that makest thy nest in the cedars, how greatly to be pitied shalt thou be when pangs come upon thee, the pain as of a woman in travail! ^24As I live, saith Jehovah, though Coniah the son of Jehoiakim king of Judah were the signet upon my right hand, yet would I pluck thee thence; ^25and I will give thee into the hand of them that seek thy life, and into the hand of them of whom thou art afraid, even into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of the Chaldeans. ^26And I will cast thee out, and thy mother that bare thee, into another country, where ye were not born; and there shall ye die. ^27But to the land whereunto their soul longeth to return, thither shall they not return. ^28Is this man Coniah a despised broken vessel? is he a vessel wherein none delighteth? wherefore are they cast out, he and his seed, and are cast into the land which they know not? ^29O earth, earth, earth, hear the word of Jehovah. ^30Thus saith Jehovah, Write ye this man childless, a man that shall not prosper in his days; for no more shall a man of his seed prosper, sitting upon the throne of David, and ruling in Judah.

Jeremiah 23

23

^1Woe unto the shepherds that destroy and scatter the sheep of my pasture! saith Jehovah. ^2Therefore thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, against the shepherds that feed my people: Ye have scattered my flock, and driven them away, and have not visited them; behold, I will visit upon you the evil of your doings, saith Jehovah. ^3And I will gather the remnant of my flock out of all the countries whither I have driven them, and will bring them again to their folds; and they shall be fruitful and multiply. ^4And I will set up shepherds over them, who shall feed them; and they shall fear no more, nor be dismayed, neither shall any be lacking, saith Jehovah. ^5Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will raise unto David a righteous Branch, and he shall reign as king and deal wisely, and shall execute justice and righteousness in the land. ^6In his days Judah shall be saved, and Israel shall dwell safely; and this is his name whereby he shall be called: Jehovah our righteousness. ^7Therefore, behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that they shall no more say, As Jehovah liveth, who brought up the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt; ^8but, As Jehovah liveth, who brought up and who led the seed of the house of Israel out of the north country, and from all the countries whither I had driven them. And they shall dwell in their own land. ^9Concerning the prophets. My heart within me is broken, all my bones shake; I am like a drunken man, and like a man whom wine hath overcome, because of Jehovah, and because of his holy words. ^10For the land is full of adulterers; for because of swearing the land mourneth; the pastures of the wilderness are dried up. And their course is evil, and their might is not right; ^11for both prophet and priest are profane; yea, in my house have I found their wickedness, saith Jehovah. ^12Wherefore their way shall be unto them as slippery places in the darkness: they shall be driven on, and fall therein; for I will bring evil upon them, even the year of their visitation, saith Jehovah. ^13And I have seen folly in the prophets of Samaria; they prophesied by Baal, and caused my people Israel to err. ^14In the prophets of Jerusalem also I have seen a horrible thing: they commit adultery, and walk in lies; and they strengthen the hands of evil-doers, so that none doth return from his wickedness: they are all of them become unto me as Sodom, and the inhabitants thereof as Gomorrah. ^15Therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts concerning the prophets: Behold, I will feed them with wormwood, and make them drink the water of gall; for from the prophets of Jerusalem is ungodliness gone forth into all the land. ^16Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, Hearken not unto the words of the prophets that prophesy unto you: they teach you vanity; they speak a vision of their own heart, and not out of the mouth of Jehovah. ^17They say continually unto them that despise me, Jehovah hath said, Ye shall have peace; and unto every one that walketh in the stubbornness of his own heart they say, No evil shall come upon you. ^18For who hath stood in the council of Jehovah, that he should perceive and hear his word? who hath marked my word, and heard it? ^19Behold, the tempest of Jehovah, even his wrath, is gone forth, yea, a whirling tempest: it shall burst upon the head of the wicked. ^20The anger of Jehovah shall not return, until he have executed, and till he have performed the intents of his heart: in the latter days ye shall understand it perfectly. ^21I sent not these prophets, yet they ran: I spake not unto them, yet they prophesied. ^22But if they had stood in my council, then had they caused my people to hear my words, and had turned them from their evil way, and from the evil of their doings. ^23Am I a God at hand, saith Jehovah, and not a God afar off? ^24Can any hide himself in secret places so that I shall not see him? saith Jehovah. Do not I fill heaven and earth? saith Jehovah. ^25I have heard what the prophets have said, that prophesy lies in my name, saying, I have dreamed, I have dreamed. ^26How long shall this be in the heart of the prophets that prophesy lies, even the prophets of the deceit of their own heart? ^27that think to cause my people to forget my name by their dreams which they tell every man to his neighbor, as their fathers forgat my name for Baal. ^28The prophet that hath a dream, let him tell a dream; and he that hath my word, let him speak my word faithfully. What is the straw to the wheat? saith Jehovah. ^29Is not my word like fire? saith Jehovah; and like a hammer that breaketh the rock in pieces? ^30Therefore, behold, I am against the prophets, saith Jehovah, that steal my words every one from his neighbor. ^31Behold, I am against the prophets, saith Jehovah, that use their tongues, and say, He saith. ^32Behold, I am against them that prophesy lying dreams, saith Jehovah, and do tell them, and cause my people to err by their lies, and by their vain boasting: yet I sent them not, nor commanded them; neither do they profit this people at all, saith Jehovah. ^33And when this people, or the prophet, or a priest, shall ask thee, saying, What is the burden of Jehovah? then shalt thou say unto them, What burden! I will cast you off, saith Jehovah. ^34And as for the prophet, and the priest, and the people, that shall say, The burden of Jehovah, I will even punish that man and his house. ^35Thus shall ye say every one to his neighbor, and every one to his brother, What hath Jehovah answered? and, What hath Jehovah spoken? ^36And the burden of Jehovah shall ye mention no more: for every man's own word shall be his burden; for ye have perverted the words of the living God, of Jehovah of hosts our God. ^37Thus shalt thou say to the prophet, What hath Jehovah answered thee? and, What hath Jehovah spoken? ^38But if ye say, The burden of Jehovah; therefore thus saith Jehovah: Because ye say this word, The burden of Jehovah, and I have sent unto you, saying, Ye shall not say, The burden of Jehovah; ^39therefore, behold, I will utterly forget you, and I will cast you off, and the city that I gave unto you and to your fathers, away from my presence: ^40and I will bring an everlasting reproach upon you, and a perpetual shame, which shall not be forgotten.

Jeremiah 24

24

^1Jehovah showed me, and, behold, two baskets of figs set before the temple of Jehovah, after that Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon had carried away captive Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, and the princes of Judah, with the craftsmen and smiths, from Jerusalem, and had brought them to Babylon. ^2One basket had very good figs, like the figs that are first-ripe; and the other basket had very bad figs, which could not be eaten, they were so bad. ^3Then said Jehovah unto me, What seest thou, Jeremiah? And I said, Figs; the good figs, very good; and the bad, very bad, that cannot be eaten, they are so bad. ^4And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^5Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel: Like these good figs, so will I regard the captives of Judah, whom I have sent out of this place into the land of the Chaldeans, for good. ^6For I will set mine eyes upon them for good, and I will bring them again to this land: and I will build them, and not pull them down; and I will plant them, and not pluck them up. ^7And I will give them a heart to know me, that I am Jehovah: and they shall be my people, and I will be their God; for they shall return unto me with their whole heart. ^8And as the bad figs, which cannot be eaten, they are so bad, surely thus saith Jehovah, So will I give up Zedekiah the king of Judah, and his princes, and the residue of Jerusalem, that remain in this land, and them that dwell in the land of Egypt, ^9I will even give them up to be tossed to and fro among all the kingdoms of the earth for evil; to be a reproach and a proverb, a taunt and a curse, in all places whither I shall drive them. ^10And I will send the sword, the famine, and the pestilence, among them, till they be consumed from off the land that I gave unto them and to their fathers.

Jeremiah 25

25

^1The word that came to Jeremiah concerning all the people of Judah, in the fourth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah (the same was the first year of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon,) ^2which Jeremiah the prophet spake unto all the people of Judah, and to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying: ^3From the thirteenth year of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah, even unto this day, these three and twenty years, the word of Jehovah hath come unto me, and I have spoken unto you, rising up early and speaking; but ye have not hearkened. ^4And Jehovah hath sent unto you all his servants the prophets, rising up early and sending them, (but ye have not hearkened, nor inclined your ear to hear,) ^5saying, Return ye now every one from his evil way, and from the evil of your doings, and dwell in the land that Jehovah hath given unto you and to your fathers, from of old and even for evermore; ^6and go not after other gods to serve them, and to worship them, and provoke me not to anger with the work of your hands; and I will do you no hurt. ^7Yet ye have not hearkened unto me, saith Jehovah; that ye may provoke me to anger with the work of your hands to your own hurt. ^8Therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Because ye have not heard my words, ^9behold, I will send and take all the families of the north, saith Jehovah, and I will send unto Nebuchadrezzar the king of Babylon, my servant, and will bring them against this land, and against the inhabitants thereof, and against all these nations round about; and I will utterly destroy them, and make them an astonishment, and a hissing, and perpetual desolations. ^10Moreover I will take from them the voice of mirth and the voice of gladness, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, the sound of the millstones, and the light of the lamp. ^11And this whole land shall be a desolation, and an astonishment; and these nations shall serve the king of Babylon seventy years. ^12And it shall come to pass, when seventy years are accomplished, that I will punish the king of Babylon, and that nation, saith Jehovah, for their iniquity, and the land of the Chaldeans; and I will make it desolate for ever. ^13And I will bring upon that land all my words which I have pronounced against it, even all that is written in this book, which Jeremiah hath prophesied against all the nations. ^14For many nations and great kings shall make bondmen of them, even of them; and I will recompense them according to their deeds, and according to the work of their hands. ^15For thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, unto me: take this cup of the wine of wrath at my hand, and cause all the nations, to whom I send thee, to drink it. ^16And they shall drink, and reel to and fro, and be mad, because of the sword that I will send among them. ^17Then took I the cup at Jehovah's hand, and made all the nations to drink, unto whom Jehovah had sent me: ^18to wit, Jerusalem, and the cities of Judah, and the kings thereof, and the princes thereof, to make them a desolation, an astonishment, a hissing, and a curse, as it is this day; ^19Pharaoh king of Egypt, and his servants, and his princes, and all his people; ^20and all the mingled people, and all the kings of the land of the Uz, and all the kings of the Philistines, and Ashkelon, and Gaza, and Ekron, and the remnant of Ashdod; ^21Edom, and Moab, and the children of Ammon; ^22and all the kings of Tyre, and all the kings of Sidon, and the kings of the isle which is beyond the sea; ^23Dedan, and Tema, and Buz, and all that have the corners of their hair cut off; ^24and all the kings of Arabia, and all the kings of the mingled people that dwell in the wilderness; ^25and all the kings of Zimri, and all the kings of Elam, and all the kings of the Medes; ^26and all the kings of the north, far and near, one with another; and all the kingdoms of the world, which are upon the face of the earth: and the king of Sheshach shall drink after them. ^27And thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Drink ye, and be drunken, and spew, and fall, and rise no more, because of the sword which I will send among you. ^28And it shall be, if they refuse to take the cup at thy hand to drink, then shalt thou say unto them, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Ye shall surely drink. ^29For, lo, I begin to work evil at the city which is called by my name; and should ye be utterly unpunished? Ye shall not be unpunished; for I will call for a sword upon all the inhabitants of the earth, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^30Therefore prophesy thou against them all these words, and say unto them, Jehovah will roar from on high, and utter his voice from his holy habitation; he will mightily roar against his fold; he will give a shout, as they that tread the grapes, against all the inhabitants of the earth. ^31A noise shall come even to the end of the earth; for Jehovah hath a controversy with the nations; he will enter into judgment with all flesh: as for the wicked, he will give them to the sword, saith Jehovah. ^32Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, Behold, evil shall go forth from nation to nation, and a great tempest shall be raised up from the uttermost parts of the earth. ^33And the slain of Jehovah shall be at that day from one end of the earth even unto the other end of the earth: they shall not be lamented, neither gathered, nor buried; they shall be dung upon the face of the ground. ^34Wail, ye shepherds, and cry; and wallow in ashes, ye principal of the flock; for the days of your slaughter and of your dispersions are fully come, and ye shall fall like a goodly vessel. ^35And the shepherds shall have no way to flee, nor the principal of the flock to escape. ^36A voice of the cry of the shepherds, and the wailing of the principal of the flock! for Jehovah layeth waste their pasture. ^37And the peaceable folds are brought to silence because of the fierce anger of Jehovah. ^38He hath left his covert, as the lion; for their land is become an astonishment because of the fierceness of the oppressing sword, and because of his fierce anger.

Jeremiah 26

26

^1In the beginning of the reign of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, came this word from Jehovah, saying, ^2Thus saith Jehovah: Stand in the court of Jehovah's house, and speak unto all the cities of Judah, which come to worship in Jehovah's house, all the words that I command thee to speak unto them; diminish not a word. ^3It may be they will hearken, and turn every man from his evil way; that I may repent me of the evil which I purpose to do unto them because of the evil of their doings. ^4And thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith Jehovah: If ye will not hearken to me, to walk in my law, which I have set before you, ^5to hearken to the words of my servants the prophets, whom I send unto you, even rising up early and sending them, but ye have not hearkened; ^6then will I make this house like Shiloh, and will make this city a curse to all the nations of the earth. ^7And the priests and the prophets and all the people heard Jeremiah speaking these words in the house of Jehovah. ^8And it came to pass, when Jeremiah had made an end of speaking all that Jehovah had commanded him to speak unto all the people, that the priests and the prophets and all the people laid hold on him, saying, Thou shalt surely die. ^9Why hast thou prophesied in the name of Jehovah, saying, This house shall be like Shiloh, and this city shall be desolate, without inhabitant? And all the people were gathered unto Jeremiah in the house of Jehovah. ^10And when the princes of Judah heard these things, they came up from the king's house unto the house of Jehovah; and they sat in the entry of the new gate of Jehovah's house. ^11Then spake the priests and the prophets unto the princes and to all the people, saying, This man is worthy of death; for he hath prophesied against this city, as ye have heard with your ears. ^12Then spake Jeremiah unto all the princes and to all the people, saying, Jehovah sent me to prophesy against this house and against this city all the words that ye have heard. ^13Now therefore amend your ways and your doings, and obey the voice of Jehovah your God; and Jehovah will repent him of the evil that he hath pronounced against you. ^14But as for me, behold, I am in your hand: do with me as is good and right in your eyes. ^15Only know ye for certain that, if ye put me to death, ye will bring innocent blood upon yourselves, and upon this city, and upon the inhabitants thereof; for of a truth Jehovah hath sent me unto you to speak all these words in your ears. ^16Then said the princes and all the people unto the priests and to the prophets: This man is not worthy of death; for he hath spoken to us in the name of Jehovah our God. ^17Then rose up certain of the elders of the land, and spake to all the assembly of the people, saying, ^18Micah the Morashtite prophesied in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah; and he spake to all the people of Judah, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Zion shall be plowed as a field, and Jerusalem shall become heaps, and the mountain of the house as the high places of a forest. ^19Did Hezekiah king of Judah and all Judah put him to death? did he not fear Jehovah, and entreat the favor of Jehovah, and Jehovah repented him of the evil which he had pronounced against them? Thus should we commit great evil against our own souls. ^20And there was also a man that prophesied in the name of Jehovah, Uriah the son of Shemaiah of Kiriath-jearim; and he prophesied against this city and against this land according to all the words of Jeremiah: ^21and when Jehoiakim the king, with all his mighty-men, and all the princes, heard his words, the king sought to put him to death; but when Uriah heard it, he was afraid, and fled, and went into Egypt: ^22and Jehoiakim the king sent men into Egypt, namely, Elnathan the son of Achbor, and certain men with him, into Egypt; ^23and they fetched forth Uriah out of Egypt, and brought him unto Jehoiakim the king, who slew him with the sword, and cast his dead body into the graves of the common people. ^24But the hand of Ahikam the son of Shaphan was with Jeremiah, that they should not give him into the hand of the people to put him to death.

Jeremiah 27

27

^1In the beginning of the reign of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, came this word unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying, ^2Thus saith Jehovah to me: Make thee bonds and bars, and put them upon thy neck; ^3and send them to the king of Edom, and to the king of Moab, and to the king of the children of Ammon, and to the king of Tyre, and to the king of Sidon, by the hand of the messengers that come to Jerusalem unto Zedekiah king of Judah; ^4and give them a charge unto their masters, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, Thus shall ye say unto your masters: ^5I have made the earth, the men and the beasts that are upon the face of the earth, by my great power and by my outstretched arm; and I give it unto whom it seemeth right unto me. ^6And now have I given all these lands into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, my servant; and the beasts of the field also have I given him to serve him. ^7And all the nations shall serve him, and his son, and his son's son, until the time of his own land come: and then many nations and great kings shall make him their bondman. ^8And it shall come to pass, that the nation and the kingdom which will not serve the same Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and that will not put their neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon, that nation will I punish, saith Jehovah, with the sword, and with the famine, and with the pestilence, until I have consumed them by his hand. ^9But as for you, hearken ye not to your prophets, nor to your diviners, nor to your dreams, nor to your soothsayers, nor to your sorcerers, that speak unto you, saying, Ye shall not serve the king of Babylon: ^10for they prophesy a lie unto you, to remove you far from your land, and that I should drive you out, and ye should perish. ^11But the nation that shall bring their neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon, and serve him, that nation will I let remain in their own land, saith Jehovah; and they shall till it, and dwell therein. ^12And I spake to Zedekiah king of Judah according to all these words, saying, Bring your necks under the yoke of the king of Babylon, and serve him and his people, and live. ^13Why will ye die, thou and thy people, by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence, as Jehovah hath spoken concerning the nation that will not serve the king of Babylon? ^14And hearken not unto the words of the prophets that speak unto you, saying, Ye shall not serve the king of Babylon; for they prophesy a lie unto you. ^15For I have not sent them, saith Jehovah, but they prophesy falsely in my name; that I may drive you out, and that ye may perish, ye, and the prophets that prophesy unto you. ^16Also I spake to the priests and to all this people, saying, Thus saith Jehovah: Hearken not to the words of your prophets that prophesy unto you, saying, Behold, the vessels of Jehovah's house shall now shortly be brought again from Babylon; for they prophesy a lie unto you. ^17Hearken not unto them; serve the king of Babylon, and live: wherefore should this city become a desolation? ^18But if they be prophets, and if the word of Jehovah be with them, let them now make intercession to Jehovah of hosts, that the vessels which are left in the house of Jehovah, and in the house of the king of Judah, and at Jerusalem, go not to Babylon. ^19For thus saith Jehovah of hosts concerning the pillars, and concerning the sea, and concerning the bases, and concerning the residue of the vessels that are left in this city, ^20which Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon took not, when he carried away captive Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, from Jerusalem to Babylon, and all the nobles of Judah and Jerusalem; ^21yea, thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, concerning the vessels that are left in the house of Jehovah, and in the house of the king of Judah, and at Jerusalem: ^22They shall be carried to Babylon, and there shall they be, until the day that I visit them, saith Jehovah; then will I bring them up, and restore them to this place.

Jeremiah 28

28

^1And it came to pass the same year, in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah king of Judah, in the fourth year, in the fifth month, that Hananiah the son of Azzur, the prophet, who was of Gibeon, spake unto me in the house of Jehovah, in the presence of the priests and of all the people, saying, ^2Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, saying, I have broken the yoke of the king of Babylon. ^3Within two full years will I bring again into this place all the vessels of Jehovah's house, that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon took away from this place, and carried to Babylon: ^4and I will bring again to this place Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, with all the captives of Judah, that went to Babylon, saith Jehovah; for I will break the yoke of the king of Babylon. ^5Then the prophet Jeremiah said unto the prophet Hananiah in the presence of the priests, and in the presence of all the people that stood in the house of Jehovah, ^6even the prophet Jeremiah said, Amen: Jehovah do so; Jehovah perform thy words which thou hast prophesied, to bring again the vessels of Jehovah's house, and all them of the captivity, from Babylon unto this place. ^7Nevertheless hear thou now this word that I speak in thine ears, and in the ears of all the people: ^8The prophets that have been before me and before thee of old prophesied against many countries, and against great kingdoms, of war, and of evil, and of pestilence. ^9The prophet that prophesieth of peace, when the word of the prophet shall come to pass, then shall the prophet be known, that Jehovah hath truly sent him. ^10Then Hananiah the prophet took the bar from off the prophet Jeremiah's neck, and brake it. ^11And Hananiah spake in the presence of all the people, saying, Thus saith Jehovah: Even so will I break the yoke of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon within two full years from off the neck of all the nations. And the prophet Jeremiah went his way. ^12Then the word of Jehovah came unto Jeremiah, after that Hananiah the prophet had broken the bar from off the neck of the prophet Jeremiah, saying, ^13Go, and tell Hananiah, saying, Thus saith Jehovah: Thou hast broken the bars of wood; but thou hast made in their stead bars of iron. ^14For thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: I have put a yoke of iron upon the neck of all these nations, that they may served Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon; and they shall serve him: and I have given him the beasts of the field also. ^15Then said the prophet Jeremiah unto Hananiah the prophet, Hear now, Hananiah: Jehovah hath not sent thee; but thou makest this people to trust in a lie. ^16Therefore thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will send thee away from off the face of the earth: this year thou shalt die, because thou hast spoken rebellion against Jehovah. ^17So Hananiah the prophet died the same year in the seventh month.

Jeremiah 29

29

^1Now these are the words of the letter that Jeremiah the prophet sent from Jerusalem unto the residue of the elders of the captivity, and to the priests, and to the prophets, and to all the people, whom Nebuchadnezzar had carried away captive from Jerusalem to Babylon, ^2(after that Jeconiah the king, and the queen-mother, and the eunuchs, and the princes of Judah and Jerusalem, and the craftsmen, and the smiths, were departed from Jerusalem,) ^3by the hand of Elasah the son of Shaphan, and Gemariah the son of Hilkiah, (whom Zedekiah king of Judah sent unto Babylon to Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon,) saying, ^4Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, unto all the captivity, whom I have caused to be carried away captive from Jerusalem unto Babylon: ^5Build ye houses, and dwell in them; and plant gardens, and eat the fruit of them. ^6Take ye wives, and beget sons and daughters; and take wives for your sons, and give your daughters to husbands, that they may bear sons and daughters; and multiply ye there, and be not diminished. ^7And seek the peace of the city whither I have caused you to be carried away captive, and pray unto Jehovah for it; for in the peace thereof shall ye have peace. ^8For thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Let not your prophets that are in the midst of you, and your diviners, deceive you; neither hearken ye to your dreams which ye cause to be dreamed. ^9For they prophesy falsely unto you in my name: I have not sent them, saith Jehovah. ^10For thus saith Jehovah, After seventy years are accomplished for Babylon, I will visit you, and perform my good word toward you, in causing you to return to this place. ^11For I know the thoughts that I think toward you, saith Jehovah, thoughts of peace, and not of evil, to give you hope in your latter end. ^12And ye shall call upon me, and ye shall go and pray unto me, and I will hearken unto you. ^13And ye shall seek me, and find me, when ye shall search for me with all your heart. ^14And I will be found of you, saith Jehovah, and I will turn again your captivity, and I will gather you from all the nations, and from all the places wither I have driven you, saith Jehovah; and I will bring you again unto the place whence I caused you to be carried away captive. ^15Because ye have said, Jehovah hath raised us up prophets in Babylon; ^16thus saith Jehovah concerning the king that sitteth upon the throne of David, and concerning all the people that dwell in this city, your brethren that are not gone forth with you into captivity; ^17thus saith Jehovah of hosts; Behold, I will send upon them the sword, the famine, and the pestilence, and will make them like vile figs, that cannot be eaten, they are so bad. ^18And I will pursue after them with the sword, with the famine, and with the pestilence, and will deliver them to be tossed to and fro among all the kingdoms of the earth, to be an execration, and an astonishment, and a hissing, and a reproach, among all the nations whither I have driven them; ^19because they have not hearkened to my words, saith Jehovah, wherewith I sent unto them my servants the prophets, rising up early and sending them; but ye would not hear, saith Jehovah. ^20Hear ye therefore the word of Jehovah, all ye of the captivity, whom I have sent away from Jerusalem to Babylon. ^21Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, concerning Ahab the son of Kolaiah, and concerning Zedekiah the son of Maaseiah, who prophesy a lie unto you in my name: Behold, I will deliver them into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon; and he shall slay them before your eyes; ^22and of them shall be taken up a curse by all the captives of Judah that are in Babylon, saying, Jehovah make thee like Zedekiah and like Ahab, whom the king of Babylon roasted in the fire; ^23because they have wrought folly in Israel, and have committed adultery with their neighbors' wives, and have spoken words in my name falsely, which I commanded them not; and I am he that knoweth, and am witness, saith Jehovah. ^24And concerning Shemaiah the Nehelamite thou shalt speak, saying, ^25Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, saying, Because thou hast sent letters in thine own name unto all the people that are at Jerusalem, and to Zephaniah the son of Maaseiah, the priest, and to all the priests, saying, ^26Jehovah hath made thee priest in the stead of Jehoiada the priest, that there may be officers in the house of Jehovah, for every man that is mad, and maketh himself a prophet, that thou shouldest put him in the stocks and in shackles. ^27Now therefore, why hast thou not rebuked Jeremiah of Anathoth, who maketh himself a prophet to you, ^28forasmuch as he hath sent unto us in Babylon, saying, The captivity is long: build ye houses, and dwell in them; and plant gardens, and eat the fruit of them? ^29And Zephaniah the priest read this letter in the ears of Jeremiah the prophet. ^30Then came the word of Jehovah unto Jeremiah, saying, ^31Send to all them of the captivity, saying, Thus saith Jehovah concerning Shemaiah the Nehelamite: Because that Shemaiah hath prophesied unto you, and I sent him not, and he hath caused you to trust in a lie; ^32therefore thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will punish Shemaiah the Nehelamite, and his seed; he shall not have a man to dwell among this people, neither shall he behold the good that I will do unto my people, saith Jehovah, because he hath spoken rebellion against Jehovah.

Jeremiah 30

30

^1The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying, ^2Thus speaketh Jehovah, the God of Israel, saying, Write thee all the words that I have spoken unto thee in a book. ^3For, lo, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will turn again the captivity of my people Israel and Judah, saith Jehovah; and I will cause them to return to the land that I gave to their fathers, and they shall possess it. ^4And these are the words that Jehovah spake concerning Israel and concerning Judah. ^5For thus saith Jehovah: We have heard a voice of trembling, of fear, and not of peace. ^6Ask ye now, and see whether a man doth travail with child: wherefore do I see every man with his hands on his loins, as a woman in travail, and all faces are turned into paleness? ^7Alas! for that day is great, so that none is like it: it is even the time of Jacob's trouble; but he shall be saved out of it. ^8And it shall come to pass in that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, that I will break his yoke from off thy neck, and will burst thy bonds; and strangers shall no more make him their bondman; ^9but they shall serve Jehovah their God, and David their king, whom I will raise up unto them. ^10Therefore fear thou not, O Jacob my servant, saith Jehovah; neither be dismayed, O Israel: for, lo, I will save thee from afar, and thy seed from the land of their captivity; and Jacob shall return, and shall be quiet and at ease, and none shall make him afraid. ^11For I am with thee, saith Jehovah, to save thee: for I will make a full end of all the nations whither I have scattered thee, but I will not make a full end of thee; but I will correct thee in measure, and will in no wise leave thee unpunished. ^12For thus saith Jehovah, Thy hurt is incurable, and thy wound grievous. ^13There is none to plead thy cause, that thou mayest be bound up: thou hast no healing medicines. ^14All thy lovers have forgotten thee; they seek thee not: for I have wounded thee with the wound of an enemy, with the chastisement of a cruel one, for the greatness of thine iniquity, because thy sins were increased. ^15Why criest thou for thy hurt? thy pain is incurable: for the greatness of thine iniquity, because thy sins were increased, I have done these things unto thee. ^16Therefore all they that devour thee shall be devoured; and all thine adversaries, every one of them, shall go into captivity; and they that despoil thee shall be a spoil, and all that prey upon thee will I give for a prey. ^17For I will restore health unto thee, and I will heal thee of thy wounds, saith Jehovah; because they have called thee an outcast, saying, It is Zion, whom no man seeketh after. ^18Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I will turn again the captivity of Jacob's tents, and have compassion on his dwelling-places; and the city shall be builded upon its own hill, and the palace shall be inhabited after its own manner. ^19And out of them shall proceed thanksgiving and the voice of them that make merry: and I will multiply them, and they shall not be few; I will also glorify them, and they shall not be small. ^20Their children also shall be as aforetime, and their congregation shall be established before me; and I will punish all that oppress them. ^21And their prince shall be of themselves, and their ruler shall proceed from the midst of them; and I will cause him to draw near, and he shall approach unto me: for who is he that hath had boldness to approach unto me? saith Jehovah. ^22And ye shall be my people, and I will be your God. ^23Behold, the tempest of Jehovah, even his wrath, is gone forth, a sweeping tempest: it shall burst upon the head of the wicked. ^24The fierce anger of Jehovah shall not return, until he have executed, and till he have performed the intents of his heart: in the latter days ye shall understand it.

Jeremiah 31

31

^1At that time, saith Jehovah, will I be the God of all the families of Israel, and they shall be my people. ^2Thus saith Jehovah, The people that were left of the sword found favor in the wilderness; even Israel, when I went to cause him to rest. ^3Jehovah appeared of old unto me, saying, Yea, I have loved thee with an everlasting love: therefore with lovingkindness have I drawn thee. ^4Again will I build thee, and thou shalt be built, O virgin of Israel: again shalt thou be adorned with thy tabrets, and shalt go forth in the dances of them that make merry. ^5Again shalt thou plant vineyards upon the mountains of Samaria; the planters shall plant, and shall enjoy the fruit thereof. ^6For there shall be a day, that the watchmen upon the hills of Ephraim shall cry, Arise ye, and let us go up to Zion unto Jehovah our God. ^7For thus saith Jehovah, Sing with gladness for Jacob, and shout for the chief of the nations: publish ye, praise ye, and say, O Jehovah, save thy people, the remnant of Israel. ^8Behold, I will bring them from the north country, and gather them from the uttermost parts of the earth, and with them the blind and the lame, the woman with child and her that travaileth with child together: a great company shall they return hither. ^9They shall come with weeping; and with supplications will I lead them: I will cause them to walk by rivers of waters, in a straight way wherein they shall not stumble; for I am a father to Israel, and Ephraim is my first-born. ^10Hear the word of Jehovah, O ye nations, and declare it in the isles afar off; and say, He that scattered Israel will gather him, and keep him, as shepherd doth his flock. ^11For Jehovah hath ransomed Jacob, and redeemed him from the hand of him that was stronger than he. ^12And they shall come and sing in the height of Zion, and shall flow unto the goodness of Jehovah, to the grain, and to the new wine, and to the oil, and to the young of the flock and of the herd: and their soul shall be as a watered garden; and they shall not sorrow any more at all. ^13Then shall the virgin rejoice in the dance, and the young men and the old together; for I will turn their mourning into joy, and will comfort them, and make them rejoice from their sorrow. ^14And I will satiate the soul of the priests with fatness, and my people shall be satisfied with my goodness, saith Jehovah. ^15Thus saith Jehovah: A voice is heard in Ramah, lamentation, and bitter weeping, Rachel weeping for her children; she refuseth to be comforted for her children, because they are not. ^16Thus saith Jehovah: Refrain thy voice from weeping, and thine eyes from tears; for thy work shall be rewarded, saith Jehovah; and they shall come again from the land of the enemy. ^17And there is hope for thy latter end, saith Jehovah; and thy children shall come again to their own border. ^18I have surely heard Ephraim bemoaning himself thus, Thou hast chastised me, and I was chastised, as a calf unaccustomed to the yoke: turn thou me, and I shall be turned; for thou art Jehovah my God. ^19Surely after that I was turned, I repented; and after that I was instructed, I smote upon my thigh: I was ashamed, yea, even confounded, because I did bear the reproach of my youth. ^20Is Ephraim my dear son? is he a darling child? for as often as I speak against him, I do earnestly remember him still: therefore my heart yearneth for him; I will surely have mercy upon him, saith Jehovah. ^21Set thee up waymarks, make thee guide-posts; set thy heart toward the highway, even the way by which thou wentest: turn again, O virgin of Israel, turn again to these thy cities. ^22How long wilt thou go hither and thither, O thou backsliding daughter? for Jehovah hath created a new thing in the earth: a woman shall encompass a man. ^23Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, Yet again shall they use this speech in the land of Judah and in the cities thereof, when I shall bring again their captivity: Jehovah bless thee, O habitation of righteousness, O mountain of holiness. ^24And Judah and all the cities thereof shall dwell therein together, the husbandmen, and they that go about with flocks. ^25For I have satiated the weary soul, and every sorrowful soul have I replenished. ^26Upon this I awaked, and beheld; and my sleep was sweet unto me. ^27Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will sow the house of Israel and the house of Judah with the seed of man, and with the seed of beast. ^28And it shall come to pass that, like as I have watched over them to pluck up and to break down and to overthrow and to destroy and to afflict, so will I watch over them to build and to plant, saith Jehovah. ^29In those days they shall say no more, The fathers have eaten sour grapes, and the children's teeth are set on edge. ^30But every one shall die for his own iniquity: every man that eateth the sour grapes, his teeth shall be set on edge. ^31Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel, and with the house of Judah: ^32not according to the covenant that I made with their fathers in the day that I took them by the hand to bring them out of the land of Egypt; which my covenant they brake, although I was a husband unto them, saith Jehovah. ^33But this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days, saith Jehovah: I will put my law in their inward parts, and in their heart will I write it; and I will be their God, and they shall be my people: ^34and they shall teach no more every man his neighbor, and every man his brother, saying, Know Jehovah; for they shall all know me, from the least of them unto the greatest of them, saith Jehovah: for I will forgive their iniquity, and their sin will I remember no more. ^35Thus saith Jehovah, who giveth the sun for a light by day, and the ordinances of the moon and of the stars for a light by night, who stirreth up the sea, so that the waves thereof roar; Jehovah of hosts is his name: ^36If these ordinances depart from before me, saith Jehovah, then the seed of Israel also shall cease from being a nation before me for ever. ^37Thus saith Jehovah: If heaven above can be measured, and the foundations of the earth searched out beneath, then will I also cast off all the seed of Israel for all that they have done, saith Jehovah. ^38Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that the city shall be built to Jehovah from the tower of Hananel unto the gate of the corner. ^39And the measuring line shall go out further straight onward unto the hill Gareb, and shall turn about unto Goah. ^40And the whole valley of the dead bodies and of the ashes, and all the fields unto the brook Kidron, unto the corner of the horse gate toward the east, shall be holy unto Jehovah; it shall not be plucked up, nor thrown down any more for ever.

Jeremiah 32

32

^1The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah in the tenth year of Zedekiah king of Judah, which was the eighteenth year of Nebuchadrezzar. ^2Now at that time the king of Babylon's army was besieging Jerusalem; and Jeremiah the prophet was shut up in the court of the guard, which was in the king of Judah's house. ^3For Zedekiah king of Judah had shut him up, saying, Wherefore dost thou prophesy, and say, Thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will give this city into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall take it; ^4and Zedekiah king of Judah shall not escape out of the hand of the Chaldeans, but shall surely be delivered into the hand of the king of Babylon, and shall speak with him mouth to mouth, and his eyes shall behold his eyes; ^5and he shall bring Zedekiah to Babylon, and there shall he be until I visit him, saith Jehovah: though ye fight with the Chaldeans, ye shall not prosper? ^6And Jeremiah said, The word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^7Behold, Hanamel the son of Shallum thine uncle shall come unto thee, saying, Buy thee my field that is in Anathoth; for the right of redemption is thine to buy it. ^8So Hanamel mine uncle's son came to me in the court of the guard according to the word of Jehovah, and said unto me, Buy my field, I pray thee, that is in Anathoth, which is in the land of Benjamin; for the right of inheritance is thine, and the redemption is thine; buy it for thyself. Then I knew that this was the word of Jehovah. ^9And I bought the field that was in Anathoth of Hanamel mine uncle's son, and weighed him the money, even seventeen shekels of silver. ^10And I subscribed the deed, and sealed it, and called witnesses, and weighed him the money in the balances. ^11So I took the deed of the purchase, both that which was sealed, according to the law and custom, and that which was open: ^12and I delivered the deed of the purchase unto Baruch the son of Neriah, the son of Mahseiah, in the presence of Hanamel mine uncle's son, and in the presence of the witnesses that subscribed the deed of the purchase, before all the Jews that sat in the court of the guard. ^13And I charged Baruch before them, saying, ^14Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Take these deeds, this deed of the purchase which is sealed, and this deed which is open, and put them in an earthen vessel; that they may continue many days. ^15For thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Houses and fields and vineyards shall yet again be bought in this land. ^16Now after I had delivered the deed of the purchase unto Baruch the son of Neriah, I prayed unto Jehovah, saying, ^17Ah Lord Jehovah! behold, thou hast made the heavens and the earth by thy great power and by thine outstretched arm; there is nothing too hard for thee, ^18who showest lovingkindness unto thousands, and recompensest the iniquity of the fathers into the bosom of their children after them; the great, the mighty God, Jehovah of hosts is his name; ^19great in counsel, and mighty in work; whose eyes are open upon all the ways of the sons of men, to give every one according to his ways, and according to the fruit of his doings: ^20who didst set signs and wonders in the land of Egypt, even unto this day, both in Israel and among other men; and madest thee a name, as at this day; ^21and didst bring forth thy people Israel out of the land of Egypt with signs, and with wonders, and with a strong hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with great terror; ^22and gavest them this land, which thou didst swear to their fathers to give them, a land flowing with milk and honey; ^23and they came in, and possessed it, but they obeyed not thy voice, neither walked in thy law; they have done nothing of all that thou commandedst them to do: therefore thou hast caused all this evil to come upon them. ^24Behold, the mounds, they are come unto the city to take it; and the city is given into the hand of the Chaldeans that fight against it, because of the sword, and of the famine, and of the pestilence; and what thou hast spoken is come to pass; and, behold, thou seest it. ^25And thou hast said unto me, O Lord Jehovah, Buy thee the field for money, and call witnesses; whereas the city is given into the hand of the Chaldeans. ^26Then came the word of Jehovah unto Jeremiah, saying, ^27Behold, I am Jehovah, the God of all flesh: is there anything too hard for me? ^28Therefore thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I will give this city into the hand of the Chaldeans, and into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, and he shall take it: ^29and the Chaldeans, that fight against this city, shall come and set this city on fire, and burn it, with the houses, upon whose roofs they have offered incense unto Baal, and poured out drink-offerings unto other gods, to provoke me to anger. ^30For the children of Israel and the children of Judah have done only that which was evil in my sight from their youth; for the children of Israel have only provoked me to anger with the work of their hands, saith Jehovah. ^31For this city hath been to me a provocation of mine anger and of my wrath from the day that they built it even unto this day; that I should remove it from before my face, ^32because of all the evil of the children of Israel and of the children of Judah, which they have done to provoke me to anger, they, their kings, their princes, their priests, and their prophets, and the men of Judah, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^33And they have turned unto me the back, and not the face: and though I taught them, rising up early and teaching them, yet they have not hearkened to receive instruction. ^34But they set their abominations in the house which is called by my name, to defile it. ^35And they built the high places of Baal, which are in the valley of the son of Hinnom, to cause their sons and their daughters to pass through the fire unto Molech; which I commanded them not, neither came it into my mind, that they should do this abomination, to cause Judah to sin. ^36And now therefore thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, concerning this city, whereof ye say, It is given into the hand of the king of Babylon by the sword, and by the famine, and by the pestilence: ^37Behold, I will gather them out of all the countries, whither I have driven them in mine anger, and in my wrath, and in great indignation; and I will bring them again unto this place, and I will cause them to dwell safely: ^38and they shall be my people, and I will be their God: ^39and I will give them one heart and one way, that they may fear me for ever, for the good of them, and of their children after them: ^40and I will make an everlasting covenant with them, that I will not turn away from following them, to do them good; and I will put my fear in their hearts, that they may not depart from me. ^41Yea, I will rejoice over them to do them good, and I will plant them in this land assuredly with my whole heart and with my whole soul. ^42For thus saith Jehovah: Like as I have brought all this great evil upon this people, so will I bring upon them all the good that I have promised them. ^43And fields shall be bought in this land, whereof ye say, It is desolate, without man or beast; it is given into the hand of the Chaldeans. ^44Men shall buy fields for money, and subscribe the deeds, and seal them, and call witnesses, in the land of Benjamin, and in the places about Jerusalem, and in the cities of Judah, and in the cities of the hill-country, and in the cities of the lowland, and in the cities of the South: for I will cause their captivity to return, saith Jehovah.

Jeremiah 33

33

^1Moreover the word of Jehovah came unto Jeremiah the second time, while he was yet shut up in the court of the guard, saying, ^2Thus saith Jehovah that doeth it, Jehovah that formeth it to establish it; Jehovah is his name: ^3Call unto me, and I will answer thee, and will show thee great things, and difficult, which thou knowest not. ^4For thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, concerning the houses of this city, and concerning the houses of the kings of Judah, which are broken down to make a defence against the mounds and against the sword; ^5while men come to fight with the Chaldeans, and to fill them with the dead bodies of men, whom I have slain in mine anger and in my wrath, and for all whose wickedness I have hid my face from this city: ^6Behold, I will bring it health and cure, and I will cure them; and I will reveal unto them abundance of peace and truth. ^7And I will cause the captivity of Judah and the captivity of Israel to return, and will build them, as at the first. ^8And I will cleanse them from all their iniquity, whereby they have sinned against me; and I will pardon all their iniquities, whereby they have sinned against me, and whereby they have transgressed against me. ^9And this city shall be to me for a name of joy, for a praise and for a glory, before all the nations of the earth, which shall hear all the good that I do unto them, and shall fear and tremble for all the good and for all the peace that I procure unto it. ^10Thus saith Jehovah: Yet again there shall be heard in this place, whereof ye say, It is waste, without man and without beast, even in the cities of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem, that are desolate, without man and without inhabitant and without beast, ^11the voice of joy and the voice of gladness, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, the voice of them that say, Give thanks to Jehovah of hosts, for Jehovah is good, for his lovingkindness endureth for ever; and of them that bring sacrifices of thanksgiving into the house of Jehovah. For I will cause the captivity of the land to return as at the first, saith Jehovah. ^12Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Yet again shall there be in this place, which is waste, without man and without beast, and in all the cities thereof, a habitation of shepherds causing their flocks to lie down. ^13In the cities of the hill-country, in the cities of the lowland, and in the cities of the South, and in the land of Benjamin, and in the places about Jerusalem, and in the cities of Judah, shall the flocks again pass under the hands of him that numbereth them, saith Jehovah. ^14Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will perform that good word which I have spoken concerning the house of Israel and concerning the house of Judah. ^15In those days, and at that time, will I cause a Branch of righteousness to grow up unto David; and he shall execute justice and righteousness in the land. ^16In those days shall Judah be saved, and Jerusalem shall dwell safely; and this is the name whereby she shall be called: Jehovah our righteousness. ^17For thus saith Jehovah: David shall never want a man to sit upon the throne of the house of Israel; ^18neither shall the priests the Levites want a man before me to offer burnt-offerings, and to burn meal-offerings, and to do sacrifice continually. ^19And the word of Jehovah came unto Jeremiah, saying, ^20Thus saith Jehovah: If ye can break my covenant of the day, and my covenant of the night, so that there shall not be day and night in their season; ^21then may also my covenant be broken with David my servant, that he shall not have a son to reign upon his throne; and with the Levites the priests, my ministers. ^22As the host of heaven cannot be numbered, neither the sand of the sea measured; so will I multiply the seed of David my servant, and the Levites that minister unto me. ^23And the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah, saying, ^24Considerest thou not what this people have spoken, saying, The two families which Jehovah did choose, he hath cast them off? thus do they despise my people, that they should be no more a nation before them. ^25Thus saith Jehovah: If my covenant of day and night stand not, if I have not appointed the ordinances of heaven and earth; ^26then will I also cast away the seed of Jacob, and of David my servant, so that I will not take of his seed to be rulers over the seed of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob: for I will cause their captivity to return, and will have mercy on them.

Jeremiah 35

35

^1The word which came unto Jeremiah from Jehovah in the days of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, saying, ^2Go unto the house of the Rechabites, and speak unto them, and bring them into the house of Jehovah, into one of the chambers, and give them wine to drink. ^3Then I took Jaazaniah the son of Jeremiah, the son of Habazziniah, and his brethren, and all his sons, and the whole house of the Rechabites; ^4and I brought them into the house of Jehovah, into the chamber of the sons of Hanan the son of Igdaliah, the man of God, which was by the chamber of the princes, which was above the chamber of Maaseiah the son of Shallum, the keeper of the threshold. ^5And I set before the sons of the house of the Rechabites bowls full of wine, and cups; and I said unto them, Drink ye wine. ^6But they said, We will drink no wine; for Jonadab the son of Rechab, our father, commanded us, saying, Ye shall drink no wine, neither ye, nor your sons, for ever: ^7neither shall ye build house, nor sow seed, nor plant vineyard, nor have any; but all your days ye shall dwell in tents; that ye may live many days in the land wherein ye sojourn. ^8And we have obeyed the voice of Jonadab the son of Rechab, our father, in all that he charged us, to drink no wine all our days, we, our wives, our sons, or our daughters; ^9nor to build houses for us to dwell in; neither have we vineyard, nor field, nor seed: ^10but we have dwelt in tents, and have obeyed, and done according to all that Jonadab our father commanded us. ^11But it came to pass, when Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon came up into the land, that we said, Come, and let us go to Jerusalem for fear of the army of the Chaldeans, and for fear of the army of the Syrians; so we dwell at Jerusalem. ^12Then came the word of Jehovah unto Jeremiah, saying, ^13Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Go, and say to the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, Will ye not receive instruction to hearken to my words? saith Jehovah. ^14The words of Jonadab the son of Rechab, that he commanded his sons, not to drink wine, are performed; and unto this day they drink none, for they obey their father's commandment: but I have spoken unto you, rising up early and speaking; and ye have not hearkened unto me. ^15I have sent also unto you all my servants the prophets, rising up early and sending them, saying, Return ye now every man from his evil way, and amend your doings, and go not after other gods to serve them, and ye shall dwell in the land which I have given to you and to your fathers: but ye have not inclined your ear, nor hearkened unto me. ^16Forasmuch as the sons of Jonadab the son of Rechab have performed the commandment of their father which he commanded them, but this people hath not hearkened unto me; ^17therefore thus saith Jehovah, the God of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will bring upon Judah and upon all the inhabitants of Jerusalem all the evil that I have pronounced against them; because I have spoken unto them, but they have not heard; and I have called unto them, but they have not answered. ^18And Jeremiah said unto the house of the Rechabites, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Because ye have obeyed the commandment of Jonadab your father, and kept all his precepts, and done according unto all that he commanded you; ^19therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Jonadab the son of Rechab shall not want a man to stand before me for ever.

Jeremiah 36

36

^1And it came to pass in the fourth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, that this word came unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying, ^2Take thee a roll of a book, and write therein all the words that I have spoken unto thee against Israel, and against Judah, and against all the nations, from the day I spake unto thee, from the days of Josiah, even unto this day. ^3It may be that the house of Judah will hear all the evil which I purpose to do unto them; that they may return every man from his evil way; that I may forgive their iniquity and their sin. ^4Then Jeremiah called Baruch the son of Neriah; and Baruch wrote from the mouth of Jeremiah all the words of Jehovah, which he had spoken unto him, upon a roll of a book. ^5And Jeremiah commanded Baruch, saying, I am shut up; I cannot go into the house of Jehovah: ^6therefore go thou, and read in the roll, which thou hast written from my mouth, the words of Jehovah in the ears of the people in Jehovah's house upon the fast-day; and also thou shalt read them in the ears of all Judah that come out of their cities. ^7It may be they will present their supplication before Jehovah, and will return every one from his evil way; for great is the anger and the wrath that Jehovah hath pronounced against this people. ^8And Baruch the son of Neriah did according to all that Jeremiah the prophet commanded him, reading in the book the words of Jehovah in Jehovah's house. ^9Now it came to pass in the fifth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, in the ninth month, that all the people in Jerusalem, and all the people that came from the cities of Judah unto Jerusalem, proclaimed a fast before Jehovah. ^10Then read Baruch in the book the words of Jeremiah in the house of Jehovah, in the chamber of Gemariah the son of Shaphan, the scribe, in the upper court, at the entry of the new gate of Jehovah's house, in the ears of all the people. ^11And when Micaiah the son of Gemariah, the son of Shaphan, had heard out of the book all the words of Jehovah, ^12he went down into the king's house, into the scribe's chamber: and, lo, all the princes were sitting there, to wit, Elishama the scribe, and Delaiah the son of Shemaiah, and Elnathan the son of Achbor, and Gemariah the son of Shaphan, and Zedekiah the son of Hananiah, and all the princes. ^13Then Micaiah declared unto them all the words that he had heard, when Baruch read the book in the ears of the people. ^14Therefore all the princes sent Jehudi the son of Nethaniah, the son of Shelemiah, the son of Cushi, unto Baruch, saying, Take in thy hand the roll wherein thou hast read in the ears of the people, and come. So Baruch the son of Neriah took the roll in his hand, and came unto them. ^15And they said unto him, Sit down now, and read it in our ears. So Baruch read it in their ears. ^16Now it came to pass, when they had heard all the words, they turned in fear one toward another, and said unto Baruch, We will surely tell the king of all these words. ^17And they asked Baruch, saying, Tell us now, How didst thou write all these words at his mouth? ^18Then Baruch answered them, He pronounced all these words unto me with his mouth, and I wrote them with ink in the book. ^19Then said the princes unto Baruch, Go, hide thee, thou and Jeremiah; and let no man know where ye are. ^20And they went in to the king into the court; but they had laid up the roll in the chamber of Elishama the scribe; and they told all the words in the ears of the king. ^21So the king sent Jehudi to fetch the roll; and he took it out of the chamber of Elishama the scribe. And Jehudi read it in the ears of the king, and in the ears of all the princes that stood beside the king. ^22Now the king was sitting in the winter-house in the ninth month: and there was a fire in the brazier burning before him. ^23And it came to pass, when Jehudi had read three or four leaves, that the king cut it with the penknife, and cast it into the fire that was in the brazier, until all the roll was consumed in the fire that was in the brazier. ^24And they were not afraid, nor rent their garments, neither the king, nor any of his servants that heard all these words. ^25Moreover Elnathan and Delaiah and Gemariah had made intercession to the king that he would not burn the roll; but he would not hear them. ^26And the king commanded Jerahmeel the king's son, and Seraiah the son of Azriel, and Shelemiah the son of Abdeel, to take Baruch the scribe and Jeremiah the prophet; but Jehovah hid them. ^27Then the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah, after that the king had burned the roll, and the words which Baruch wrote at the mouth of Jeremiah, saying, ^28Take thee again another roll, and write in it all the former words that were in the first roll, which Jehoiakim the king of Judah hath burned. ^29And concerning Jehoiakim king of Judah thou shalt say, Thus saith Jehovah: Thou hast burned this roll, saying, Why hast thou written therein, saying, The king of Babylon shall certainly come and destroy this land, and shall cause to cease from thence man and beast? ^30Therefore thus saith Jehovah concerning Jehoiakim king of Judah: He shall have none to sit upon the throne of David; and his dead body shall be cast out in the day to the heat, and in the night to the frost. ^31And I will punish him and his seed and his servants for their iniquity; and I will bring upon them, and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and upon the men of Judah, all the evil that I have pronounced against them, but they hearkened not. ^32Then took Jeremiah another roll, and gave it to Baruch the scribe, the son of Neriah, who wrote therein from the mouth of Jeremiah all the words of the book which Jehoiakim king of Judah had burned in the fire; and there were added besides unto them many like words.

Jeremiah 37

37

^1And Zedekiah the son of Josiah reigned as king, instead of Coniah the son of Jehoiakim, whom Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon made king in the land of Judah. ^2But neither he, nor his servants, nor the people of the land, did hearken unto the words of Jehovah, which he spake by the prophet Jeremiah. ^3And Zedekiah the king sent Jehucal the son of Shelemiah, and Zephaniah the son of Maaseiah, the priest, to the prophet Jeremiah, saying, Pray now unto Jehovah our God for us. ^4Now Jeremiah came in and went out among the people; for they had not put him into prison. ^5And Pharaoh's army was come forth out of Egypt; and when the Chaldeans that were besieging Jerusalem heard tidings of them, they brake up from Jerusalem. ^6Then came the word of Jehovah unto the prophet Jeremiah, saying, ^7Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Thus shall ye say to the king of Judah, that sent you unto me to inquire of me: Behold, Pharaoh's army, which is come forth to help you, shall return to Egypt into their own land. ^8And the Chaldeans shall come again, and fight against this city; and they shall take it, and burn it with fire. ^9Thus saith Jehovah, Deceive not yourselves, saying, The Chaldeans shall surely depart from us; for they shall not depart. ^10For though ye had smitten the whole army of the Chaldeans that fight against you, and there remained but wounded men among them, yea would they rise up every man in his tent, and burn this city with fire. ^11And it came to pass that, when the army of the Chaldeans was broken up from Jerusalem for fear of Pharaoh's army, ^12then Jeremiah went forth out of Jerusalem to go into the land of Benjamin, to receive his portion there, in the midst of the people. ^13And when he was in the gate of Benjamin, a captain of the ward was there, whose name was Irijah, the son of Shelemiah, the son of Hananiah; and he laid hold on Jeremiah the prophet, saying, Thou art falling away to the Chaldeans. ^14Then said Jeremiah, It is false; I am not falling away to the Chaldeans. But he hearkened not to him; so Irijah laid hold on Jeremiah, and brought him to the princes. ^15And the princes were wroth with Jeremiah, and smote him, and put him in prison in the house of Jonathan the scribe; for they had made that the prison. ^16When Jeremiah was come into the dungeon-house, and into the cells, and Jeremiah had remained there many days; ^17Then Zedekiah the king sent, and fetched him: and the king asked him secretly in his house, and said, Is there any word from Jehovah? And Jeremiah said, There is. He said also, Thou shalt be delivered into the hand of the king of Babylon. ^18Moreover Jeremiah said unto king Zedekiah, Wherein have I sinned against thee, or against thy servants, or against this people, that ye have put me in prison? ^19Where now are your prophets that prophesied unto you, saying, The king of Babylon shall not come against you, nor against this land? ^20And now hear, I pray thee, O my lord the king: let my supplication, I pray thee, be presented before thee, that thou cause me not to return to the house of Jonathan the scribe, lest I die there. ^21Then Zedekiah the king commanded, and they committed Jeremiah into the court of the guard; and they gave him daily a loaf of bread out of the bakers' street, until all the bread in the city was spent. Thus Jeremiah remained in the court of the guard.

Jeremiah 38

38

^1And Shephatiah the son of Mattan, and Gedaliah the son of Pashhur, and Jucal the son of Shelemiah, and Pashhur the son of Malchijah, heard the words that Jeremiah spake unto all the people, saying, ^2Thus saith Jehovah, He that abideth in this city shall die by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence; but he that goeth forth to the Chaldeans shall live, and his life shall be unto him for a prey, and he shall live. ^3Thus saith Jehovah, This city shall surely be given into the hand of the army of the king of Babylon, and he shall take it. ^4Then the princes said unto the king, Let this man, we pray thee, be put to death; forasmuch as he weakeneth the hands of the men of war that remain in this city, and the hands of all the people, in speaking such words unto them: for this man seeketh not the welfare of this people, but the hurt. ^5And Zedekiah the king said, Behold, he is in your hand; for the king is not he that can do anything against you. ^6Then took they Jeremiah, and cast him into the dungeon of Malchijah the king's son, that was in the court of the guard: and they let down Jeremiah with cords. And in the dungeon there was no water, but mire; and Jeremiah sank in the mire. ^7Now when Ebed-melech the Ethiopian, a eunuch, who was in the king's house, heard that they had put Jeremiah in the dungeon (the king then sitting in the gate of Benjamin,) ^8Ebed-melech went forth out of the king's house, and spake to the king, saying, ^9My lord the king, these men have done evil in all that they have done to Jeremiah the prophet, whom they have cast into the dungeon; and he is like to die in the place where he is, because of the famine; for there is no more bread in the city. ^10Then the king commanded Ebed-melech the Ethiopian, saying, Take from hence thirty men with thee, and take up Jeremiah the prophet out of the dungeon, before he die. ^11So Ebed-melech took the men with him, and went into the house of the king under the treasury, and took thence rags and worn-out garments, and let them down by cords into the dungeon to Jeremiah. ^12And Ebed-melech the Ethiopian said unto Jeremiah, Put now these rags and worn-out garments under thine armholes under the cords. And Jeremiah did so. ^13So they drew up Jeremiah with the cords, and took him up out of the dungeon: and Jeremiah remained in the court of the guard. ^14Then Zedekiah the king sent, and took Jeremiah the prophet unto him into the third entry that is in the house of Jehovah: and the king said unto Jeremiah, I will ask thee a thing; hide nothing from me. ^15Then Jeremiah said unto Zedekiah, If I declare it unto thee, wilt thou not surely put me to death? and if I give thee counsel, thou wilt not hearken unto me. ^16So Zedekiah the king sware secretly unto Jeremiah, saying, As Jehovah liveth, that made us this soul, I will not put thee to death, neither will I give thee into the hand of these men that seek thy life. ^17Then said Jeremiah unto Zedekiah, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of hosts, the God of Israel: If thou wilt go forth unto the king of Babylon's princes, then thy soul shall live, and this city shall not be burned with fire; and thou shalt live, and thy house. ^18But if thou wilt not go forth to the king of Babylon's princes, then shall this city be given into the hand of the Chaldeans, and they shall burn it with fire, and thou shalt not escape out of their hand. ^19And Zedekiah the king said unto Jeremiah, I am afraid of the Jews that are fallen away to the Chaldeans, lest they deliver me into their hand, and they mock me. ^20But Jeremiah said, They shall not deliver thee. Obey, I beseech thee, the voice of Jehovah, in that which I speak unto thee: so it shall be well with thee, and thy soul shall live. ^21But if thou refuse to go forth, this is the word that Jehovah hath showed me: ^22behold, all the women that are left in the king of Judah's house shall be brought forth to the king of Babylon's princes, and those women shall say, Thy familiar friends have set thee on, and have prevailed over thee: now that thy feet are sunk in the mire, they are turned away back. ^23And they shall bring out all thy wives and thy children to the Chaldeans; and thou shalt not escape out of their hand, but shalt be taken by the hand of the king of Babylon: and thou shalt cause this city to be burned with fire. ^24Then said Zedekiah unto Jeremiah, Let no man know of these words, and thou shalt not die. ^25But if the princes hear that I have talked with thee, and they come unto thee, and say unto thee, Declare unto us now what thou hast said unto the king; hide it not from us, and we will not put thee to death; also what the king said unto thee: ^26then thou shalt say unto them, I presented my supplication before the king, that he would not cause me to return to Jonathan's house, to die there. ^27Then came all the princes unto Jeremiah, and asked him; and he told them according to all these words that the king had commanded. So they left off speaking with him; for the matter was not perceived. ^28So Jeremiah abode in the court of the guard until the day that Jerusalem was taken.

Jeremiah 39

39

^1And it came to pass when Jerusalem was taken, (in the ninth year of Zedekiah king of Judah, in the tenth month, came Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon and all his army against Jerusalem, and besieged it; ^2in the eleventh year of Zedekiah, in the fourth month, the ninth day of the month, a breach was made in the city,) ^3that all the princes of the king of Babylon came in, and sat in the middle gate, to wit, Nergal-sharezer, Samgar-nebo, Sarsechim, Rab-saris, Nergal-sharezer, Rab-mag, with all the rest of the princes of the king of Babylon. ^4And it came to pass that, when Zedekiah the king of Judah and all the men of war saw them, then they fled, and went forth out of the city by night, by the way of the king's garden, through the gate betwixt the two walls; and he went out toward the Arabah. ^5But the army of the Chaldeans pursued after them, and overtook Zedekiah in the plains of Jericho: and when they had taken him, they brought him up to Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon to Riblah in the land of Hamath; and he gave judgment upon him. ^6Then the king of Babylon slew the sons of Zedekiah in Riblah before his eyes: also the king of Babylon slew all the nobles of Judah. ^7Moreover he put out Zedekiah's eyes, and bound him in fetters, to carry him to Babylon. ^8And the Chaldeans burned the king's house, and the houses of the people, with fire, and brake down the walls of Jerusalem. ^9Then Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard carried away captive into Babylon the residue of the people that remained in the city, the deserters also that fell away to him, and the residue of the people that remained. ^10But Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard left of the poor of the people, that had nothing, in the land of Judah, and gave them vineyards and fields at the same time. ^11Now Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon gave charge concerning Jeremiah to Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard, saying, ^12Take him, and look well to him, and do him no harm; but do unto him even as he shall say unto thee. ^13So Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard sent, and Nebushazban, Rab-saris, and Nergal-sharezer, Rab-mag, and all the chief officers of the king of Babylon; ^14they sent, and took Jeremiah out of the court of the guard, and committed him unto Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, that he should carry him home: so he dwelt among the people. ^15Now the word of Jehovah came unto Jeremiah, while he was shut up in the court of the guard, saying, ^16Go, and speak to Ebed-melech the Ethiopian, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will bring my words upon this city for evil, and not for good; and they shall be accomplished before thee in that day. ^17But I will deliver thee in that day, saith Jehovah; and thou shalt not be given into the hand of the men of whom thou art afraid. ^18For I will surely save thee, and thou shalt not fall by the sword, but thy life shall be for a prey unto thee; because thou hast put thy trust in me, saith Jehovah.

Jeremiah 40

40

^1The word which came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, after that Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard had let him go from Ramah, when he had taken him being bound in chains among all the captives of Jerusalem and Judah, that were carried away captive unto Babylon. ^2And the captain of the guard took Jeremiah, and said unto him, Jehovah thy God pronounced this evil upon this place; ^3and Jehovah hath brought it, and done according as he spake: because ye have sinned against Jehovah, and have not obeyed his voice, therefore this thing is come upon you. ^4And now, behold, I loose thee this day from the chains which are upon thy hand. If it seem good unto thee to come with me into Babylon, come, and I will look well unto thee; but if it seem ill unto thee to come with me into Babylon, forbear: behold, all the land is before thee; whither it seemeth good and right unto thee to go, thither go. ^5Now while he was not yet gone back, Go back then, said he, to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, whom the king of Babylon hath made governor over the cities of Judah, and dwell with him among the people; or go wheresoever it seemeth right unto thee to go. So the captain of the guard gave him victuals and a present, and let him go. ^6Then went Jeremiah unto Gedaliah the son of Ahikam to Mizpah, and dwelt with him among the people that were left in the land. ^7Now when all the captains of the forces that were in the fields, even they and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had made Gedaliah the son of Ahikam governor in the land, and had committed unto him men, and women, and children, and of the poorest of the land, of them that were not carried away captive to Babylon; ^8then they came to Gedaliah to Mizpah, to wit, Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and Johanan and Jonathan the sons of Kareah, and Seraiah the son of Tanhumeth, and the sons of Ephai the Netophathite, and Jezaniah the son of the Maacathite, they and their men. ^9And Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the son of Shaphan sware unto them and to their men, saying, Fear not to serve the Chaldeans: dwell in the land, and serve the king of Babylon, and it shall be well with you. ^10As for me, behold, I will dwell at Mizpah, to stand before the Chaldeans that shall come unto us: but ye, gather ye wine and summer fruits and oil, and put them in your vessels, and dwell in your cities that ye have taken. ^11Likewise when all the Jews that were in Moab, and among the children of Ammon, and in Edom, and that were in all the countries, heard that the king of Babylon had left a remnant of Judah, and that he had set over them Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan; ^12then all the Jews returned out of all places whither they were driven, and came to the land of Judah, to Gedaliah, unto Mizpah, and gathered wine and summer fruits very much. ^13Moreover Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces that were in the fields, came to Gedaliah to Mizpah, ^14and said unto him, Dost thou know that Baalis the king of the children of Ammon hath sent Ishmael the son of Nethaniah to take thy life? But Gedaliah the son of Ahikam believed them not. ^15Then Johanan the son of Kareah spake to Gedaliah in Mizpah secretly, saying, Let me go, I pray thee, and I will slay Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and no man shall know it: wherefore should he take thy life, that all the Jews that are gathered unto thee should be scattered, and the remnant of Judah perish? ^16But Gedaliah the son of Ahikam said unto Johanan the son of Kareah, Thou shalt not do this thing; for thou speakest falsely of Ishmael.

Jeremiah 41

41

^1Now it came to pass in the seventh month, that Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, the son of Elishama, of the seed royal and one of the chief officers of the king, and ten men with him, came unto Gedaliah the son of Ahikam to Mizpah; and there they did eat bread together in Mizpah. ^2Then arose Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and the ten men that were with him, and smote Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the son of Shaphan with the sword, and slew him, whom the king of Babylon had made governor over the land. ^3Ishmael also slew all the Jews that were with him, to wit, with Gedaliah, at Mizpah, and the Chaldeans that were found there, the men of war. ^4And it came to pass the second day after he had slain Gedaliah, and no man knew it, ^5that there came men from Shechem, from Shiloh, and from Samaria, even fourscore men, having their beards shaven and their clothes rent, and having cut themselves, with meal-offerings and frankincense in their hand, to bring them to the house of Jehovah. ^6And Ishmael the son of Nethaniah went forth from Mizpah to meet them, weeping all along as he went: and it came to pass, as he met them, he said unto them, Come to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam. ^7And it was so, when they came into the midst of the city, that Ishmael the son of Nethaniah slew them, and cast them into the midst of the pit, he, and the men that were with him. ^8But ten men were found among them that said unto Ishmael, Slay us not; for we have stores hidden in the field, of wheat, and of barley, and of oil, and of honey. So he forbare, and slew them not among their brethren. ^9Now the pit wherein Ishmael cast all the dead bodies of the men whom he had slain, by the side of Gedaliah (the same was that which Asa the king had made for fear of Baasha king of Israel,) Ishmael the son of Nethaniah filled it with them that were slain. ^10Then Ishmael carried away captive all the residue of the people that were in Mizpah, even the king's daughters, and all the people that remained in Mizpah, whom Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard had committed to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam; Ishmael the son of Nethaniah carried them away captive, and departed to go over to the children of Ammon. ^11But when Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces that were with him, heard of all the evil that Ishmael the son of Nethaniah had done, ^12then they took all the men, and went to fight with Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and found him by the great waters that are in Gibeon. ^13Now it came to pass that, when all the people that were with Ishmael saw Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces that were with him, then they were glad. ^14So all the people that Ishmael had carried away captive from Mizpah turned about and came back, and went unto Johanan the son of Kareah. ^15But Ishmael the son of Nethaniah escaped from Johanan with eight men, and went to the children of Ammon. ^16Then took Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces that were with him, all the remnant of the people whom he had recovered from Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, from Mizpah, after that he had slain Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, to wit, the men of war, and the women, and the children, and the eunuchs, whom he had brought back from Gibeon: ^17and they departed, and dwelt in Geruth Chimham, which is by Beth-lehem, to go to enter into Egypt, ^18because of the Chaldeans; for they were afraid of them, because Ishmael the son of Nethaniah had slain Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, whom the king of Babylon made governor over the land.

Jeremiah 42

42

^1Then all the captains of the forces, and Johanan the son of Kareah, and Jezaniah the son of Hoshaiah, and all the people from the least even unto the greatest, came near, ^2and said unto Jeremiah the prophet, Let, we pray thee, our supplication be presented before thee, and pray for us unto Jehovah thy God, even for all this remnant; for we are left but a few of many, as thine eyes do behold us: ^3that Jehovah thy God may show us the way wherein we should walk, and the thing that we should do. ^4Then Jeremiah the prophet said unto them, I have heard you; behold, I will pray unto Jehovah your God according to your words; and it shall come to pass that whatsoever thing Jehovah shall answer you, I will declare it unto you; I will keep nothing back from you. ^5Then they said to Jeremiah, Jehovah be a true and faithful witness amongst us, if we do not according to all the word wherewith Jehovah thy God shall send thee to us. ^6Whether it be good, or whether it be evil, we will obey the voice of Jehovah our God, to whom we send thee; that it may be well with us, when we obey the voice of Jehovah our God. ^7And it came to pass after ten days, that the word of Jehovah came unto Jeremiah. ^8Then called he Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces that were with him, and all the people from the least even to the greatest, ^9and said unto them, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, unto whom ye sent me to present your supplication before him: ^10If ye will still abide in this land, then will I build you, and not pull you down, and I will plant you, and not pluck you up; for I repent me of the evil that I have done unto you. ^11Be not afraid of the king of Babylon, of whom ye are afraid; be not afraid of him, saith Jehovah: for I am with you to save you, and to deliver you from his hand. ^12And I will grant you mercy, that he may have mercy upon you, and cause you to return to your own land. ^13But if ye say, We will not dwell in this land; so that ye obey not the voice of Jehovah your God, ^14saying, No; but we will go into the land of Egypt, where we shall see no war, nor hear the sound of the trumpet, nor have hunger of bread; and there will we dwell: ^15now therefore hear ye the word of Jehovah, O remnant of Judah: Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, If ye indeed set your faces to enter into Egypt, and go to sojourn there; ^16then it shall come to pass, that the sword, which ye fear, shall overtake you there in the land of Egypt; and the famine, whereof ye are afraid, shall follow hard after you there in Egypt; and there ye shall die. ^17So shall it be with all the men that set their faces to go into Egypt to sojourn there: they shall die by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence; and none of them shall remain or escape from the evil that I will bring upon them. ^18For thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: As mine anger and my wrath hath been poured forth upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so shall my wrath be poured forth upon you, when ye shall enter into Egypt; and ye shall be an execration, and an astonishment, and a curse, and a reproach; and ye shall see this place no more. ^19Jehovah hath spoken concerning you, O remnant of Judah, Go ye not into Egypt: know certainly that I have testified unto you this day. ^20For ye have dealt deceitfully against your own souls; for ye sent me unto Jehovah your God, saying, Pray for us unto Jehovah our God; and according unto all that Jehovah our God shall say, so declare unto us, and we will do it: ^21and I have this day declared it to you; but ye have not obeyed the voice of Jehovah your God in anything for which he hath sent me unto you. ^22Now therefore know certainly that ye shall die by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence, in the place whither ye desire to go to sojourn there.

Jeremiah 44

44

^1The word that came to Jeremiah concerning all the Jews that dwelt in the land of Egypt, that dwelt at Migdol, and at Tahpanhes, and at Memphis, and in the country of Pathros, saying, ^2Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Ye have seen all the evil that I have brought upon Jerusalem, and upon all the cities of Judah; and, behold, this day they are a desolation, and no man dwelleth therein, ^3because of their wickedness which they have committed to provoke me to anger, in that they went to burn incense, and to serve other gods, that they knew not, neither they, nor ye, nor your fathers. ^4Howbeit I sent unto you all my servants the prophets, rising up early and sending them, saying, Oh, do not this abominable thing that I hate. ^5But they hearkened not, nor inclined their ear to turn from their wickedness, to burn no incense unto other gods. ^6Wherefore my wrath and mine anger was poured forth, and was kindled in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem; and they are wasted and desolate, as it is this day. ^7Therefore now thus saith Jehovah, the God of hosts, the God of Israel: Wherefore commit ye this great evil against your own souls, to cut off from you man and woman, infant and suckling, out of the midst of Judah, to leave you none remaining; ^8in that ye provoke me unto anger with the works of your hands, burning incense unto other gods in the land of Egypt, whither ye are gone to sojourn; that ye may be cut off, and that ye may be a curse and a reproach among all the nations of the earth? ^9Have ye forgotten the wickedness of your fathers, and the wickedness of the kings of Judah, and the wickedness of their wives, and your own wickedness, and the wickedness of your wives which they committed in the land of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem? ^10They are not humbled even unto this day, neither have they feared, nor walked in my law, nor in my statutes, that I set before you and before your fathers. ^11Therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will set my face against you for evil, even to cut off all Judah. ^12And I will take the remnant of Judah, that have set their faces to go into the land of Egypt to sojourn there, and they shall all be consumed; in the land of Egypt shall they fall; they shall be consumed by the sword and by the famine; they shall die, from the least even unto the greatest, by the sword and by the famine; and they shall be an execration, and an astonishment, and a curse, and a reproach. ^13For I will punish them that dwell in the land of Egypt, as I have punished Jerusalem, by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence; ^14so that none of the remnant of Judah, that are gone into the land of Egypt to sojourn there, shall escape or be left, to return into the land of Judah, to which they have a desire to return to dwell there: for none shall return save such as shall escape. ^15Then all the men who knew that their wives burned incense unto other gods, and all the women that stood by, a great assembly, even all the people that dwelt in the land of Egypt, in Pathros, answered Jeremiah, saying, ^16As for the word that thou hast spoken unto us in the name of Jehovah, we will not hearken unto thee. ^17But we will certainly perform every word that is gone forth out of our mouth, to burn incense unto the queen of heaven, and to pour out drink-offerings unto her, as we have done, we and our fathers, our kings and our princes, in the cities of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem; for then had we plenty of victuals, and were well, and saw no evil. ^18But since we left off burning incense to the queen of heaven, and pouring out drink-offerings unto her, we have wanted all things, and have been consumed by the sword and by the famine. ^19And when we burned incense to the queen of heaven, and poured out drink-offerings unto her, did we make her cakes to worship her, and pour out drink-offerings unto her, without our husbands? ^20Then Jeremiah said unto all the people, to the men, and to the women, even to all the people that had given him that answer, saying, ^21The incense that ye burned in the cities of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem, ye and your fathers, your kings and your princes, and the people of the land, did not Jehovah remember them, and came it not into his mind? ^22so that Jehovah could not longer bear, because of the evil of your doings, and because of the abominations which ye have committed; therefore is your land become a desolation, and an astonishment, and a curse, without inhabitant, as it is this day. ^23Because ye have burned incense, and because ye have sinned against Jehovah, and have not obeyed the voice of Jehovah, nor walked in his law, nor in his statutes, nor in his testimonies; therefore this evil is happened unto you, as it is this day. ^24Moreover Jeremiah said unto all the people, and to all the women, Hear the word of Jehovah, all Judah that are in the land of Egypt: ^25Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, saying, Ye and your wives have both spoken with your mouths, and with your hands have fulfilled it, saying, We will surely perform our vows that we have vowed, to burn incense to the queen of heaven, and to pour out drink-offerings unto her: establish then your vows, and perform your vows. ^26Therefore hear ye the word of Jehovah, all Judah that dwell in the land of Egypt: Behold, I have sworn by my great name, saith Jehovah, that my name shall no more be named in the mouth of any man of Judah in all the land of Egypt, saying, As the Lord Jehovah liveth. ^27Behold, I watch over them for evil, and not for good; and all the men of Judah that are in the land of Egypt shall be consumed by the sword and by the famine, until there be an end of them. ^28And they that escape the sword shall return out of the land of Egypt into the land of Judah, few in number; and all the remnant of Judah, that are gone into the land of Egypt to sojourn there, shall know whose word shall stand, mine, or theirs. ^29And this shall be the sign unto you, saith Jehovah, that I will punish you in this place, that ye may know that my words shall surely stand against you for evil: ^30Thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will give Pharaoh Hophra king of Egypt into the hand of his enemies, and into the hand of them that seek his life; as I gave Zedekiah king of Judah into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, who was his enemy, and sought his life.

Jeremiah 46

46

^1The word of Jehovah which came to Jeremiah the prophet concerning the nations. ^2Of Egypt: concerning the army of Pharaoh-neco king of Egypt, which was by the river Euphrates in Carchemish, which Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon smote in the fourth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah. ^3Prepare ye the buckler and shield, and draw near to battle. ^4Harness the horses, and get up, ye horsemen, and stand forth with your helmets; furbish the spears, put on the coats of mail. ^5Wherefore have I seen it? they are dismayed and are turned backward; and their mighty ones are beaten down, and are fled apace, and look not back: terror is on every side, saith Jehovah. ^6Let not the swift flee away, nor the mighty man escape; in the north by the river Euphrates have they stumbled and fallen. ^7Who is this that riseth up like the Nile, whose waters toss themselves like the rivers? ^8Egypt riseth up like the Nile, and his waters toss themselves like the rivers: and he saith, I will rise up, I will cover the earth; I will destroy cities and the inhabitants thereof. ^9Go up, ye horses; and rage, ye chariots; and let the mighty men go forth: Cush and Put, that handle the shield; and the Ludim, that handle and bend the bow. ^10For that day is a day of the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, a day of vengeance, that he may avenge him of his adversaries: and the sword shall devour and be satiate, and shall drink its fill of their blood; for the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, hath a sacrifice in the north country by the river Euphrates. ^11Go up into Gilead, and take balm, O virgin daughter of Egypt: in vain dost thou use many medicines; there is no healing for thee. ^12The nations have heard of thy shame, and the earth is full of thy cry; for the mighty man hath stumbled against the mighty, they are fallen both of them together. ^13The word that Jehovah spake to Jeremiah the prophet, how that Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon should come and smite the land of Egypt. ^14Declare ye in Egypt, and publish in Migdol, and publish in Memphis and in Tahpanhes: say ye, Stand forth, and prepare thee; for the sword hath devoured round about thee. ^15Why are thy strong ones swept away? they stood not, because Jehovah did drive them. ^16He made many to stumble, yea, they fell one upon another: and they said, Arise, and let us go again to our own people, and to the land of our nativity, from the oppressing sword. ^17They cried there, Pharaoh king of Egypt is but a noise; he hath let the appointed time pass by. ^18As I live, saith the King, whose name is Jehovah of hosts, surely like Tabor among the mountains, and like Carmel by the sea, so shall he come. ^19O thou daughter that dwellest in Egypt, furnish thyself to go into captivity; for Memphis shall become a desolation, and shall be burnt up, without inhabitant. ^20Egypt is a very fair heifer; but destruction out of the north is come, it is come. ^21Also her hired men in the midst of her are like calves of the stall; for they also are turned back, they are fled away together, they did not stand: for the day of their calamity is come upon them, the time of their visitation. ^22The sound thereof shall go like the serpent; for they shall march with an army, and come against her with axes, as hewers of wood. ^23They shall cut down her forest, saith Jehovah, though it cannot be searched; because they are more than the locusts, and are innumerable. ^24The daughter of Egypt shall be put to shame; she shall be delivered into the hand of the people of the north. ^25Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, saith: Behold, I will punish Amon of No, and Pharaoh, and Egypt, with her gods, and her kings; even Pharaoh, and them that trust in him: ^26and I will deliver them into the hand of those that seek their lives, and into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of his servants; and afterwards it shall be inhabited, as in the days of old, saith Jehovah. ^27But fear not thou, O Jacob my servant, neither be dismayed, O Israel: for, lo, I will save thee from afar, and thy seed from the land of their captivity; and Jacob shall return, and shall be quiet and at ease, and none shall make him afraid. ^28Fear not thou, O Jacob my servant, saith Jehovah; for I am with thee: for I will make a full end of all the nations whither I have driven thee; but I will not make a full end of thee, but I will correct thee in measure, and will in no wise leave thee unpunished.

Jeremiah 47

47

^1The word of Jehovah that came to Jeremiah the prophet concerning the Philistines, before that Pharaoh smote Gaza. ^2Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, waters rise up out of the north, and shall become an overflowing stream, and shall overflow the land and all that is therein, the city and them that dwell therein; and the men shall cry, and all the inhabitants of the land shall wail. ^3At the noise of the stamping of the hoofs of his strong ones, at the rushing of his chariots, at the rumbling of his wheels, the fathers look not back to their children for feebleness of hands; ^4because of the day that cometh to destroy all the Philistines, to cut off from Tyre and Sidon every helper that remaineth: for Jehovah will destroy the Philistines, the remnant of the isle of Caphtor. ^5Baldness is come upon Gaza; Ashkelon is brought to nought, the remnant of their valley: how long wilt thou cut thyself? ^6O thou sword of Jehovah, how long will it be ere thou be quiet? put up thyself into thy scabbard; rest, and be still. ^7How canst thou be quiet, seeing Jehovah hath given thee a charge? Against Ashkelon, and against the sea-shore, there hath he appointed it.

Jeremiah 48

48

^1Of Moab. Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Woe unto Nebo! for it is laid waste; Kiriathaim is put to shame, it is taken; Misgab is put to shame and broken down. ^2The praise of Moab is no more; in Heshbon they have devised evil against her: Come, and let us cut her off from being a nation. Thou also, O Madmen, shalt be brought to silence: the sword shall pursue thee. ^3The sound of a cry from Horonaim, desolation and great destruction! ^4Moab is destroyed; her little ones have caused a cry to be heard. ^5For by the ascent of Luhith with continual weeping shall they go up; for at the descent of Horonaim they have heard the distress of the cry of destruction. ^6Flee, save your lives, and be like the heath in the wilderness. ^7For, because thou hast trusted in thy works and in thy treasures, thou also shalt be taken: and Chemosh shall go forth into captivity, his priests and his princes together. ^8And the destroyer shall come upon every city, and no city shall escape; the valley also shall perish, and the plain shall be destroyed; as Jehovah hath spoken. ^9Give wings unto Moab, that she may fly and get her away: and her cities shall become a desolation, without any to dwell therein. ^10Cursed be he that doeth the work of Jehovah negligently; and cursed be he that keepeth back his sword from blood. ^11Moab hath been at ease from his youth, and he hath settled on his lees, and hath not been emptied from vessel to vessel, neither hath he gone into captivity: therefore his taste remaineth in him, and his scent is not changed. ^12Therefore, behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will send unto him them that pour off, and they shall pour him off; and they shall empty his vessels, and break their bottles in pieces. ^13And Moab shall be ashamed of Chemosh, as the house of Israel was ashamed of Beth-el their confidence. ^14How say ye, We are mighty men, and valiant men for the war? ^15Moab is laid waste, and they are gone up into his cities, and his chosen young men are gone down to the slaughter, saith the King, whose name is Jehovah of hosts. ^16The calamity of Moab is near to come, and his affliction hasteth fast. ^17All ye that are round about him, bemoan him, and all ye that know his name; say, How is the strong staff broken, the beautiful rod! ^18O thou daughter that dwellest in Dibon, come down from thy glory, and sit in thirst; for the destroyer of Moab is come up against thee, he hath destroyed thy strongholds. ^19O inhabitant of Aroer, stand by the way, and watch: ask him that fleeth, and her that escapeth; say, What hath been done? ^20Moab is put to shame; for it is broken down: wail and cry; tell ye it by the Arnon, that Moab is laid waste. ^21And judgment is come upon the plain country, upon Holon, and upon Jahzah, and upon Mephaath, ^22and upon Dibon, and upon Nebo, and upon Beth-diblathaim, ^23and upon Kiriathaim, and upon Beth-gamul, and upon Beth-meon, ^24and upon Kerioth, and upon Bozrah, and upon all the cities of the land of Moab, far or near. ^25The horn of Moab is cut off, and his arm is broken, saith Jehovah. ^26Make ye him drunken; for he magnified himself against Jehovah: and Moab shall wallow in his vomit, and he also shall be in derision. ^27For was not Israel a derision unto thee? was he found among thieves? for as often as thou speakest of him, thou waggest the head. ^28O ye inhabitants of Moab, leave the cities, and dwell in the rock; and be like the dove that maketh her nest over the mouth of the abyss. ^29We have heard of the pride of Moab, that he is very proud; his loftiness, and his pride, and his arrogancy, and the haughtiness of his heart. ^30I know his wrath, saith Jehovah, that it is nought; his boastings have wrought nothing. ^31Therefore will I wail for Moab; yea, I will cry out for all Moab: for the men of Kir-heres shall they mourn. ^32With more than the weeping of Jazer will I weep for thee, O vine of Sibmah: thy branches passed over the sea, they reached even to the sea of Jazer: upon thy summer fruits and upon thy vintage the destroyer is fallen. ^33And gladness and joy is taken away from the fruitful field and from the land of Moab; and I have caused wine to cease from the winepresses: none shall tread with shouting; the shouting shall be no shouting. ^34From the cry of Heshbon even unto Elealeh, even unto Jahaz have they uttered their voice, from Zoar even unto Horonaim, to Eglath-shelishiyah: for the waters of Nimrim also shall become desolate. ^35Moreover I will cause to cease in Moab, saith Jehovah, him that offereth in the high place, and him that burneth incense to his gods. ^36Therefore my heart soundeth for Moab like pipes, and my heart soundeth like pipes for the men of Kir-heres: therefore the abundance that he hath gotten is perished. ^37For every head is bald, and every beard clipped: upon all the hands are cuttings, and upon the loins sackcloth. ^38On all the housetops of Moab and in the streets thereof there is lamentation every where; for I have broken Moab like a vessel wherein none delighteth, saith Jehovah. ^39How is it broken down! how do they wail! how hath Moab turned the back with shame! so shall Moab become a derision and a terror to all that are round about him. ^40For thus saith Jehovah: Behold, he shall fly as an eagle, and shall spread out his wings against Moab. ^41Kerioth is taken, and the strongholds are seized, and the heart of the mighty men of Moab at that day shall be as the heart of a woman in her pangs. ^42And Moab shall be destroyed from being a people, because he hath magnified himself against Jehovah. ^43Fear, and the pit, and the snare, are upon thee, O inhabitant of Moab, saith Jehovah. ^44He that fleeth from the fear shall fall into the pit; and he that getteth up out of the pit shall be taken in the snare: for I will bring upon him, even upon Moab, the year of their visitation, saith Jehovah. ^45They that fled stand without strength under the shadow of Heshbon; for a fire is gone forth out of Heshbon, and a flame from the midst of Sihon, and hath devoured the corner of Moab, and the crown of the head of the tumultuous ones. ^46Woe unto thee, O Moab! the people of Chemosh is undone; for thy sons are taken away captive, and thy daughters into captivity. ^47Yet will I bring back the captivity of Moab in the latter days, saith Jehovah. Thus far is the judgment of Moab.

Jeremiah 49

49

^1Of the children of Ammon. Thus saith Jehovah: Hath Israel no sons? hath he no heir? why then doth Malcam possess Gad, and his people well in the cities thereof? ^2Therefore, behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will cause an alarm of war to be heard against Rabbah of the children of Ammon; and it shall become a desolate heap, and her daughters shall be burned with fire: then shall Israel possess them that did possess him, saith Jehovah. ^3Wail, O Heshbon, for Ai is laid waste; cry, ye daughters of Rabbah, gird you with sackcloth: lament, and run to and fro among the fences; for Malcam shall go into captivity, his priests and his princes together. ^4Wherefore gloriest thou in the valleys, thy flowing valley, O backsliding daughter? that trusted in her treasures, saying, Who shall come unto me? ^5Behold, I will bring a fear upon thee, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, from all that are round about thee; and ye shall be driven out every man right forth, and there shall be none to gather together the fugitives. ^6But afterward I will bring back the captivity of the children of Ammon, saith Jehovah. ^7Of Edom. Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Is wisdom no more in Teman? is counsel perished from the prudent? is their wisdom vanished? ^8Flee ye, turn back, dwell in the depths, O inhabitants of Dedan; for I will bring the calamity of Esau upon him, the time that I shall visit him. ^9If grape-gatherers came to thee, would they not leave some gleaning grapes? if thieves by night, would they not destroy till they had enough? ^10But I have made Esau bare, I have uncovered his secret places, and he shall not be able to hide himself: his seed is destroyed, and his brethren, and his neighbors; and he is not. ^11Leave thy fatherless children, I will preserve them alive; and let thy widows trust in me. ^12For thus saith Jehovah: Behold, they to whom it pertained not to drink of the cup shall assuredly drink; and art thou he that shall altogether go unpunished? thou shalt not go unpunished, but thou shalt surely drink. ^13For I have sworn by myself, saith Jehovah, that Bozrah shall become an astonishment, a reproach, a waste, and a curse; and all the cities thereof shall be perpetual wastes. ^14I have heard tidings from Jehovah, and an ambassador is sent among the nations, saying, Gather yourselves together, and come against her, and rise up to the battle. ^15For, behold, I have made thee small among the nations, and despised among men. ^16As for thy terribleness, the pride of thy heart hath deceived thee, O thou that dwellest in the clefts of the rock, that holdest the height of the hill: though thou shouldest make thy nest as high as the eagle, I will bring thee down from thence, saith Jehovah. ^17And Edom shall become an astonishment: every one that passeth by it shall be astonished, and shall hiss at all the plagues thereof. ^18As in the overthrow of Sodom and Gomorrah and the neighbor cities thereof, saith Jehovah, no man shall dwell there, neither shall any son of man sojourn therein. ^19Behold, he shall come up like a lion from the pride of the Jordan against the strong habitation: for I will suddenly make them run away from it; and whoso is chosen, him will I appoint over it: for who is like me? and who will appoint me a time? and who is the shepherd that will stand before me? ^20Therefore hear ye the counsel of Jehovah, that he hath taken against Edom; and his purposes, that he hath purposed against the inhabitants of Teman: Surely they shall drag them away, even the little ones of the flock; surely he shall make their habitation desolate over them. ^21The earth trembleth at the noise of their fall; there is a cry, the noise whereof is heard in the Red Sea. ^22Behold, he shall come up and fly as the eagle, and spread out his wings against Bozrah: and the heart of the mighty men of Edom at that day shall be as the heart of a woman in her pangs. ^23Of Damascus. Hamath is confounded, and Arpad; for they have heard evil tidings, they are melted away: there is sorrow on the sea; it cannot be quiet. ^24Damascus is waxed feeble, she turneth herself to flee, and trembling hath seized on her: anguish and sorrows have taken hold of her, as of a woman in travail. ^25How is the city of praise not forsaken, the city of my joy? ^26Therefore her young men shall fall in her streets, and all the men of war shall be brought to silence in that day, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^27And I will kindle a fire in the wall of Damascus, and it shall devour the palaces of Ben-hadad. ^28Of Kedar, and of the kingdoms of Hazor, which Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon smote. Thus saith Jehovah: Arise ye, go up to Kedar, and destroy the children of the east. ^29Their tents and their flocks shall they take; they shall carry away for themselves their curtains, and all their vessels, and their camels; and they shall cry unto them, Terror on every side! ^30Flee ye, wander far off, dwell in the depths, O ye inhabitants of Hazor, saith Jehovah; for Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon hath taken counsel against you, and hath conceived a purpose against you. ^31Arise, get you up unto a nation that is at ease, that dwelleth without care, saith Jehovah; that have neither gates nor bars, that dwell alone. ^32And their camels shall be a booty, and the multitude of their cattle a spoil: and I will scatter unto all winds them that have the corners of their hair cut off; and I will bring their calamity from every side of them, saith Jehovah. ^33And Hazor shall be a dwelling-place of jackals, a desolation for ever: no man shall dwell there, neither shall any son of man sojourn therein. ^34The word of Jehovah that came to Jeremiah the prophet concerning Elam, in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah king of Judah, saying, ^35Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Behold, I will break the bow of Elam, the chief of their might. ^36And upon Elam will I bring the four winds from the four quarters of heaven, and will scatter them toward all those winds; and there shall be no nation whither the outcasts of Elam shall not come. ^37And I will cause Elam to be dismayed before their enemies, and before them that seek their life; and I will bring evil upon them, even my fierce anger, saith Jehovah; and I will send the sword after them, till I have consumed them; ^38and I will set my throne in Elam, and will destroy from thence king and princes, saith Jehovah. ^39But it shall come to pass in the latter days, that I will bring back the captivity of Elam, saith Jehovah.

Jeremiah 50

50

^1The word that Jehovah spake concerning Babylon, concerning the land of the Chaldeans, by Jeremiah the prophet. ^2Declare ye among the nations and publish, and set up a standard; publish, and conceal not: say, Babylon is taken, Bel is put to shame, Merodach is dismayed; her images are put to shame, her idols are dismayed. ^3For out of the north there cometh up a nation against her, which shall make her land desolate, and none shall dwell therein: they are fled, they are gone, both man and beast. ^4In those days, and in that time, saith Jehovah, the children of Israel shall come, they and the children of Judah together; they shall go on their way weeping, and shall seek Jehovah their God. ^5They shall inquire concerning Zion with their faces thitherward, saying, Come ye, and join yourselves to Jehovah in an everlasting covenant that shall not be forgotten. ^6My people have been lost sheep: their shepherds have caused them to go astray; they have turned them away on the mountains; they have gone from mountain to hill; they have forgotten their resting-place. ^7All that found them have devoured them; and their adversaries said, We are not guilty, because they have sinned against Jehovah, the habitation of righteousness, even Jehovah, the hope of their fathers. ^8Flee out of the midst of Babylon, and go forth out of the land of the Chaldeans, and be as the he-goats before the flocks. ^9For, lo, I will stir up and cause to come up against Babylon a company of great nations from the north country; and they shall set themselves in array against her; from thence she shall be taken: their arrows shall be as of an expert mighty man; none shall return in vain. ^10And Chaldea shall be a prey: all that prey upon her shall be satisfied, saith Jehovah. ^11Because ye are glad, because ye rejoice, O ye that plunder my heritage, because ye are wanton as a heifer that treadeth out the grain, and neigh as strong horses; ^12your mother shall be utterly put to shame; she that bare you shall be confounded: behold, she shall be the hindermost of the nations, a wilderness, a dry land, and a desert. ^13Because of the wrath of Jehovah she shall not be inhabited, but she shall be wholly desolate: every one that goeth by Babylon shall be astonished, and hiss at all her plagues. ^14Set yourselves in array against Babylon round about, all ye that bend the bow; shoot at her, spare no arrows: for she hath sinned against Jehovah. ^15Shout against her round about: she hath submitted herself; her bulwarks are fallen, her walls are thrown down; for it is the vengeance of Jehovah: take vengeance upon her; as she hath done, do unto her. ^16Cut off the sower from Babylon, and him that handleth the sickle in the time of harvest: for fear of the oppressing sword they shall turn every one to his people, and they shall flee every one to his own land. ^17Israel is a hunted sheep; the lions have driven him away: first, the king of Assyria devoured him; and now at last Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon hath broken his bones. ^18Therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will punish the king of Babylon and his land, as I have punished the king of Assyria. ^19And I will bring Israel again to his pasture, and he shall feed on Carmel and Bashan, and his soul shall be satisfied upon the hills of Ephraim and in Gilead. ^20In those days, and in that time, saith Jehovah, the iniquity of Israel shall be sought for, and there shall be none; and the sins of Judah, and they shall not be found: for I will pardon them whom I leave as a remnant. ^21Go up against the land of Merathaim, even against it, and against the inhabitants of Pekod: slay and utterly destroy after them, saith Jehovah, and do according to all that I have commanded thee. ^22A sound of battle is in the land, and of great destruction. ^23How is the hammer of the whole earth cut asunder and broken! how is Babylon become a desolation among the nations! ^24I have laid a snare for thee, and thou art also taken, O Babylon, and thou wast not aware: thou art found, and also caught, because thou hast striven against Jehovah. ^25Jehovah hath opened his armory, and hath brought forth the weapons of his indignation; for the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, hath a work to do in the land of the Chaldeans. ^26Come against her from the utmost border; open her store-houses; cast her up as heaps, and destroy her utterly; let nothing of her be left. ^27Slay all her bullocks; let them go down to the slaughter: woe unto them! for their day is come, the time of their visitation. ^28The voice of them that flee and escape out of the land of Babylon, to declare in Zion the vengeance of Jehovah our God, the vengeance of his temple. ^29Call together the archers against Babylon, all them that bend the bow; encamp against her round about; let none thereof escape: recompense her according to her work; according to all that she hath done, do unto her; for she hath been proud against Jehovah, against the Holy One of Israel. ^30Therefore shall her young men fall in her streets, and all her men of war shall be brought to silence in that day, saith Jehovah. ^31Behold, I am against thee, O thou proud one, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts; for thy day is come, the time that I will visit thee. ^32And the proud one shall stumble and fall, and none shall raise him up; and I will kindle a fire in his cities, and it shall devour all that are round about him. ^33Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: The children of Israel and the children of Judah are oppressed together; and all that took them captive hold them fast; they refuse to let them go. ^34Their Redeemer is strong; Jehovah of hosts is his name: he will thoroughly plead their cause, that he may give rest to the earth, and disquiet the inhabitants of Babylon. ^35A sword is upon the Chaldeans, saith Jehovah, and upon the inhabitants of Babylon, and upon her princes, and upon her wise men. ^36A sword is upon the boasters, and they shall become fools; a sword is upon her mighty men, and they shall be dismayed. ^37A sword is upon their horses, and upon their chariots, and upon all the mingled people that are in the midst of her; and they shall become as women: a sword is upon her treasures, and they shall be robbed. ^38A drought is upon her waters, and they shall be dried up; for it is a land of graven images, and they are mad over idols. ^39Therefore the wild beasts of the desert with the wolves shall dwell there, and the ostriches shall dwell therein: and it shall be no more inhabited for ever; neither shall it be dwelt in from generation to generation. ^40As when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah and the neighbor cities thereof, saith Jehovah, so shall no man dwell there, neither shall any son of man sojourn therein. ^41Behold, a people cometh from the north; and a great nation and many kings shall be stirred up from the uttermost parts of the earth. ^42They lay hold on bow and spear; they are cruel, and have no mercy; their voice roareth like the sea; and they ride upon horses, every one set in array, as a man to the battle, against thee, O daughter of Babylon. ^43The king of Babylon hath heard the tidings of them, and his hands wax feeble: anguish hath taken hold of him, and pangs as of a woman in travail. ^44Behold, the enemy shall come up like a lion from the pride of the Jordan against the strong habitation: for I will suddenly make them run away from it; and whoso is chosen, him will I appoint over it: for who is like me? and who will appoint me a time? and who is the shepherd that can stand before me? ^45Therefore hear ye the counsel of Jehovah, that he hath taken against Babylon; and his purposes, that he hath purposed against the land of the Chaldeans: Surely they shall drag them away, even the little ones of the flock; surely he shall make their habitation desolate over them. ^46At the noise of the taking of Babylon the earth trembleth, and the cry is heard among the nations.

Jeremiah 51

51

^1Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I will raise up against Babylon, and against them that dwell in Leb-kamai, a destroying wind. ^2And I will send unto Babylon strangers, that shall winnow her; and they shall empty her land: for in the day of trouble they shall be against her round about. ^3Against him that bendeth let the archer bend his bow, and against him that lifteth himself up in his coat of mail: and spare ye not her young men; destroy ye utterly all her host. ^4And they shall fall down slain in the land of the Chaldeans, and thrust through in her streets. ^5For Israel is not forsaken, nor Judah, of his God, of Jehovah of hosts; though their land is full of guilt against the Holy One of Israel. ^6Flee out of the midst of Babylon, and save every man his life; be not cut off in her iniquity: for it is the time of Jehovah's vengeance; he will render unto her a recompense. ^7Babylon hath been a golden cup in Jehovah's hand, that made all the earth drunken: the nations have drunk of her wine; therefore the nations are mad. ^8Babylon is suddenly fallen and destroyed: wail for her; take balm for her pain, if so be she may be healed. ^9We would have healed Babylon, but she is not healed: forsake her, and let us go every one into his own country; for her judgment reacheth unto heaven, and is lifted up even to the skies. ^10Jehovah hath brought forth our righteousness: come, and let us declare in Zion the work of Jehovah our God. ^11Make sharp the arrows; hold firm the shields: Jehovah hath stirred up the spirit of the kings of the Medes; because his purpose is against Babylon, to destroy it: for it is the vengeance of Jehovah, the vengeance of his temple. ^12Set up a standard against the walls of Babylon, make the watch strong, set the watchmen, prepare the ambushes; for Jehovah hath both purposed and done that which he spake concerning the inhabitants of Babylon. ^13O thou that dwellest upon many waters, abundant in treasures, thine end is come, the measure of thy covetousness. ^14Jehovah of hosts hath sworn by himself, saying, Surely I will fill thee with men, as with the canker-worm; and they shall lift up a shout against thee. ^15He hath made the earth by his power, he hath established the world by his wisdom, and by his understanding hath he stretched out the heavens: ^16when he uttereth his voice, there is a tumult of waters in the heavens, and he causeth the vapors to ascend from the ends of the earth; he maketh lightnings for the rain, and bringeth forth the wind out of his treasuries. ^17Every man is become brutish and is without knowledge; every goldsmith is put to shame by his image; for his molten image is falsehood, and there is no breath in them. ^18They are vanity, a work of delusion: in the time of their visitation they shall perish. ^19The portion of Jacob is not like these; for he is the former of all things; and Israel is the tribe of his inheritance: Jehovah of hosts is his name. ^20Thou art my battle-axe and weapons of war: and with thee will I break in pieces the nations; and with thee will I destroy kingdoms; ^21and with thee will I break in pieces the horse and his rider; ^22and with thee will I break in pieces the chariot and him that rideth therein; and with thee will I break in pieces man and woman; and with thee will I break in pieces the old man and the youth; and with thee will I break in pieces the young man and the virgin; ^23and with thee will I break in pieces the shepherd and his flock; and with thee will I break in pieces the husbandman and his yoke of oxen; and with thee will I break in pieces governors and deputies. ^24And I will render unto Babylon and to all the inhabitants of Chaldea all their evil that they have done in Zion in your sight, saith Jehovah. ^25Behold, I am against thee, O destroying mountain, saith Jehovah, which destroyest all the earth; and I will stretch out my hand upon thee, and roll thee down from the rocks, and will make thee a burnt mountain. ^26And they shall not take of thee a stone for a corner, nor a stone for foundations; but thou shalt be desolate for ever, saith Jehovah. ^27Set ye up a standard in the land, blow the trumpet among the nations, prepare the nations against her, call together against her the kingdoms of Ararat, Minni, and Ashkenaz: appoint a marshal against her; cause the horses to come up as the rough canker-worm. ^28Prepare against her the nations, the kings of the Medes, the governors thereof, and all the deputies thereof, and all the land of their dominion. ^29And the land trembleth and is in pain; for the purposes of Jehovah against Babylon do stand, to make the land of Babylon a desolation, without inhabitant. ^30The mighty men of Babylon have forborne to fight, they remain in their strongholds; their might hath failed; they are become as women: her dwelling-places are set on fire; her bars are broken. ^31One post shall run to meet another, and one messenger to met another, to show the king of Babylon that his city is taken on every quarter: ^32and the passages are seized, and the reeds they have burned with fire, and the men of war are affrighted. ^33For thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel: The daughter of Babylon is like a threshing-floor at the time when it is trodden; yet a little while, and the time of harvest shall come for her. ^34Nebuchadrezzar the king of Babylon hath devoured me, he hath crushed me, he hath made me an empty vessel, he hath, like a monster, swallowed me up, he hath filled his maw with my delicacies; he hath cast me out. ^35The violence done to me and to my flesh be upon Babylon, shall the inhabitant of Zion say; and, My blood be upon the inhabitants of Chaldea, shall Jerusalem say. ^36Therefore thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I will plead thy cause, and take vengeance for thee; and I will dry up her sea, and make her fountain dry. ^37And Babylon shall become heaps, a dwelling-place for jackals, an astonishment, and a hissing, without inhabitant. ^38They shall roar together like young lions; they shall growl as lions' whelps. ^39When they are heated, I will make their feast, and I will make them drunken, that they may rejoice, and sleep a perpetual sleep, and not wake, saith Jehovah. ^40I will bring them down like lambs to the slaughter, like rams with he-goats. ^41How is Sheshach taken! and the praise of the whole earth seized! how is Babylon become a desolation among the nations! ^42The sea is come up upon Babylon; she is covered with the multitude of the waves thereof. ^43Her cities are become a desolation, a dry land, and a desert, a land wherein no man dwelleth, neither doth any son of man pass thereby. ^44And I will execute judgment upon Bel in Babylon, and I will bring forth out of his mouth that which he hath swallowed up; and the nations shall not flow any more unto him: yea, the wall of Babylon shall fall. ^45My people, go ye out of the midst of her, and save yourselves every man from the fierce anger of Jehovah. ^46And let not your heart faint, neither fear ye for the tidings that shall be heard in the land; for tidings shall come one year, and after that in another year shall come tidings, and violence in the land, ruler against ruler. ^47Therefore, behold, the days come, that I will execute judgment upon the graven images of Babylon; and her whole land shall be confounded; and all her slain shall fall in the midst of her. ^48Then the heavens and the earth, and all that is therein, shall sing for joy over Babylon; for the destroyers shall come unto her from the north, saith Jehovah. ^49As Babylon hath caused the slain of Israel to fall, so at Babylon shall fall the slain of all the land. ^50Ye that have escaped the sword, go ye, stand not still; remember Jehovah from afar, and let Jerusalem come into your mind. ^51We are confounded, because we have heard reproach; confusion hath covered our faces: for strangers are come into the sanctuaries of Jehovah's house. ^52Wherefore, behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will execute judgment upon her graven images; and through all her land the wounded shall groan. ^53Though Babylon should mount up to heaven, and though she should fortify the height of her strength, yet from me shall destroyers come unto her, saith Jehovah. ^54The sound of a cry from Babylon, and of great destruction from the land of the Chaldeans! ^55For Jehovah layeth Babylon waste, and destroyeth out of her the great voice; and their waves roar like many waters; the noise of their voice is uttered: ^56for the destroyer is come upon her, even upon Babylon, and her mighty men are taken, their bows are broken in pieces; for Jehovah is a God of recompenses, he will surely requite. ^57And I will make drunk her princes and her wise men, her governors and her deputies, and her mighty men; and they shall sleep a perpetual sleep, and not wake, saith the King, whose name is Jehovah of hosts. ^58Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: The broad walls of Babylon shall be utterly overthrown, and her high gates shall be burned with fire; and the peoples shall labor for vanity, and the nations for the fire; and they shall be weary. ^59The word which Jeremiah the prophet commanded Seraiah the son of Neriah, the son of Mahseiah, when he went with Zedekiah the king of Judah to Babylon in the fourth year of his reign. Now Seraiah was chief chamberlain. ^60And Jeremiah wrote in a book all the evil that should come upon Babylon, even all these words that are written concerning Babylon. ^61And Jeremiah said to Seraiah, When thou comest to Babylon, then see that thou read all these words, ^62and say, O Jehovah, thou hast spoken concerning this place, to cut it off, that none shall dwell therein, neither man nor beast, but that it shall be desolate for ever. ^63And it shall be, when thou hast made an end of reading this book, that thou shalt bind a stone to it, and cast it into the midst of the Euphrates: ^64and thou shalt say, Thus shall Babylon sink, and shall not rise again because of the evil that I will bring upon her; and they shall be weary. Thus far are the words of Jeremiah.

Job 2

2

^1Again it came to pass on the day when the sons of God came to present themselves before Jehovah, that Satan came also among them to present himself before Jehovah. ^2And Jehovah said unto Satan, From whence comest thou? And Satan answered Jehovah, and said, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it. ^3And Jehovah said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job? for there is none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and turneth away from evil: and he still holdeth fast his integrity, although thou movedst me against him, to destroy him without cause. ^4And Satan answered Jehovah, and said, Skin for skin, yea, all that a man hath will he give for his life. ^5But put forth thy hand now, and touch his bone and his flesh, and he will renounce thee to thy face. ^6And Jehovah said unto Satan, Behold, he is in thy hand; only spare his life. ^7So Satan went forth from the presence of Jehovah, and smote Job with sore boils from the sole of his foot unto his crown. ^8And he took him a potsherd to scrape himself therewith; and he sat among the ashes. ^9Then said his wife unto him, Dost thou still hold fast thine integrity? renounce God, and die. ^10But he said unto her, Thou speakest as one of the foolish women speaketh. What? shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not receive evil? In all this did not Job sin with his lips. ^11Now when Job's three friends heard of all this evil that was come upon him, they came every one from his own place: Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite, and they made an appointment together to come to bemoan him and to comfort him. ^12And when they lifted up their eyes afar off, and knew him not, they lifted up their voice, and wept; and they rent every one his robe, and sprinkled dust upon their heads toward heaven. ^13So they sat down with him upon the ground seven days and seven nights, and none spake a word unto him: for they saw that his grief was very great.

Job 42

42

^1Then Job answered Jehovah, and said,

^2I know that thou canst do all things,

And that no purpose of thine can be restrained.

^3Who is this that hideth counsel without knowledge?

Therefore have I uttered that which I understood not,

Things too wonderful for me, which I knew not.

^4Hear, I beseech thee, and I will speak;

I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me.

^5I had heard of thee by the hearing of the ear;

But now mine eye seeth thee:

^6Wherefore I abhor myself,

And repent in dust and ashes.

^7And it was so, that, after Jehovah had spoken these words unto Job, Jehovah said to Eliphaz the Temanite, My wrath is kindled against thee, and against thy two friends; for ye have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job hath. ^8Now therefore, take unto you seven bullocks and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and offer up for yourselves a burnt-offering; and my servant Job shall pray for you; for him will I accept, that I deal not with you after your folly; for ye have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job hath. ^9So Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite went, and did according as Jehovah commanded them: and Jehovah accepted Job.

^10And Jehovah turned the captivity of Job, when he prayed for his friends: and Jehovah gave Job twice as much as he had before. ^11Then came there unto him all his brethren, and all his sisters, and all they that had been of his acquaintance before, and did eat bread with him in his house: and they bemoaned him, and comforted him concerning all the evil that Jehovah had brought upon him: every man also gave him a piece of money, and every one a ring of gold. ^12So Jehovah blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning: And he had fourteen thousand sheep, and six thousand camels, and a thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand she-asses. ^13He had also seven sons and three daughters. ^14And he called the name of the first, Jemimah: and the name of the second, Keziah; and the name of the third, Keren-happuch. ^15And in all the land were no women found so fair as the daughters of Job: and their father gave them inheritance among their brethren. ^16And after this Job lived a hundred and forty years, and saw his sons, and his sons' sons, even four generations. ^17So Job died, being old and full of days.

Joel 2

2

^1Blow ye the trumpet in Zion, and sound an alarm in my holy mountain; let all the inhabitants of the land tremble: for the day of Jehovah cometh, for it is nigh at hand; ^2a day of darkness and gloominess, a day of clouds and thick darkness, as the dawn spread upon the mountains; a great people and a strong; there hath not been ever the like, neither shall be any more after them, even to the years of many generations. ^3A fire devoureth before them; and behind them a flame burneth: the land is as the garden of Eden before them, and behind them a desolate wilderness; yea, and none hath escaped them. ^4The appearance of them is as the appearance of horses; and as horsemen, so do they run. ^5Like the noise of chariots on the tops of the mountains do they leap, like the noise of a flame of fire that devoureth the stubble, as a strong people set in battle array. ^6At their presence the peoples are in anguish; all faces are waxed pale. ^7They run like mighty men; they climb the wall like men of war; and they march every one on his ways, and they break not their ranks. ^8Neither doth one thrust another; they march every one in his path; and they burst through the weapons, and break not off their course. ^9They leap upon the city; they run upon the wall; they climb up into the houses; they enter in at the windows like a thief. ^10The earth quaketh before them; the heavens tremble; the sun and the moon are darkened, and the stars withdraw their shining. ^11And Jehovah uttereth his voice before his army; for his camp is very great; for he is strong that executeth his word; for the day of Jehovah is great and very terrible; and who can abide it? ^12Yet even now, saith Jehovah, turn ye unto me with all your heart, and with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning: ^13and rend your heart, and not your garments, and turn unto Jehovah your God; for he is gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and abundant in lovingkindness, and repenteth him of the evil. ^14Who knoweth whether he will not turn and repent, and leave a blessing behind him, even a meal-offering and a drink-offering unto Jehovah your God? ^15Blow the trumpet in Zion, sanctify a fast, call a solemn assembly; ^16gather the people, sanctify the assembly, assemble the old men, gather the children, and those that suck the breasts; let the bridegroom go forth from his chamber, and the bride out of her closet. ^17Let the priests, the ministers of Jehovah, weep between the porch and the altar, and let them say, Spare thy people, O Jehovah, and give not thy heritage to reproach, that the nations should rule over them: wherefore should they say among the peoples, Where is their God? ^18Then was Jehovah jealous for his land, and had pity on his people. ^19And Jehovah answered and said unto his people, Behold, I will send you grain, and new wine, and oil, and ye shall be satisfied therewith; and I will no more make you a reproach among the nations; ^20but I will remove far off from you the northern army, and will drive it into a land barren and desolate, its forepart into the eastern sea, and its hinder part into the western sea; and its stench shall come up, and its ill savor shall come up, because it hath done great things. ^21Fear not, O land, be glad and rejoice; for Jehovah hath done great things. ^22Be not afraid, ye beasts of the field; for the pastures of the wilderness do spring, for the tree beareth its fruit, the fig-tree and the vine do yield their strength. ^23Be glad then, ye children of Zion, and rejoice in Jehovah your God; for he giveth you the former rain in just measure, and he causeth to come down for you the rain, the former rain and the latter rain, in the first month. ^24And the floors shall be full of wheat, and the vats shall overflow with new wine and oil. ^25And I will restore to you the years that the locust hath eaten, the canker-worm, and the caterpillar, and the palmer-worm, my great army which I sent among you. ^26And ye shall eat in plenty and be satisfied, and shall praise the name of Jehovah your God, that hath dealt wondrously with you; and my people shall never be put to shame. ^27And ye shall know that I am in the midst of Israel, and that I am Jehovah your God, and there is none else; and my people shall never be put to shame. ^28And it shall come to pass afterward, that I will pour out my Spirit upon all flesh; and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, your old men shall dream dreams, your young men shall see visions: ^29and also upon the servants and upon the handmaids in those days will I pour out my Spirit. ^30And I will show wonders in the heavens and in the earth: blood, and fire, and pillars of smoke. ^31The sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the great and terrible day of Jehovah cometh. ^32And it shall come to pass, that whosoever shall call on the name of Jehovah shall be delivered; for in mount Zion and in Jerusalem there shall be those that escape, as Jehovah hath said, and among the remnant those whom Jehovah doth call.

Joel 3

3

^1For, behold, in those days, and in that time, when I shall bring back the captivity of Judah and Jerusalem, ^2I will gather all nations, and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoshaphat; and I will execute judgment upon them there for my people and for my heritage Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations: and they have parted my land, ^3and have cast lots for my people, and have given a boy for a harlot, and sold a girl for wine, that they may drink. ^4Yea, and what are ye to me, O Tyre, and Sidon, and all the regions of Philistia? will ye render me a recompense? and if ye recompense me, swiftly and speedily will I return your recompense upon your own head. ^5Forasmuch as ye have taken my silver and my gold, and have carried into your temples my goodly precious things, ^6and have sold the children of Judah and the children of Jerusalem unto the sons of the Grecians, that ye may remove them far from their border; ^7behold, I will stir them up out of the place whither ye have sold them, and will return your recompense upon your own head; ^8and I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hand of the children of Judah, and they shall sell them to the men of Sheba, to a nation far off: for Jehovah hath spoken it. ^9Proclaim ye this among the nations; prepare war; stir up the mighty men; let all the men of war draw near, let them come up. ^10Beat your plowshares into swords, and your pruning-hooks into spears: let the weak say, I am strong. ^11Haste ye, and come, all ye nations round about, and gather yourselves together: thither cause thy mighty ones to come down, O Jehovah. ^12Let the nations bestir themselves, and come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat; for there will I sit to judge all the nations round about. ^13Put ye in the sickle; for the harvest is ripe: come, tread ye; for the winepress is full, the vats overflow; for their wickedness is great. ^14Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of decision! for the day of Jehovah is near in the valley of decision. ^15The sun and the moon are darkened, and the stars withdraw their shining. ^16And Jehovah will roar from Zion, and utter his voice from Jerusalem; and the heavens and the earth shall shake: but Jehovah will be a refuge unto his people, and a stronghold to the children of Israel. ^17So shall ye know that I am Jehovah your God, dwelling in Zion my holy mountain: then shall Jerusalem be holy, and there shall no strangers pass through her any more. ^18And it shall come to pass in that day, that the mountains shall drop down sweet wine, and the hills shall flow with milk, and all the brooks of Judah shall flow with waters; and a fountain shall come forth from the house of Jehovah, and shall water the valley of Shittim. ^19Egypt shall be a desolation, and Edom shall be a desolate wilderness, for the violence done to the children of Judah, because they have shed innocent blood in their land. ^20But Judah shall abide for ever, and Jerusalem from generation to generation. ^21And I will cleanse their blood, that I have not cleansed: for Jehovah dwelleth in Zion.

John 2

2

^1And the third day there was a marriage in Cana of Galilee; and the mother of Jesus was there: ^2and Jesus also was bidden, and his disciples, to the marriage. ^3And when the wine failed, the mother of Jesus saith unto him, They have no wine. ^4And Jesus saith unto her, Woman, what have I to do with thee? mine hour is not yet come. ^5His mother saith unto the servants, Whatsoever he saith unto you, do it. ^6Now there were six waterpots of stone set there after the Jews' manner of purifying, containing two or three firkins apiece. ^7Jesus saith unto them, Fill the waterpots with water. And they filled them up to the brim. ^8And he saith unto them, Draw out now, and bear unto the ruler of the feast. And they bare it. ^9And when the ruler of the feast tasted the water now become wine, and knew not whence it was (but the servants that had drawn the water knew), the ruler of the feast calleth the bridegroom, ^10and saith unto him, Every man setteth on first the good wine; and when men have drunk freely, then that which is worse: thou hast kept the good wine until now. ^11This beginning of his signs did Jesus in Cana of Galilee, and manifested his glory; and his disciples believed on him. ^12After this he went down to Capernaum, he, and his mother, and his brethren, and his disciples; and there they abode not many days. ^13And the passover of the Jews was at hand, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. ^14And he found in the temple those that sold oxen and sheep and doves, and the changers of money sitting: ^15and he made a scourge of cords, and cast all out of the temple, both the sheep and the oxen; and he poured out the changers' money, and overthrew their tables; ^16and to them that sold the doves he said, Take these things hence; make not my Father's house a house of merchandise. ^17His disciples remembered that it was written, Zeal for thy house shall eat me up. ^18The Jews therefore answered and said unto him, What sign showest thou unto us, seeing that thou doest these things? ^19Jesus answered and said unto them, Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up. ^20The Jews therefore said, Forty and six years was this temple in building, and wilt thou raise it up in three days? ^21But he spake of the temple of his body. ^22When therefore he was raised from the dead, his disciples remembered that he spake this; and they believed the span, and the word which Jesus had said. ^23Now when he was in Jerusalem at the passover, during the feast, many believed on his name, beholding his signs which he did. ^24But Jesus did not trust himself unto them, for that he knew all men, ^25and because he needed not that any one should bear witness concerning man; for he himself knew what was in man.

John 3

3

^1Now there was a man of the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews: ^2the same came unto him by night, and said to him, Rabbi, we know that thou art a teacher come from God; for no one can do these signs that thou doest, except God be with him. ^3Jesus answered and said unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except one be born anew, he cannot see the kingdom of God. ^4Nicodemus saith unto him, How can a man be born when he is old? can he enter a second time into his mother's womb, and be born? ^5Jesus answered, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except one be born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God! ^6That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is born of the Spirit is spirit. ^7Marvel not that I said unto thee, Ye must be born anew. ^8The wind bloweth where it will, and thou hearest the voice thereof, but knowest not whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the Spirit. ^9Nicodemus answered and said unto him, How can these things be? ^10Jesus answered and said unto him, Art thou the teacher of Israel, and understandest not these things? ^11Verily, verily, I say unto thee, We speak that which we know, and bear witness of that which we have seen; and ye receive not our witness. ^12If I told you earthly things and ye believe not, how shall ye believe if I tell you heavenly things? ^13And no one hath ascended into heaven, but he that descended out of heaven, even the Son of man, who is in heaven. ^14And as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, even so must the Son of man be lifted up; ^15that whosoever believeth may in him have eternal life. ^16For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth on him should not perish, but have eternal life. ^17For God sent not the Son into the world to judge the world; but that the world should be saved through him. ^18He that believeth on him is not judged: he that believeth not hath been judged already, because he hath not believed on the name of the only begotten Son of God. ^19And this is the judgment, that the light is come into the world, and men loved the darkness rather than the light; for their works were evil. ^20For every one that doeth evil hateth the light, and cometh not to the light, lest his works should be reproved. ^21But he that doeth the truth cometh to the light, that his works may be made manifest, that they have been wrought in God. ^22After these things came Jesus and his disciples into the land of Judea; and there he tarried with them, and baptized. ^23And John also was baptizing in Enon near to Salim, because there was much water there: and they came, and were baptized. ^24For John was not yet cast into prison. ^25There arose therefore a questioning on the part of John's disciples with a Jew about purifying. ^26And they came unto John, and said to him, Rabbi, he that was with thee beyond the Jordan, to whom thou hast borne witness, behold, the same baptizeth, and all men come to him. ^27John answered and said, A man can receive nothing, except it have been given him from heaven. ^28Ye yourselves bear me witness, that I said, I am not the Christ, but, that I am sent before him. ^29He that hath the bride is the bridegroom: but the friend of the bridegroom, that standeth and heareth him, rejoiceth greatly because of the bridegroom's voice: this my joy therefore is made full. ^30He must increase, but I must decrease. ^31He that cometh from above is above all: he that is of the earth is of the earth, and of the earth he speaketh: he that cometh from heaven is above all. ^32What he hath seen and heard, of that he beareth witness; and no man receiveth his witness. ^33He that hath received his witness hath set his seal to this, that God is true. ^34For he whom God hath sent speaketh the words of God: for he giveth not the Spirit by measure. ^35The Father loveth the Son, and hath given all things into his hand. ^36He that believeth on the Son hath eternal life; but he that obeyeth not the Son shall not see life, but the wrath of God abideth on him.

John 4

4

^1When therefore the Lord knew that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus was making and baptizing more disciples than John ^2(although Jesus himself baptized not, but his disciples), ^3he left Judea, and departed again into Galilee. ^4And he must needs pass through Samaria. ^5So he cometh to a city of Samaria, called Sychar, near to the parcel of ground that Jacob gave to his son Joseph: ^6and Jacob's well was there. Jesus therefore, being wearied with his journey, sat thus by the well. It was about the sixth hour. ^7There cometh a woman of Samaria to draw water: Jesus saith unto her, Give me to drink. ^8For his disciples were gone away into the city to buy food. ^9The Samaritan woman therefore saith unto him, How is it that thou, being a Jew, askest drink of me, who am a Samaritan woman? (For Jews have no dealings with Samaritans.) ^10Jesus answered and said unto her, If thou knewest the gift of God, and who it is that saith to thee, Give me to drink; thou wouldest have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water. ^11The woman saith unto him, Sir, thou hast nothing to draw with, and the well is deep: whence then hast thou that living water? ^12Art thou greater than our father Jacob, who gave us the well, and drank thereof himself, and his sons, and his cattle? ^13Jesus answered and said unto her, Every one that drinketh of this water shall thirst again: ^14but whosoever drinketh of the water that I shall give him shall never thirst; but the water that I shall give him shall become in him a well of water springing up unto eternal life. ^15The woman saith unto him, Sir, give me this water, that I thirst not, neither come all the way hither to draw. ^16Jesus saith unto her, Go, call thy husband, and come hither. ^17The woman answered and said unto him, I have no husband. Jesus saith unto her, Thou saidst well, I have no husband: ^18for thou hast had five husbands; and he whom thou now hast is not thy husband: this hast thou said truly. ^19The woman saith unto him, Sir, I perceive that thou art a prophet. ^20Our fathers worshipped in this mountain; and ye say, that in Jerusalem is the place where men ought to worship. ^21Jesus saith unto her, Woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when neither in this mountain, nor in Jerusalem, shall ye worship the Father. ^22Ye worship that which ye know not: we worship that which we know; for salvation is from the Jews. ^23But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worshippers shall worship the Father in spirit and truth: for such doth the Father seek to be his worshippers. ^24God is a Spirit: and they that worship him must worship in spirit and truth. ^25The woman saith unto him, I know that Messiah cometh (he that is called Christ): when he is come, he will declare unto us all things. ^26Jesus saith unto her, I that speak unto thee am he. ^27And upon this came his disciples; and they marvelled that he was speaking with a woman; yet no man said, What seekest thou? or, Why speakest thou with her? ^28So the woman left her waterpot, and went away into the city, and saith to the people, ^29Come, see a man, who told me all things that ever I did: can this be the Christ? ^30They went out of the city, and were coming to him. ^31In the mean while the disciples prayed him, saying, Rabbi, eat. ^32But he said unto them, I have meat to eat that ye know not. ^33The disciples therefore said one to another, Hath any man brought him aught to eat? ^34Jesus saith unto them, My meat is to do the will of him that sent me, and to accomplish his work. ^35Say not ye, There are yet four months, and then cometh the harvest? behold, I say unto you, Lift up your eyes, and look on the fields, that they are white already unto harvest. ^36He that reapeth receiveth wages, and gathereth fruit unto life eternal; that he that soweth and he that reapeth may rejoice together. ^37For herein is the saying true, One soweth, and another reapeth. ^38I sent you to reap that whereon ye have not labored: others have labored, and ye are entered into their labor. ^39And from that city many of the Samaritans believed on him because of the word of the woman, who testified, He told me all things that ever I did. ^40So when the Samaritans came unto him, they besought him to abide with them: and he abode there two days. ^41And many more believed because of his word; ^42and they said to the woman, Now we believe, not because of thy speaking: for we have heard for ourselves, and know that this is indeed the Saviour of the world. ^43And after the two days he went forth from thence into Galilee. ^44For Jesus himself testified, that a prophet hath no honor in his own country. ^45So when he came into Galilee, the Galilaeans received him, having seen all the things that he did in Jerusalem at the feast: for they also went unto the feast. ^46He came therefore again unto Cana of Galilee, where he made the water wine. And there was a certain nobleman, whose son was sick at Capernaum. ^47When he heard that Jesus was come out of Judaea into Galilee, he went unto him, and besought him that he would come down, and heal his son; for he was at the point of death. ^48Jesus therefore said unto him, Except ye see signs and wonders, ye will in no wise believe. ^49The nobleman saith unto him, Sir, come down ere my child die. ^50Jesus saith unto him, Go thy way; thy son liveth. The man believed the word that Jesus spake unto him, and he went his way. ^51And as he was now going down, his servants met him, saying, that his son lived. ^52So he inquired of them the hour when he began to amend. They said therefore unto him, Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him. ^53So the father knew that it was at that hour in which Jesus said unto him, Thy son liveth: and himself believed, and his whole house. ^54This is again the second sign that Jesus did, having come out of Judaea into Galilee.

John 5

5

^1After these things there was a feast of the Jews; and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. ^2Now there is in Jerusalem by the sheep gate a pool, which is called in Hebrew Bethesda, having five porches. ^3In these lay a multitude of them that were sick, blind, halt, withered, waiting for the moving of the water. ^4for an angel of the Lord went down at certain seasons into the pool, and troubled the water: whosoever then first after the troubling of the waters stepped in was made whole, with whatsoever disease he was holden. ^5And a certain man was there, who had been thirty and eight years in his infirmity. ^6When Jesus saw him lying, and knew that he had been now a long time in that case, he saith unto him, Wouldest thou be made whole? ^7The sick man answered him, Sir, I have no man, when the water is troubled, to put me into the pool: but while I am coming, another steppeth down before me. ^8Jesus saith unto him, Arise, take up thy bed, and walk. ^9And straightway the man was made whole, and took up his bed and walked. Now it was the sabbath on that day. ^10So the Jews said unto him that was cured, It is the sabbath, and it is not lawful for thee to take up thy bed. ^11But he answered them, He that made me whole, the same said unto me, Take up thy bed, and walk. ^12They asked him, Who is the man that said unto thee, Take up thy bed, and walk? ^13But he that was healed knew not who it was; for Jesus had conveyed himself away, a multitude being in the place. ^14Afterward Jesus findeth him in the temple, and said unto him, Behold, thou art made whole: sin no more, lest a worse thing befall thee. ^15The man went away, and told the Jews that it was Jesus who had made him whole. ^16And for this cause the Jews persecuted Jesus, because he did these things on the sabbath. ^17But Jesus answered them, My Father worketh even until now, and I work. ^18For this cause therefore the Jews sought the more to kill him, because he not only brake the sabbath, but also called God his own Father, making himself equal with God. ^19Jesus therefore answered and said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, The Son can do nothing of himself, but what he seeth the Father doing: for what things soever he doeth, these the Son also doeth in like manner. ^20For the Father loveth the Son, and showeth him all things that himself doeth: and greater works than these will he show him, that ye may marvel. ^21For as the Father raiseth the dead and giveth them life, even so the Son also giveth life to whom he will. ^22For neither doth the Father judge any man, but he hath given all judgment unto the Son; ^23that all may honor the Son, even as they honor the Father. He that honoreth not the Son honoreth not the Father that sent him. ^24Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that heareth my word, and believeth him that sent me, hath eternal life, and cometh not into judgment, but hath passed out of death into life. ^25Verily, verily, I say unto you, The hour cometh, and now is, when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God; and they that hear shall live. ^26For as the Father hath life in himself, even so gave he to the Son also to have life in himself: ^27and he gave him authority to execute judgment, because he is a son of man. ^28Marvel not at this: for the hour cometh, in which all that are in the tombs shall hear his voice, ^29and shall come forth; they that have done good, unto the resurrection of life; and they that have done evil, unto the resurrection of judgment. ^30I can of myself do nothing: as I hear, I judge: and my judgment is righteous; because I seek not mine own will, but the will of him that sent me. ^31If I bear witness of myself, my witness is not true. ^32It is another that beareth witness of me; and I know that the witness which he witnesseth of me is true. ^33Ye have sent unto John, and he hath borne witness unto the truth. ^34But the witness which I receive is not from man: howbeit I say these things, that ye may be saved. ^35He was the lamp that burneth and shineth; and ye were willing to rejoice for a season in his light. ^36But the witness which I have is greater than that of John; for the works which the Father hath given me to accomplish, the very works that I do, bear witness of me, that the Father hath sent me. ^37And the Father that sent me, he hath borne witness of me. Ye have neither heard his voice at any time, nor seen his form. ^38And ye have not his word abiding in you: for whom he sent, him ye believe not. ^39Ye search the spans, because ye think that in them ye have eternal life; and these are they which bear witness of me; ^40and ye will not come to me, that ye may have life. ^41I receive not glory from men. ^42But I know you, that ye have not the love of God in yourselves. ^43I am come in my Father's name, and ye receive me not: if another shall come in his own name, him ye will receive. ^44How can ye believe, who receive glory one of another, and the glory that cometh from the only God ye seek not? ^45Think not that I will accuse you to the Father: there is one that accuseth you, even Moses, on whom ye have set your hope. ^46For if ye believed Moses, ye would believe me; for he wrote of me. ^47But if ye believe not his writings, how shall ye believe my words?

John 6

6

^1After these things Jesus went away to the other side of the sea of Galilee, which is the sea of Tiberias. ^2And a great multitude followed him, because they beheld the signs which he did on them that were sick. ^3And Jesus went up into the mountain, and there he sat with his disciples. ^4Now the passover, the feast of the Jews, was at hand. ^5Jesus therefore lifting up his eyes, and seeing that a great multitude cometh unto him, saith unto Philip, Whence are we to buy bread, that these may eat? ^6And this he said to prove him: for he himself knew what he would do. ^7Philip answered him, Two hundred shillings' worth of bread is not sufficient for them, that every one may take a little. ^8One of his disciples, Andrew, Simon Peter's brother, saith unto him, ^9There is a lad here, who hath five barley loaves, and two fishes: but what are these among so many? ^10Jesus said, Make the people sit down. Now there was much grass in the place. So the men sat down, in number about five thousand. ^11Jesus therefore took the loaves; and having given thanks, he distributed to them that were set down; likewise also of the fishes as much as they would. ^12And when they were filled, he saith unto his disciples, Gather up the broken pieces which remain over, that nothing be lost. ^13So they gathered them up, and filled twelve baskets with broken pieces from the five barley loaves, which remained over unto them that had eaten. ^14When therefore the people saw the sign which he did, they said, This is of a truth the prophet that cometh into the world. ^15Jesus therefore perceiving that they were about to come and take him by force, to make him king, withdrew again into the mountain himself alone. ^16And when evening came, his disciples went down unto the sea; ^17and they entered into a boat, and were going over the sea unto Capernaum. And it was now dark, and Jesus had not yet come to them. ^18And the sea was rising by reason of a great wind that blew. ^19When therefore they had rowed about five and twenty or thirty furlongs, they behold Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing nigh unto the boat: and they were afraid. ^20But he saith unto them, It is I; be not afraid. ^21They were willing therefore to receive him into the boat: and straightway the boat was at the land whither they were going. ^22On the morrow the multitude that stood on the other side of the sea saw that there was no other boat there, save one, and that Jesus entered not with his disciples into the boat, but that his disciples went away alone ^23(howbeit there came boats from Tiberias nigh unto the place where they ate the bread after the Lord had given thanks): ^24when the multitude therefore saw that Jesus was not there, neither his disciples, they themselves got into the boats, and came to Capernaum, seeking Jesus. ^25And when they found him on the other side of the sea, they said unto him, Rabbi, when camest thou hither? ^26Jesus answered them and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Ye seek me, not because ye saw signs, but because ye ate of the loaves, and were filled. ^27Work not for the food which perisheth, but for the food which abideth unto eternal life, which the Son of man shall give unto you: for him the Father, even God, hath sealed. ^28They said therefore unto him, What must we do, that we may work the works of God? ^29Jesus answered and said unto them, This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath sent. ^30They said therefore unto him, What then doest thou for a sign, that we may see, and believe thee? what workest thou? ^31Our fathers ate the manna in the wilderness; as it is written, He gave them bread out of heaven to eat. ^32Jesus therefore said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, It was not Moses that gave you the bread out of heaven; but my Father giveth you the true bread out of heaven. ^33For the bread of God is that which cometh down out of heaven, and giveth life unto the world. ^34They said therefore unto him, Lord, evermore give us this bread. ^35Jesus said unto them. I am the bread of life: he that cometh to me shall not hunger, and he that believeth on me shall never thirst. ^36But I said unto you, that ye have seen me, and yet believe not. ^37All that which the Father giveth me shall come unto me; and him that cometh to me I will in no wise cast out. ^38For I am come down from heaven, not to do mine own will, but the will of him that sent me. ^39And this is the will of him that sent me, that of all that which he hath given me I should lose nothing, but should raise it up at the last day. ^40For this is the will of my Father, that every one that beholdeth the Son, and believeth on him, should have eternal life; and I will raise him up at the last day. ^41The Jews therefore murmured concerning him, because he said, I am the bread which came down out of heaven. ^42And they said, Is not this Jesus, the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? how doth he now say, I am come down out of heaven? ^43Jesus answered and said unto them, Murmur not among yourselves. ^44No man can come to me, except the Father that sent me draw him: and I will raise him up in the last day. ^45It is written in the prophets, And they shall all be taught of God. Every one that hath heard from the Father, and hath learned, cometh unto me. ^46Not that any man hath seen the Father, save he that is from God, he hath seen the Father. ^47Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that believeth hath eternal life. ^48I am the bread of life. ^49Your fathers ate the manna in the wilderness, and they died. ^50This is the bread which cometh down out of heaven, that a man may eat thereof, and not die. ^51I am the living bread which came down out of heaven: if any man eat of this bread, he shall live for ever: yea and the bread which I will give is my flesh, for the life of the world. ^52The Jews therefore strove one with another, saying, How can this man give us his flesh to eat? ^53Jesus therefore said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except ye eat the flesh of the Son of man and drink his blood, ye have not life in yourselves. ^54He that eateth my flesh and drinketh my blood hath eternal life: and I will raise him up at the last day. ^55For my flesh is meat indeed, and my blood is drink indeed. ^56He that eateth my flesh and drinketh my blood abideth in me, and I in him. ^57As the living Father sent me, and I live because of the Father; so he that eateth me, he also shall live because of me. ^58This is the bread which came down out of heaven: not as the fathers ate, and died; he that eateth this bread shall live for ever. ^59These things said he in the synagogue, as he taught in Capernaum. ^60Many therefore of his disciples, when they heard this, said, This is a hard saying; who can hear it? ^61But Jesus knowing in himself that his disciples murmured at this, said unto them, Doth this cause you to stumble? ^62What then if ye should behold the Son of man ascending where he was before? ^63It is the spirit that giveth life; the flesh profiteth nothing: the words that I have spoken unto you are spirit, and are life. ^64But there are some of you that believe not. For Jesus knew from the beginning who they were that believed not, and who it was that should betray him. ^65And he said, For this cause have I said unto you, that no man can come unto me, except it be given unto him of the Father. ^66Upon this many of his disciples went back, and walked no more with him. ^67Jesus said therefore unto the twelve, Would ye also go away? ^68Simon Peter answered him, Lord, to whom shall we go? thou hast the words of eternal life. ^69And we have believed and know that thou art the Holy One of God. ^70Jesus answered them, Did not I choose you the twelve, and one of you is a devil? ^71Now he spake of Judas the son of Simon Iscariot, for he it was that should betray him, being one of the twelve.

John 7

7

^1And after these things Jesus walked in Galilee: for he would not walk in Judaea, because the Jews sought to kill him. ^2Now the feast of the Jews, the feast of tabernacles, was at hand. ^3His brethren therefore said unto him, Depart hence, and go into Judaea, that thy disciples also may behold thy works which thou doest. ^4For no man doeth anything in secret, and himself seeketh to be known openly. If thou doest these things, manifest thyself to the world. ^5For even his brethren did not believe on him. ^6Jesus therefore saith unto them, My time is not yet come; but your time is always ready. ^7The world cannot hate you; but me it hateth, because I testify of it, that its works are evil. ^8Go ye up unto the feast: I go not up unto this feast; because my time is not yet fulfilled. ^9And having said these things unto them, he abode still in Galilee. ^10But when his brethren were gone up unto the feast, then went he also up, not publicly, but as it were in secret. ^11The Jews therefore sought him at the feast, and said, Where is he? ^12And there was much murmuring among the multitudes concerning him: some said, He is a good man; others said, Not so, but he leadeth the multitude astray. ^13Yet no man spake openly of him for fear of the Jews. ^14But when it was now the midst of the feast Jesus went up into the temple, and taught. ^15The Jews therefore marvelled, saying, How knoweth this man letters, having never learned? ^16Jesus therefore answered them and said, My teaching is not mine, but his that sent me. ^17If any man willeth to do his will, he shall know of the teaching, whether it is of God, or whether I speak from myself. ^18He that speaketh from himself seeketh his own glory: but he that seeketh the glory of him that sent him, the same is true, and no unrighteousness is in him. ^19Did not Moses give you the law, and yet none of you doeth the law? Why seek ye to kill me? ^20The multitude answered, Thou hast a demon: who seeketh to kill thee? ^21Jesus answered and said unto them, I did one work, and ye all marvel because thereof. ^22Moses hath given you circumcision (not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers); and on the sabbath ye circumcise a man. ^23If a man receiveth circumcision on the sabbath, that the law of Moses may not be broken; are ye wroth with me, because I made a man every whit whole on the sabbath? ^24Judge not according to appearance, but judge righteous judgment. ^25Some therefore of them of Jerusalem said, Is not this he whom they seek to kill? ^26And lo, he speaketh openly, and they say nothing unto him. Can it be that the rulers indeed know that this is the Christ? ^27Howbeit we know this man whence he is: but when the Christ cometh, no one knoweth whence he is. ^28Jesus therefore cried in the temple, teaching and saying, Ye both know me, and know whence I am; and I am not come of myself, but he that sent me is true, whom ye know not. ^29I know him; because I am from him, and he sent me. ^30They sought therefore to take him: and no man laid his hand on him, because his hour was not yet come. ^31But of the multitude many believed on him; and they said, When the Christ shall come, will he do more signs than those which this man hath done? ^32The Pharisees heard the multitude murmuring these things concerning him; and the chief priests and the Pharisees sent officers to take him. ^33Jesus therefore said, Yet a little while am I with you, and I go unto him that sent me. ^34Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me: and where I am, ye cannot come. ^35The Jews therefore said among themselves, Whither will this man go that we shall not find him? will he go unto the Dispersion among the Greeks, and teach the Greeks? ^36What is this word that he said, Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me; and where I am, ye cannot come? ^37Now on the last day, the great day of the feast, Jesus stood and cried, saying, If any man thirst, let him come unto me and drink. ^38He that believeth on me, as the span hath said, from within him shall flow rivers of living water. ^39But this spake he of the Spirit, which they that believed on him were to receive: for the Spirit was not yet given; because Jesus was not yet glorified. ^40Some of the multitude therefore, when they heard these words, said, This is of a truth the prophet. ^41Others said, This is the Christ. But some said, What, doth the Christ come out of Galilee? ^42Hath not the span said that the Christ cometh of the seed of David, and from Bethlehem, the village where David was? ^43So there arose a division in the multitude because of him. ^44And some of them would have taken him; but no man laid hands on him. ^45The officers therefore came to the chief priests and Pharisees; and they said unto them, Why did ye not bring him? ^46The officers answered, Never a man so spake. ^47The Pharisees therefore answered them, Are ye also led astray? ^48Hath any of the rulers believed on him, or of the Pharisees? ^49But this multitude that knoweth not the law are accursed. ^50Nicodemus saith unto them (he that came to him before, being one of them), ^51Doth our law judge a man, except it first hear from himself and know what he doeth? ^52They answered and said unto him, Art thou also of Galilee? Search, and see that out of Galilee ariseth no prophet.

^53And they went every man unto his own house:

John 8

8

^1but Jesus went unto the mount of Olives. ^2And early in the morning he came again into the temple, and all the people came unto him; and he sat down, and taught them. ^3And the scribes and the Pharisees bring a woman taken in adultery; and having set her in the midst, ^4they say unto him, Teacher, this woman hath been taken in adultery, in the very act. ^5Now in the law Moses commanded us to stone such: what then sayest thou of her? ^6And this they said, trying him, that they might have whereof to accuse him. But Jesus stooped down, and with his finger wrote on the ground. ^7But when they continued asking him, he lifted up himself, and said unto them, He that is without sin among you, let him first cast a stone at her. ^8And again he stooped down, and with his finger wrote on the ground. ^9And they, when they heard it, went out one by one, beginning from the eldest, even unto the last: and Jesus was left alone, and the woman, where she was, in the midst. ^10And Jesus lifted up himself, and said unto her, Woman, where are they? did no man condemn thee? ^11And she said, No man, Lord. And Jesus said, Neither do I condemn thee: go thy way; from henceforth sin no more. ^12Again therefore Jesus spake unto them, saying, I am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in the darkness, but shall have the light of life. ^13The Pharisees therefore said unto him, Thou bearest witness of thyself; thy witness is not true. ^14Jesus answered and said unto them, Even if I bear witness of myself, my witness is true; for I know whence I came, and whither I go; but ye know not whence I come, or whither I go. ^15Ye judge after the flesh; I judge no man. ^16Yea and if I judge, my judgment is true; for I am not alone, but I and the Father that sent me. ^17Yea and in your law it is written, that the witness of two men is true. ^18I am he that beareth witness of myself, and the Father that sent me beareth witness of me. ^19They said therefore unto him, Where is thy Father? Jesus answered, Ye know neither me, nor my Father: if ye knew me, ye would know my Father also. ^20These words spake he in the treasury, as he taught in the temple: and no man took him; because his hour was not yet come. ^21He said therefore again unto them, I go away, and ye shall seek me, and shall die in your sin: whither I go, ye cannot come. ^22The Jews therefore said, Will he kill himself, that he saith, Whither I go, ye cannot come? ^23And he said unto them, Ye are from beneath; I am from above: ye are of this world; I am not of this world. ^24I said therefore unto you, that ye shall die in your sins: for except ye believe that I am he, ye shall die in your sins. ^25They said therefore unto him, Who art thou? Jesus said unto them, Even that which I have also spoken unto you from the beginning. ^26I have many things to speak and to judge concerning you: howbeit he that sent me is true; and the things which I heard from him, these speak I unto the world. ^27They perceived not that he spake to them of the Father. ^28Jesus therefore said, When ye have lifted up the Son of man, then shall ye know that I am he, and that I do nothing of myself, but as the Father taught me, I speak these things. ^29And he that sent me is with me; he hath not left me alone; for I do always the things that are pleasing to him. ^30As he spake these things, many believed on him. ^31Jesus therefore said to those Jews that had believed him, If ye abide in my word, then are ye truly my disciples; ^32and ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free. ^33They answered unto him, We are Abraham's seed, and have never yet been in bondage to any man: how sayest thou, Ye shall be made free? ^34Jesus answered them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Every one that committeth sin is the bondservant of sin. ^35And the bondservant abideth not in the house for ever: the son abideth for ever. ^36If therefore the Son shall make you free, ye shall be free indeed. ^37I know that ye are Abraham's seed: yet ye seek to kill me, because my word hath not free course in you. ^38I speak the things which I have seen with my Father: and ye also do the things which ye heard from your father. ^39They answered and said unto him, Our father is Abraham. Jesus saith unto them, If ye were Abraham's children, ye would do the works of Abraham. ^40But now ye seek to kill me, a man that hath told you the truth, which I heard from God: this did not Abraham. ^41Ye do the works of your father. They said unto him, We were not born of fornication; we have one Father, even God. ^42Jesus said unto them, If God were your Father, ye would love me: for I came forth and am come from God; for neither have I come of myself, but he sent me. ^43Why do ye not understand my speech? Even because ye cannot hear my word. ^44Ye are of your father the devil, and the lusts of your father it is your will to do. He was a murderer from the beginning, and standeth not in the truth, because there is no truth in him. When he speaketh a lie, he speaketh of his own: for he is a liar, and the father thereof. ^45But because I say the truth, ye believe me not. ^46Which of you convicteth me of sin? If I say truth, why do ye not believe me? ^47He that is of God heareth the words of God: for this cause ye hear them not, because ye are not of God. ^48The Jews answered and said unto him, Say we not well that thou art a Samaritan, and hast a demon? ^49Jesus answered, I have not a demon; but I honor my Father, and ye dishonor me. ^50But I seek not mine own glory: there is one that seeketh and judgeth. ^51Verily, verily, I say unto you, If a man keep my word, he shall never see death. ^52The Jews said unto him, Now we know that thou hast a demon. Abraham died, and the prophets; and thou sayest, If a man keep my word, he shall never taste of death. ^53Art thou greater than our father Abraham, who died? and the prophets died: whom makest thou thyself? ^54Jesus answered, If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing: it is my Father that glorifieth me; of whom ye say, that he is your God; ^55and ye have not known him: but I know him; and if I should say, I know him not, I shall be like unto you, a liar: but I know him, and keep his word. ^56Your father Abraham rejoiced to see my day; and he saw it, and was glad. ^57The Jews therefore said unto him, Thou art not yet fifty years old, and hast thou seen Abraham? ^58Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Before Abraham was born, I am. ^59They took up stones therefore to cast at him: but Jesus hid himself, and went out of the temple.

John 9

9

^1And as he passed by, he saw a man blind from his birth. ^2And his disciples asked him, saying, Rabbi, who sinned, this man, or his parents, that he should be born blind? ^3Jesus answered, Neither did this man sin, nor his parents: but that the works of God should be made manifest in him. ^4We must work the works of him that sent me, while it is day: the night cometh, when no man can work. ^5When I am in the world, I am the light of the world. ^6When he had thus spoken, he spat on the ground, and made clay of the spittle, and anointed his eyes with the clay, ^7and said unto him, Go, wash in the pool of Siloam (which is by interpretation, Sent). He went away therefore, and washed, and came seeing. ^8The neighbors therefore, and they that saw him aforetime, that he was a beggar, said, Is not this he that sat and begged? ^9Others said, It is he: others said, No, but he is like him. He said, I am he. ^10They said therefore unto him, How then were thine eyes opened? ^11He answered, The man that is called Jesus made clay, and anointed mine eyes, and said unto me, Go to Siloam, and wash: so I went away and washed, and I received sight. ^12And they said unto him, Where is he? He saith, I know not. ^13They bring to the Pharisees him that aforetime was blind. ^14Now it was the sabbath on the day when Jesus made the clay, and opened his eyes. ^15Again therefore the Pharisees also asked him how he received his sight. And he said unto them, He put clay upon mine eyes, and I washed, and I see. ^16Some therefore of the Pharisees said, This man is not from God, because he keepeth not the sabbath. But others said, How can a man that is a sinner do such signs? And there was division among them. ^17They say therefore unto the blind man again, What sayest thou of him, in that he opened thine eyes? And he said, He is a prophet. ^18The Jews therefore did not believe concerning him, that he had been blind, and had received his sight, until they called the parents of him that had received his sight, ^19and asked them, saying, Is this your son, who ye say was born blind? How then doth he now see? ^20His parents answered and said, We know that this is our son, and that he was born blind: ^21but how he now seeth, we know not; or who opened his eyes, we know not: ask him; he is of age; he shall speak for himself. ^22These things said his parents, because they feared the Jews: for the Jews had agreed already, that if any man should confess him to be Christ, he should be put out of the synagogue. ^23Therefore said his parents, He is of age; ask him. ^24So they called a second time the man that was blind, and said unto him, Give glory to God: we know that this man is a sinner. ^25He therefore answered, Whether he is a sinner, I know not: one thing I know, that, whereas I was blind, now I see. ^26They said therefore unto him, What did he to thee? How opened he thine eyes? ^27He answered them, I told you even now, and ye did not hear; wherefore would ye hear it again? would ye also become his disciples? ^28And they reviled him, and said, Thou art his disciple; but we are disciples of Moses. ^29We know that God hath spoken unto Moses: but as for this man, we know not whence he is. ^30The man answered and said unto them, Why, herein is the marvel, that ye know not whence he is, and yet he opened mine eyes. ^31We know that God heareth not sinners: but if any man be a worshipper of God, and do his will, him he heareth. ^32Since the world began it was never heard that any one opened the eyes of a man born blind. ^33If this man were not from God, he could do nothing. ^34They answered and said unto him, Thou wast altogether born in sins, and dost thou teach us? And they cast him out. ^35Jesus heard that they had cast him out; and finding him, he said, Dost thou believe on the Son of God? ^36He answered and said, And who is he, Lord, that I may believe on him? ^37Jesus said unto him, Thou hast both seen him, and he it is that speaketh with thee. ^38And he said, Lord, I believe. And he worshipped him. ^39And Jesus said, For judgment came I into this world, that they that see not may see; and that they that see may become blind. ^40Those of the Pharisees who were with him heard these things, and said unto him, Are we also blind? ^41Jesus said unto them, If ye were blind, ye would have no sin: but now ye say, We see: your sin remaineth.

John 10

10

^1Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that entereth not by the door into the fold of the sheep, but climbeth up some other way, the same is a thief and a robber. ^2But he that entereth in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep. ^3To him the porter openeth; and the sheep hear his voice: and he calleth his own sheep by name, and leadeth them out. ^4When he hath put forth all his own, he goeth before them, and the sheep follow him: for they know his voice. ^5And a stranger will they not follow, but will flee from him: for they know not the voice of strangers. ^6This parable spake Jesus unto them: but they understood not what things they were which he spake unto them. ^7Jesus therefore said unto them again, Verily, verily, I say unto you, I am the door of the sheep. ^8All that came before me are thieves and robbers: but the sheep did not hear them. ^9I am the door; by me if any man enter in, he shall be saved, and shall go in and go out, and shall find pasture. ^10The thief cometh not, but that he may steal, and kill, and destroy: I came that they may have life, and may have it abundantly. ^11I am the good shepherd: the good shepherd layeth down his life for the sheep. ^12He that is a hireling, and not a shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, beholdeth the wolf coming, and leaveth the sheep, and fleeth, and the wolf snatcheth them, and scattereth them: ^13he fleeth because he is a hireling, and careth not for the sheep. ^14I am the good shepherd; and I know mine own, and mine own know me, ^15even as the Father knoweth me, and I know the Father; and I lay down my life for the sheep. ^16And other sheep I have, which are not of this fold: them also I must bring, and they shall hear my voice: and they shall become one flock, one shepherd. ^17Therefore doth the Father love me, because I lay down my life, that I may take it again. ^18No one taketh it away from me, but I lay it down of myself. I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again. This commandment received I from my Father. ^19There arose a division again among the Jews because of these words. ^20And many of them said, He hath a demon, and is mad; why hear ye him? ^21Others said, These are not the sayings of one possessed with a demon. Can a demon open the eyes of the blind? ^22And it was the feast of the dedication at Jerusalem: ^23it was winter; and Jesus was walking in the temple in Solomon's porch. ^24The Jews therefore came round about him, and said unto him, How long dost thou hold us in suspense? If thou art the Christ, tell us plainly. ^25Jesus answered them, I told you, and ye believe not: the works that I do in my Father's name, these bear witness of me. ^26But ye believe not, because ye are not of my sheep. ^27My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me: ^28and I give unto them eternal life; and they shall never perish, and no one shall snatch them out of my hand. ^29My Father, who hath given them unto me, is greater than all; and no one is able to snatch them out of the Father's hand. ^30I and the Father are one. ^31The Jews took up stones again to stone him. ^32Jesus answered them, Many good works have I showed you from the Father; for which of those works do ye stone me? ^33The Jews answered him, For a good work we stone thee not, but for blasphemy; and because that thou, being a man, makest thyself God. ^34Jesus answered them, Is it not written in your law, I said, ye are gods? ^35If he called them gods, unto whom the word of God came (and the span cannot be broken), ^36say ye of him, whom the Father sanctified and sent into the world, Thou blasphemest; because I said, I am the Son of God? ^37If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not. ^38But if I do them, though ye believe not me, believe the works: that ye may know and understand that the Father is in me, and I in the Father. ^39They sought again to take him: and he went forth out of their hand. ^40And he went away again beyond the Jordan into the place where John was at the first baptizing; and there be abode. ^41And many came unto him; and they said, John indeed did no sign: but all things whatsoever John spake of this man were true. ^42And many believed on him there.

John 11

11

^1Now a certain man was sick, Lazarus of Bethany, of the village of Mary and her sister Martha. ^2And it was that Mary who anointed the Lord with ointment, and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick. ^3The sisters therefore sent unto him, saying, Lord, behold, he whom thou lovest is sick. ^4But when Jesus heard it, he said, This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, that the Son of God may be glorified thereby. ^5Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus. ^6When therefore he heard that he was sick, he abode at that time two days in the place where he was. ^7Then after this he saith to the disciples, Let us go into Judaea again. ^8The disciples say unto him, Rabbi, the Jews were but now seeking to stone thee; and goest thou thither again? ^9Jesus answered, Are there not twelve hours in the day? If a man walk in the day, he stumbleth not, because he seeth the light of this world. ^10But if a man walk in the night, he stumbleth, because the light is not in him. ^11These things spake he: and after this he saith unto them, Our friend Lazarus is fallen asleep; but I go, that I may awake him out of sleep. ^12The disciples therefore said unto him, Lord, if he is fallen asleep, he will recover. ^13Now Jesus had spoken of his death: but they thought that he spake of taking rest in sleep. ^14Then Jesus therefore said unto them plainly, Lazarus is dead. ^15And I am glad for your sakes that I was not there, to the intent ye may believe; nevertheless let us go unto him. ^16Thomas therefore, who is called Didymus, said unto his fellow-disciples, Let us also go, that we may die with him. ^17So when Jesus came, he found that he had been in the tomb four days already. ^18Now Bethany was nigh unto Jerusalem, about fifteen furlongs off; ^19and many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary, to console them concerning their brother. ^20Martha therefore, when she heard that Jesus was coming, went and met him: but Mary still sat in the house. ^21Martha therefore said unto Jesus, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died. ^22And even now I know that, whatsoever thou shalt ask of God, God will give thee. ^23Jesus saith unto her, Thy brother shall rise again. ^24Martha saith unto him, I know that he shall rise again in the resurrection at the last day. ^25Jesus said unto her, I am the resurrection, and the life: he that believeth on me, though he die, yet shall he live; ^26and whosoever liveth and believeth on me shall never die. Believest thou this? ^27She saith unto him, Yea, Lord: I have believed that thou art the Christ, the Son of God, even he that cometh into the world. ^28And when she had said this, she went away, and called Mary her sister secretly, saying, The Teacher is her, and calleth thee. ^29And she, when she heard it, arose quickly, and went unto him. ^30(Now Jesus was not yet come into the village, but was still in the place where Martha met him.) ^31The Jews then who were with her in the house, and were consoling her, when they saw Mary, that she rose up quickly and went out, followed her, supposing that she was going unto the tomb to weep there. ^32Mary therefore, when she came where Jesus was, and saw him, fell down at his feet, saying unto him, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died. ^33When Jesus therefore saw her weeping, and the Jews also weeping who came with her, he groaned in the spirit, and was troubled, ^34and said, Where have ye laid him? They say unto him, Lord, come and see. ^35Jesus wept. ^36The Jews therefore said, Behold how he loved him! ^37But some of them said, Could not this man, who opened the eyes of him that was blind, have caused that this man also should not die? ^38Jesus therefore again groaning in himself cometh to the tomb. Now it was a cave, and a stone lay against it. ^39Jesus saith, Take ye away the stone. Martha, the sister of him that was dead, saith unto him, Lord, by this time the body decayeth; for he hath been dead four days. ^40Jesus saith unto her, Said I not unto thee, that, if thou believedst, thou shouldest see the glory of God? ^41So they took away the stone. And Jesus lifted up his eyes, and said, Father, I thank thee that thou heardest me. ^42And I knew that thou hearest me always: but because of the multitude that standeth around I said it, that they may believe that thou didst send me. ^43And when he had thus spoken, he cried with a loud voice, Lazarus, come forth. ^44He that was dead came forth, bound hand and foot with grave-clothes; and his face was bound about with a napkin. Jesus saith unto them, Loose him, and let him go. ^45Many therefore of the Jews, who came to Mary and beheld that which he did, believed on him. ^46But some of them went away to the Pharisees, and told them the things which Jesus had done. ^47The chief priests therefore and the Pharisees gathered a council, and said, What do we? for this man doeth many signs. ^48If we let him thus alone, all men will believe on him: and the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation. ^49But a certain one of them, Caiaphas, being high priest that year, said unto them, Ye know nothing at all, ^50nor do ye take account that it is expedient for you that one man should die for the people, and that the whole nation perish not. ^51Now this he said not of himself: but, being high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus should die for the nation; ^52and not for the nation only, but that he might also gather together into one the children of God that are scattered abroad. ^53So from that day forth they took counsel that they might put him to death. ^54Jesus therefore walked no more openly among the Jews, but departed thence into the country near to the wilderness, into a city called Ephraim; and there he tarried with the disciples. ^55Now the passover of the Jews was at hand: and many went up to Jerusalem out of the country before the passover, to purify themselves. ^56They sought therefore for Jesus, and spake one with another, as they stood in the temple, What think ye? That he will not come to the feast? ^57Now the chief priests and the Pharisees had given commandment, that, if any man knew where he was, he should show it, that they might take him.

John 12

12

^1Jesus therefore six days before the passover came to Bethany, where Lazarus was, whom Jesus raised from the dead. ^2So they made him a supper there: and Martha served; but Lazarus was one of them that sat at meat with him. ^3Mary therefore took a pound of ointment of pure nard, very precious, and anointed the feet of Jesus, and wiped his feet with her hair: and the house was filled with the odor of the ointment. ^4But Judas Iscariot, one of his disciples, that should betray him, saith, ^5Why was not this ointment sold for three hundred shillings, and given to the poor? ^6Now this he said, not because he cared for the poor; but because he was a thief, and having the bag took away what was put therein. ^7Jesus therefore said, Suffer her to keep it against the day of my burying. ^8For the poor ye have always with you; but me ye have not always. ^9The common people therefore of the Jews learned that he was there: and they came, not for Jesus' sake only, but that they might see Lazarus also, whom he had raised from the dead. ^10But the chief priests took counsel that they might put Lazarus also to death; ^11because that by reason of him many of the Jews went away, and believed on Jesus. ^12On the morrow a great multitude that had come to the feast, when they heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem, ^13took the branches of the palm trees, and went forth to meet him, and cried out, Hosanna: Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord, even the King of Israel. ^14And Jesus, having found a young ass, sat thereon; as it is written, ^15Fear not, daughter of Zion: behold, thy King cometh, sitting on an ass's colt. ^16These things understood not his disciples at the first: but when Jesus was glorified, then remembered they that these things were written of him, and that they had done these things unto him. ^17The multitude therefore that was with him when he called Lazarus out of the tomb, and raised him from the dead, bare witness. ^18For this cause also the multitude went and met him, for that they heard that he had done this sign. ^19The Pharisees therefore said among themselves, Behold how ye prevail nothing: lo, the world is gone after him. ^20Now there were certain Greeks among those that went up to worship at the feast: ^21these therefore came to Philip, who was of Bethsaida of Galilee, and asked him, saying, Sir, we would see Jesus. ^22Philip cometh and telleth Andrew: Andrew cometh, and Philip, and they tell Jesus. ^23And Jesus answereth them, saying, The hour is come, that the Son of man should be glorified. ^24Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except a grain of wheat fall into the earth and die, it abideth by itself alone; but if it die, it beareth much fruit. ^25He that loveth his life loseth it; and he that hateth his life in this world shall keep it unto life eternal. ^26If any man serve me, let him follow me; and where I am, there shall also my servant be: if any man serve me, him will the Father honor. ^27Now is my soul troubled; and what shall I say? Father, save me from this hour. But for this cause came I unto this hour. ^28Father, glorify thy name. There came therefore a voice out of heaven, saying, I have both glorified it, and will glorify it again. ^29The multitude therefore, that stood by, and heard it, said that it had thundered: others said, An angel hath spoken to him. ^30Jesus answered and said, This voice hath not come for my sake, but for your sakes. ^31Now is the judgment of this world: now shall the prince of this world be cast out. ^32And I, if I be lifted up from the earth, will draw all men unto myself. ^33But this he said, signifying by what manner of death he should die. ^34The multitude therefore answered him, We have heard out of the law that the Christ abideth for ever: and how sayest thou, The Son of man must be lifted up? who is this Son of man? ^35Jesus therefore said unto them, Yet a little while is the light among you. Walk while ye have the light, that darkness overtake you not: and he that walketh in the darkness knoweth not whither he goeth. ^36While ye have the light, believe on the light, that ye may become sons of light. These things spake Jesus, and he departed and hid himself from them. ^37But though he had done so many signs before them, yet they believed not on him: ^38that the word of Isaiah the prophet might be fulfilled, which he spake,

Lord, who hath believed our report?

And to whom hath the arm of the Lord been revealed?

^39For this cause they could not believe, for that Isaiah said again,

^40He hath blinded their eyes, and he hardened their heart;

Lest they should see with their eyes, and perceive with their heart,

And should turn,

And I should heal them.

^41These things said Isaiah, because he saw his glory; and he spake of him. ^42Nevertheless even of the rulers many believed on him; but because of the Pharisees they did not confess it, lest they should be put out of the synagogue: ^43for they loved the glory that is of men more than the glory that is of God. ^44And Jesus cried and said, He that believeth on me, believeth not on me, but on him that sent me. ^45And he that beholdeth me beholdeth him that sent me. ^46I am come a light into the world, that whosoever believeth on me may not abide in the darkness. ^47And if any man hear my sayings, and keep them not, I judge him not: for I came not to judge the world, but to save the world. ^48He that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my sayings, hath one that judgeth him: the word that I spake, the same shall judge him in the last day. ^49For I spake not from myself; but the Father that sent me, he hath given me a commandment, what I should say, and what I should speak. ^50And I know that his commandment is life eternal: the things therefore which I speak, even as the Father hath said unto me, so I speak.

John 13

13

^1Now before the feast of the passover, Jesus knowing that his hour was come that he should depart out of this world unto his Father, having loved his own that were in the world, he loved them unto the end. ^2And during supper, the devil having already put into the heart of Judas Iscariot, Simon's son, to betray him, ^3Jesus, knowing that the Father had given all the things into his hands, and that he came forth from God, and goeth unto God, ^4riseth from supper, and layeth aside his garments; and he took a towel, and girded himself. ^5Then he poureth water into the basin, and began to wash the disciples' feet, and to wipe them with the towel wherewith he was girded. ^6So he cometh to Simon Peter. He saith unto him, Lord, dost thou wash my feet? ^7Jesus answered and said unto him, What I do thou knowest not now; but thou shalt understand hereafter. ^8Peter saith unto him, Thou shalt never wash my feet. Jesus answered him, If I wash thee not, thou hast no part with me. ^9Simon Peter saith unto him, Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head. ^10Jesus saith to him, He that is bathed needeth not save to wash his feet, but is clean every whit: and ye are clean, but not all. ^11For he knew him that should betray him; therefore said he, Ye are not all clean. ^12So when he had washed their feet, and taken his garments, and sat down again, he said unto them, Know ye what I have done to you? ^13Ye call me, Teacher, and, Lord: and ye say well; for so I am. ^14If I then, the Lord and the Teacher, have washed your feet, ye also ought to wash one another's feet. ^15For I have given you an example, that ye also should do as I have done to you. ^16Verily, verily, I say unto you, a servant is not greater than his lord; neither one that is sent greater than he that sent him. ^17If ye know these things, blessed are ye if ye do them. ^18I speak not of you all: I know whom I have chosen: but that the span may be fulfilled: He that eateth my bread lifted up his heel against me. ^19From henceforth I tell you before it come to pass, that, when it is come to pass, ye may believe that I am he. ^20Verily, verily, I say unto you, he that receiveth whomsoever I send receiveth me; and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me. ^21When Jesus had thus said, he was troubled in the spirit, and testified, and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, that one of you shall betray me. ^22The disciples looked one on another, doubting of whom he spake. ^23There was at the table reclining in Jesus' bosom one of his disciples, whom Jesus loved. ^24Simon Peter therefore beckoneth to him, and saith unto him, Tell us who it is of whom he speaketh. ^25He leaning back, as he was, on Jesus' breast saith unto him, Lord, who is it? ^26Jesus therefore answereth, He it is, for whom I shall dip the sop, and give it him. So when he had dipped the sop, he taketh and giveth it to Judas, the son of Simon Iscariot. ^27And after the sop, then entered Satan into him. Jesus therefore saith unto him, What thou doest, do quickly. ^28Now no man at the table knew for what intent he spake this unto him. ^29For some thought, because Judas had the bag, that Jesus said unto him, Buy what things we have need of for the feast; or, that he should give something to the poor. ^30He then having received the sop went out straightway: and it was night. ^31When therefore he was gone out, Jesus saith, Now is the Son of man glorified, and God is glorified in him; ^32and God shall glorify him in himself, and straightway shall he glorify him. ^33Little children, yet a little while I am with you. Ye shall seek me: and as I said unto the Jews, Whither I go, ye cannot come; so now I say unto you. ^34A new commandment I give unto you, that ye love one another; even as I have loved you, that ye also love one another. ^35By this shall all men know that ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another. ^36Simon Peter saith unto him, Lord, whither goest thou? Jesus answered, Whither I go, thou canst not follow now; but thou shalt follow afterwards. ^37Peter saith unto him, Lord, why cannot I follow thee even now? I will lay down my life for thee. ^38Jesus answereth, Wilt thou lay down thy life for me? Verily, verily, I say unto thee, The cock shall not crow, till thou hast denied me thrice.

John 14

14

^1Let not your heart be troubled: believe in God, believe also in me. ^2In my Father's house are many mansions; if it were not so, I would have told you; for I go to prepare a place for you. ^3And if I go and prepare a place for you, I come again, and will receive you unto myself; that where I am, there ye may be also. ^4And whither I go, ye know the way. ^5Thomas saith unto him, Lord, we know not whither thou goest; how know we the way? ^6Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, and the truth, and the life: no one cometh unto the Father, but by me. ^7If ye had known me, ye would have known my Father also: from henceforth ye know him, and have seen him. ^8Philip saith unto him, Lord, show us the Father, and it sufficeth us. ^9Jesus saith unto him, Have I been so long time with you, and dost thou not know me, Philip? he that hath seen me hath seen the Father; how sayest thou, Show us the Father? ^10Believest thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? the words that I say unto you I speak not from myself: but the Father abiding in me doeth his works. ^11Believe me that I am in the Father, and the Father in me: or else believe me for the very works' sake. ^12Verily, verily, I say unto you, he that believeth on me, the works that I do shall he do also; and greater works than these shall he do; because I go unto the Father. ^13And whatsoever ye shall ask in my name, that will I do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son. ^14If ye shall ask anything in my name, that will I do. ^15If ye love me, ye will keep my commandments. ^16And I will pray the Father, and he shall give you another Comforter, that he may be with you for ever, ^17even the Spirit of truth: whom the world cannot receive; for it beholdeth him not, neither knoweth him: ye know him; for he abideth with you, and shall be in you. ^18I will not leave you desolate: I come unto you. ^19Yet a little while, and the world beholdeth me no more; but ye behold me: because I live, ye shall live also. ^20In that day ye shall know that I am in my Father, and ye in me, and I in you. ^21He that hath my commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me: and he that loveth me shall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifest myself unto him. ^22Judas (not Iscariot) saith unto him, Lord, what is come to pass that thou wilt manifest thyself unto us, and not unto the world? ^23Jesus answered and said unto him, If a man love me, he will keep my word: and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him. ^24He that loveth me not keepeth not my words: and the word which ye hear is not mine, but the Father's who sent me. ^25These things have I spoken unto you, while yet abiding with you. ^26But the Comforter, even the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and bring to your remembrance all that I said unto you. ^27Peace I leave with you; my peace I give unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto you. Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be fearful. ^28Ye heard how I said to you, I go away, and I come unto you. If ye loved me, ye would have rejoiced, because I go unto the Father: for the Father is greater than I. ^29And now I have told you before it come to pass, that, when it is come to pass, ye may believe. ^30I will no more speak much with you, for the prince of the world cometh: and he hath nothing in me; ^31but that the world may know that I love the Father, and as the Father gave me commandment, even so I do. Arise, let us go hence.

John 15

15

^1I am the true vine, and my Father is the husbandman. ^2Every branch in me that beareth not fruit, he taketh it away: and every branch that beareth fruit, he cleanseth it, that it may bear more fruit. ^3Already ye are clean because of the word which I have spoken unto you. ^4Abide in me, and I in you. As the branch cannot bear fruit of itself, except it abide in the vine; so neither can ye, except ye abide in me. ^5I am the vine, ye are the branches: He that abideth in me, and I in him, the same beareth much fruit: for apart from me ye can do nothing. ^6If a man abide not in me, he is cast forth as a branch, and is withered; and they gather them, and cast them into the fire, and they are burned. ^7If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ask whatsoever ye will, and it shall be done unto you. ^8Herein is my Father glorified, that ye bear much fruit; and so shall ye be my disciples. ^9Even as the Father hath loved me, I also have loved you: abide ye in my love. ^10If ye keep my commandments, ye shall abide in my love; even as I have kept my Father's commandments, and abide in his love. ^11These things have I spoken unto you, that my joy may be in you, and that your joy may be made full. ^12This is my commandment, that ye love one another, even as I have loved you. ^13Greater love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends. ^14Ye are my friends, if ye do the things which I command you. ^15No longer do I call you servants; for the servant knoweth not what his lord doeth: but I have called you friends; for all things that I heard from my Father, I have made known unto you. ^16Ye did not choose me, but I chose you, and appointed you, that ye should go and bear fruit, and that your fruit should abide: that whatsoever ye shall ask of the Father in my name, he may give it you. ^17These things I command you, that ye may love one another. ^18If the world hateth you, ye know that it hath hated me before it hated you. ^19If ye were of the world, the world would love its own: but because ye are not of the world, but I chose you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you. ^20Remember the word that I said unto you, A servant is not greater than his lord. If they persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they kept my word, they will keep yours also. ^21But all these things will they do unto you for my name's sake, because they know not him that sent me. ^22If I had not come and spoken unto them, they had not had sin: but now they have no excuse for their sin. ^23He that hateth me hateth my Father also. ^24If I had not done among them the works which none other did, they had not had sin: but now have they both seen and hated both me and my Father. ^25But this cometh to pass, that the word may be fulfilled that is written in their law, They hated me without a cause. ^26But when the Comforter is come, whom I will send unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of truth, which proceedeth from the Father, he shall bear witness of me: ^27and ye also bear witness, because ye have been with me from the beginning.

John 16

16

^1These things have I spoken unto you, that ye should not be caused to stumble. ^2They shall put you out of the synagogues: yea, the hour cometh, that whosoever killeth you shall think that he offereth service unto God. ^3And these things will they do, because they have not known the Father, nor me. ^4But these things have I spoken unto you, that when their hour is come, ye may remember them, how that I told you. And these things I said not unto you from the beginning, because I was with you. ^5But now I go unto him that sent me; and none of you asketh me, Whither goest thou? ^6But because I have spoken these things unto you, sorrow hath filled your heart. ^7Nevertheless I tell you the truth: It is expedient for you that I go away; for if I go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you; but if I go, I will send him unto you. ^8And he, when he is come, will convict the world in respect of sin, and of righteousness, and of judgment: ^9of sin, because they believe not on me; ^10of righteousness, because I go to the Father, and ye behold me no more; ^11of judgment, because the prince of this world hath been judged. ^12I have yet many things to say unto you, but ye cannot bear them now. ^13Howbeit when he, the Spirit of truth, is come, he shall guide you into all the truth: for he shall not speak from himself; but what things soever he shall hear, these shall he speak: and he shall declare unto you the things that are to come. ^14He shall glorify me: for he shall take of mine, and shall declare it unto you. ^15All things whatsoever the Father hath are mine: therefore said I, that he taketh of mine, and shall declare it unto you. ^16A little while, and ye behold me no more; and again a little while, and ye shall see me. ^17Some of his disciples therefore said one to another, What is this that he saith unto us, A little while, and ye behold me not; and again a little while, and ye shall see me: and, Because I go to the Father? ^18They said therefore, What is this that he saith, A little while? We know not what he saith. ^19Jesus perceived that they were desirous to ask him, and he said unto them, Do ye inquire among yourselves concerning this, that I said, A little while, and ye behold me not, and again a little while, and ye shall see me? ^20Verily, verily, I say unto you, that ye shall weep and lament, but the world shall rejoice: ye shall be sorrowful, but your sorrow shall be turned into joy. ^21A woman when she is in travail hath sorrow, because her hour is come: but when she is delivered of the child, she remembereth no more the anguish, for the joy that a man is born into the world. ^22And ye therefore now have sorrow: but I will see you again, and your heart shall rejoice, and your joy no one taketh away from you. ^23And in that day ye shall ask me no question. Verily, verily, I say unto you, if ye shall ask anything of the Father, he will give it you in my name. ^24Hitherto have ye asked nothing in my name: ask, and ye shall receive, that your joy may be made full. ^25These things have I spoken unto you in dark sayings: the hour cometh, when I shall no more speak unto you in dark sayings, but shall tell you plainly of the Father. ^26In that day ye shall ask in my name: and I say not unto you, that I will pray the Father for you; ^27for the Father himself loveth you, because ye have loved me, and have believed that I came forth from the Father. ^28I came out from the Father, and am come into the world: again, I leave the world, and go unto the Father. ^29His disciples say, Lo, now speakest thou plainly, and speakest no dark saying. ^30Now know we that thou knowest all things, and needest not that any man should ask thee: by this we believe that thou camest forth from God. ^31Jesus answered them, Do ye now believe? ^32Behold, the hour cometh, yea, is come, that ye shall be scattered, every man to his own, and shall leave me alone: and yet I am not alone, because the Father is with me. ^33These things have I spoken unto you, that in me ye may have peace. In the world ye have tribulation: but be of good cheer; I have overcome the world.

John 17

17

^1These things spake Jesus; and lifting up his eyes to heaven, he said, Father, the hour is come; glorify thy Son, that the son may glorify thee: ^2even as thou gavest him authority over all flesh, that to all whom thou hast given him, he should give eternal life. ^3And this is life eternal, that they should know thee the only true God, and him whom thou didst send, even Jesus Christ. ^4I glorified thee on the earth, having accomplished the work which thou hast given me to do. ^5And now, Father, glorify thou me with thine own self with the glory which I had with thee before the world was. ^6I manifested thy name unto the men whom thou gavest me out of the world: thine they were, and thou gavest them to me; and they have kept thy word. ^7Now they know that all things whatsoever thou hast given me are from thee: ^8for the words which thou gavest me I have given unto them; and they received them, and knew of a truth that I came forth from thee, and they believed that thou didst send me. ^9I pray for them: I pray not for the world, but for those whom thou hast given me; for they are thine: ^10and all things that are mine are thine, and thine are mine: and I am glorified in them. ^11And I am no more in the world, and these are in the world, and I come to thee. Holy Father, keep them in thy name which thou hast given me, that they may be one, even as we are. ^12While I was with them, I kept them in thy name which thou hast given me: and I guarded them, and not one of them perished, but the son of perdition; that the span might be fulfilled. ^13But now I come to thee; and these things I speak in the world, that they may have my joy made full in themselves. ^14I have given them thy word; and the world hated them, because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world. ^15I pray not that thou shouldest take them from the world, but that thou shouldest keep them from the evil one. ^16They are not of the world even as I am not of the world. ^17Sanctify them in the truth: thy word is truth. ^18As thou didst send me into the world, even so sent I them into the world. ^19And for their sakes I sanctify myself, that they themselves also may be sanctified in truth. ^20Neither for these only do I pray, but for them also that believe on me through their word; ^21that they may all be one; even as thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be in us: that the world may believe that thou didst send me. ^22And the glory which thou hast given me I have given unto them; that they may be one, even as we are one; ^23I in them, and thou in me, that they may be perfected into one; that the world may know that thou didst send me, and lovedst them, even as thou lovedst me. ^24Father, I desire that they also whom thou hast given me be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory, which thou hast given me: for thou lovedst me before the foundation of the world. ^25O righteous Father, the world knew thee not, but I knew thee; and these knew that thou didst send me; ^26and I made known unto them thy name, and will make it known; that the love wherewith thou lovedst me may be in them, and I in them.

John 18

18

^1When Jesus had spoken these words, he went forth with his disciples over the brook Kidron, where was a garden, into which he entered, himself and his disciples. ^2Now Judas also, who betrayed him, knew the place: for Jesus oft-times resorted thither with his disciples. ^3Judas then, having received the band of soldiers, and officers from the chief priests and the Pharisees, cometh thither with lanterns and torches and weapons. ^4Jesus therefore, knowing all the things that were coming upon him, went forth, and saith unto them, Whom seek ye? ^5They answered him, Jesus of Nazareth. Jesus saith unto them, I am he. And Judas also, who betrayed him, was standing with them. ^6When therefore he said unto them, I am he, they went backward, and fell to the ground. ^7Again therefore he asked them, Whom seek ye? And they said, Jesus of Nazareth. ^8Jesus answered, I told you that I am he; if therefore ye seek me, let these go their way: ^9that the word might be fulfilled which he spake, Of those whom thou hast given me I lost not one. ^10Simon Peter therefore having a sword drew it, and struck the high priest's servant, and cut off his right ear. Now the servant's name was Malchus. ^11Jesus therefore said unto Peter, Put up the sword into the sheath: the cup which the Father hath given me, shall I not drink it? ^12So the band and the chief captain, and the officers of the Jews, seized Jesus and bound him, ^13and led him to Annas first; for he was father in law to Caiaphas, who was high priest that year. ^14Now Caiaphas was he that gave counsel to the Jews, that it was expedient that one man should die for the people. ^15And Simon Peter followed Jesus, and so did another disciple. Now that disciple was known unto the high priest, and entered in with Jesus into the court of the high priest; ^16but Peter was standing at the door without. So the other disciple, who was known unto the high priest, went out and spake unto her that kept the door, and brought in Peter. ^17The maid therefore that kept the door saith unto Peter, Art thou also one of this man's disciples? He saith, I am not. ^18Now the servants and the officers were standing there, having made a fire of coals; for it was cold; and they were warming themselves: and Peter also was with them, standing and warming himself. ^19The high priest therefore asked Jesus of his disciples, and of his teaching. ^20Jesus answered him, I have spoken openly to the world; I ever taught in synagogues, and in the temple, where all the Jews come together; and in secret spake I nothing. ^21Why askest thou me? Ask them that have heard me, what I spake unto them: behold, these know the things which I said. ^22And when he had said this, one of the officers standing by struck Jesus with his hand, saying, Answerest thou the high priest so? ^23Jesus answered him, If I have spoken evil, bear witness of the evil: but if well, why smitest thou me? ^24Annas therefore sent him bound unto Caiaphas the high priest. ^25Now Simon Peter was standing and warming himself. They said therefore unto him, Art thou also one of his disciples? He denied, and said, I am not. ^26One of the servants of the high priest, being a kinsman of him whose ear Peter cut off, saith, Did not I see thee in the garden with him? ^27Peter therefore denied again: and straightway the cock crew. ^28They lead Jesus therefore from Caiaphas into the Praetorium: and it was early; and they themselves entered not into the Praetorium, that they might not be defiled, but might eat the passover. ^29Pilate therefore went out unto them, and saith, What accusation bring ye against this man? ^30They answered and said unto him, If this man were not an evildoer, we should not have delivered him up unto thee. ^31Pilate therefore said unto them, Take him yourselves, and judge him according to your law. The Jews said unto him, It is not lawful for us to put any man to death: ^32that the word of Jesus might be fulfilled, which he spake, signifying by what manner of death he should die. ^33Pilate therefore entered again into the Praetorium, and called Jesus, and said unto him, Art thou the King of the Jews? ^34Jesus answered, Sayest thou this of thyself, or did others tell it thee concerning me? ^35Pilate answered, Am I a Jew? Thine own nation and the chief priests delivered thee unto me: what hast thou done? ^36Jesus answered, My kingdom is not of this world: if my kingdom were of this world, then would my servants fight, that I should not be delivered to the Jews: but now is my kingdom not from hence. ^37Pilate therefore said unto him, Art thou a king then? Jesus answered, Thou sayest that I am a king. To this end have I been born, and to this end am I come into the world, that I should bear witness unto the truth. Every one that is of the truth heareth my voice. ^38Pilate saith unto him, What is truth? And when he had said this, he went out again unto the Jews, and saith unto them, I find no crime in him. ^39But ye have a custom, that I should release unto you one at the passover: will ye therefore that I release unto you the King of the Jews? ^40They cried out therefore again, saying, Not this man, but Barabbas. Now Barabbas was a robber.)

John 19

19

^1Then Pilate therefore took Jesus, and scourged him. ^2And the soldiers platted a crown of thorns, and put it on his head, and arrayed him in a purple garment; ^3and they came unto him, and said, Hail, King of the Jews! and they struck him with their hands. ^4And Pilate went out again, and saith unto them, Behold, I bring him out to you, that ye may know that I find no crime in him. ^5Jesus therefore came out, wearing the crown of thorns and the purple garment. And Pilate saith unto them, Behold, the man! ^6When therefore the chief priests and the officers saw him, they cried out, saying, Crucify him, crucify him! Pilate saith unto them, Take him yourselves, and crucify him: for I find no crime in him. ^7The Jews answered him, We have a law, and by that law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God. ^8When Pilate therefore heard this saying, he was the more afraid; ^9and he entered into the Praetorium again, and saith unto Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus gave him no answer. ^10Pilate therefore saith unto him, Speakest thou not unto me? Knowest thou not that I have power to release thee, and have power to crucify thee? ^11Jesus answered him, Thou wouldest have no power against me, except it were given thee from above: therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath greater sin. ^12Upon this Pilate sought to release him: but the Jews cried out, saying, If thou release this man, thou art not Caesar's friend: every one that maketh himself a king speaketh against Caesar. ^13When Pilate therefore heard these words, he brought Jesus out, and sat down on the judgment-seat at a place called The Pavement, but in Hebrew, Gabbatha. ^14Now it was the Preparation of the passover: it was about the sixth hour. And he saith unto the Jews, Behold, your King! ^15They therefore cried out, Away with him, away with him, crucify him! Pilate saith unto them, Shall I crucify your King? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Caesar. ^16Then therefore he delivered him unto them to be crucified. ^17They took Jesus therefore: and he went out, bearing the cross for himself, unto the place called The place of a skull, which is called in Hebrew, Golgotha: ^18where they crucified him, and with him two others, on either side one, and Jesus in the midst. ^19And Pilate wrote a title also, and put it on the cross. And there was written, JESUS OF NAZARETH, THE KING OF THE JEWS. ^20This title therefore read many of the Jews, for the place where Jesus was crucified was nigh to the city; and it was written in Hebrew, and in Latin, and in Greek. ^21The chief priests of the Jews therefore said to Pilate, Write not, The King of the Jews; but that he said, I am King of the Jews. ^22Pilate answered, What I have written I have written. ^23The soldiers therefore, when they had crucified Jesus, took his garments and made four parts, to every soldier a part; and also the coat: now the coat was without seam, woven from the top throughout. ^24They said therefore one to another, Let us not rend it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be: that the span might be fulfilled, which saith,

They parted my garments among them,

And upon my vesture did they cast lots.

^25These things therefore the soldiers did. But there were standing by the cross of Jesus his mother, and his mother's sister, Mary the wife of Clopas, and Mary Magdalene. ^26When Jesus therefore saw his mother, and the disciple standing by whom he loved, he saith unto his mother, Woman, behold thy son! ^27Then saith he to the disciple, Behold, thy mother! And from that hour the disciple took her unto his own home. ^28After this Jesus, knowing that all things are now finished, that the span might be accomplished, saith, I thirst. ^29There was set there a vessel full of vinegar: so they put a sponge full of the vinegar upon hyssop, and brought it to his mouth. ^30When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up his spirit. ^31The Jews therefore, because it was the Preparation, that the bodies should not remain on the cross upon the sabbath (for the day of that sabbath was a high day), asked of Pilate that their legs might be broken, and that they might be taken away. ^32The soldiers therefore came, and brake the legs of the first, and of the other that was crucified with him: ^33but when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already, they brake not his legs: ^34howbeit one of the soldiers with a spear pierced his side, and straightway there came out blood and water. ^35And he that hath seen hath borne witness, and his witness is true: and he knoweth that he saith true, that ye also may believe. ^36For these things came to pass, that the span might be fulfilled, A bone of him shall not be broken. ^37And again another span saith, They shall look on him whom they pierced. ^38And after these things Joseph of Arimathaea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly for fear of the Jews, asked of Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus: and Pilate gave him leave. He came therefore, and took away his body. ^39And there came also Nicodemus, he who at the first came to him by night, bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about a hundred pounds. ^40So they took the body of Jesus, and bound it in linen cloths with the spices, as the custom of the Jews is to bury. ^41Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden; and in the garden a new tomb wherein was never man yet laid. ^42There then because of the Jews' Preparation (for the tomb was nigh at hand) they laid Jesus.

John 20

20

^1Now on the first day of the week cometh Mary Magdalene early, while it was yet dark, unto the tomb, and seeth the stone taken away from the tomb. ^2She runneth therefore, and cometh to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple whom Jesus loved, and saith unto them, They have taken away the Lord out of the tomb, and we know not where they have laid him. ^3Peter therefore went forth, and the other disciple, and they went toward the tomb. ^4And they ran both together: and the other disciple outran Peter, and came first to the tomb; ^5and stooping and looking in, he seeth the linen cloths lying; yet entered he not in. ^6Simon Peter therefore also cometh, following him, and entered into the tomb; and he beholdeth the linen cloths lying, ^7and the napkin, that was upon his head, not lying with the linen cloths, but rolled up in a place by itself. ^8Then entered in therefore the other disciple also, who came first to the tomb, and he saw, and believed. ^9For as yet they knew not the span, that he must rise from the dead. ^10So the disciples went away again unto their own home. ^11But Mary was standing without at the tomb weeping: so, as she wept, she stooped and looked into the tomb; ^12and she beholdeth two angels in white sitting, one at the head, and one at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain. ^13And they say unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? She saith unto them, Because they have taken away my Lord, and I know not where they have laid him. ^14When she had thus said, she turned herself back, and beholdeth Jesus standing, and knew not that it was Jesus. ^15Jesus saith unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? whom seekest thou? She, supposing him to be the gardener, saith unto him, Sir, if thou hast borne him hence, tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will take him away. ^16Jesus saith unto her, Mary. She turneth herself, and saith unto him in Hebrew, Rabboni; which is to say, Teacher. ^17Jesus saith to her, Touch me not; for I am not yet ascended unto the Father: but go unto my brethren, and say to them, I ascend unto my Father and your Father, and my God and your God. ^18Mary Magdalene cometh and telleth the disciples, I have seen the Lord; and that he had said these things unto her. ^19When therefore it was evening, on that day, the first day of the week, and when the doors were shut where the disciples were, for fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in the midst, and saith unto them, Peace be unto you. ^20And when he had said this, he showed unto them his hands and his side. The disciples therefore were glad, when they saw the Lord. ^21Jesus therefore said to them again, Peace be unto you: as the Father hath sent me, even so send I you. ^22And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Spirit: ^23whose soever sins ye forgive, they are forgiven unto them; whose soever sins ye retain, they are retained. ^24But Thomas, one of the twelve, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came. ^25The other disciples therefore said unto him, We have seen the Lord. But he said unto them, Except I shall see in his hands the print of the nails, and put my hand into his side, I will not believe. ^26And after eight days again his disciples were within, and Thomas with them. Jesus cometh, the doors being shut, and stood in the midst, and said, Peace be unto you. ^27Then saith he to Thomas, Reach hither thy finger, and see my hands; and reach hither thy hand, and put it into my side: and be not faithless, but believing. ^28Thomas answered and said unto him, My Lord and my God. ^29Jesus saith unto him, Because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed: blessed are they that have not seen, and yet have believed. ^30Many other signs therefore did Jesus in the presence of the disciples, which are not written in this book: ^31but these are written, that ye may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God; and that believing ye may have life in his name.

John 21

21

^1After these things Jesus manifested himself again to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias; and he manifested himself on this wise. ^2There was together Simon Peter, and Thomas called Didymus, and Nathanael of Cana in Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two other of his disciples. ^3Simon Peter saith unto them, I go a fishing. They say unto him, We also come with thee. They went forth, and entered into the boat; and that night they took nothing. ^4But when day was now breaking, Jesus stood on the beach: yet the disciples knew not that it was Jesus. ^5Jesus therefore saith unto them, Children, have ye aught to eat? They answered him, No. ^6And he said unto them, Cast the net on the right side of the boat, and ye shall find. They cast therefore, and now they were not able to draw it for the multitude of fishes. ^7That disciple therefore whom Jesus loved saith unto Peter, It is the Lord. So when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he girt his coat about him (for he was naked), and cast himself into the sea. ^8But the other disciples came in the little boat (for they were not far from the land, but about two hundred cubits off), dragging the net full of fishes. ^9So when they got out upon the land, they see a fire of coals there, and fish laid thereon, and bread. ^10Jesus saith unto them, Bring of the fish which ye have now taken. ^11Simon Peter therefore went up, and drew the net to land, full of great fishes, a hundred and fifty and three: and for all there were so many, the net was not rent. ^12Jesus saith unto them, Come and break your fast. And none of the disciples durst inquire of him, Who art thou? knowing that it was the Lord. ^13Jesus cometh, and taketh the bread, and giveth them, and the fish likewise. ^14This is now the third time that Jesus was manifested to the disciples, after that he was risen from the dead. ^15So when they had broken their fast, Jesus saith to Simon Peter, Simon, son of John, lovest thou me more than these? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, Feed my lambs. ^16He saith to him again a second time, Simon, son of John, lovest thou me? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, Tend my sheep. ^17He saith unto him the third time, Simon, son of John, lovest thou me? Peter was grieved because he said unto him the third time, Lovest thou me? And he said unto him, Lord, thou knowest all things; thou knowest that I love thee. Jesus saith unto him, Feed my sheep. ^18Verily, verily, I say unto thee, When thou wast young, thou girdedst thyself, and walkedst whither thou wouldest: but when thou shalt be old, thou shalt stretch forth thy hands, and another shall gird thee, and carry thee whither thou wouldest not. ^19Now this he spake, signifying by what manner of death he should glorify God. And when he had spoken this, he saith unto him, Follow me. ^20Peter, turning about, seeth the disciple whom Jesus loved following; who also leaned back on his breast at the supper, and said, Lord, who is he that betrayeth thee? ^21Peter therefore seeing him saith to Jesus, Lord, and what shall this man do? ^22Jesus saith unto him, If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? Follow thou me. ^23This saying therefore went forth among the brethren, that that disciple should not die: yet Jesus said not unto him, that he should not die; but, If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? ^24This is the disciple that beareth witness of these things, and wrote these things: and we know that his witness is true. ^25And there are also many other things which Jesus did, the which if they should be written every one, I suppose that even the world itself would not contain the books that should be written.

Jonah 3

3

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto Jonah the second time, saying, ^2Arise, go unto Nineveh, that great city, and preach unto it the preaching that I bid thee. ^3So Jonah arose, and went unto Nineveh, according to the word of Jehovah. Now Nineveh was an exceeding great city, of three days' journey. ^4And Jonah began to enter into the city a day's journey, and he cried, and said, Yet forty days, and Nineveh shall be overthrown. ^5And the people of Nineveh believed God; and they proclaimed a fast, and put on sackcloth, from the greatest of them even to the least of them. ^6And the tidings reached the king of Nineveh, and he arose from his throne, and laid his robe from him, and covered him with sackcloth, and sat in ashes. ^7And he made proclamation and published through Nineveh by the decree of the king and his nobles, saying, Let neither man nor beast, herd nor flock, taste anything; let them not feed, nor drink water; ^8but let them be covered with sackcloth, both man and beast, and let them cry mightily unto God: yea, let them turn every one from his evil way, and from the violence that is in his hands. ^9Who knoweth whether God will not turn and repent, and turn away from his fierce anger, that we perish not? ^10And God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way; and God repented of the evil which he said he would do unto them; and he did it not.

Jonah 4

4

^1But it displeased Jonah exceedingly, and he was angry. ^2And he prayed unto Jehovah, and said, I pray thee, O Jehovah, was not this my saying, when I was yet in my country? Therefore I hasted to flee unto Tarshish; for I knew that thou art a gracious God, and merciful, slow to anger, and abundant in lovingkindness, and repentest thee of the evil. ^3Therefore now, O Jehovah, take, I beseech thee, my life from me; for it is better for me to die than to live. ^4And Jehovah said, Doest thou well to be angry? ^5Then Jonah went out of the city, and sat on the east side of the city, and there made him a booth, and sat under it in the shade, till he might see what would become of the city. ^6And Jehovah God prepared a gourd, and made it to come up over Jonah, that it might be a shade over his head, to deliver him from his evil case. So Jonah was exceeding glad because of the gourd. ^7But God prepared a worm when the morning rose the next day, and it smote the gourd, that it withered. ^8And it came to pass, when the sun arose, that God prepared a sultry east wind; and the sun beat upon the head of Jonah, that he fainted, and requested for himself that he might die, and said, It is better for me to die than to live. ^9And God said to Jonah, Doest thou well to be angry for the gourd? And he said, I do well to be angry, even unto death. ^10And Jehovah said, Thou hast had regard for the gourd, for which thou hast not labored, neither madest it grow; which came up in a night, and perished in a night: ^11and should not I have regard for Nineveh, that great city, wherein are more than sixscore thousand persons that cannot discern between their right hand and their left hand; and also much cattle?

Joshua 2

2

^1And Joshua the son of Nun sent out of Shittim two men as spies secretly, saying, Go, view the land, and Jericho. And they went and came into the house of a harlot whose name was Rahab, and lay there. ^2And it was told the king of Jericho, saying, Behold, there came men in hither to-night of the children of Israel to search out the land. ^3And the king of Jericho sent unto Rahab, saying, Bring forth the men that are come to thee, that are entered into thy house; for they are come to search out all the land. ^4And the woman took the two men, and hid them; and she said, Yea, the men came unto me, but I knew not whence they were: ^5and it came to pass about the time of the shutting of the gate, when it was dark, that the men went out; whither the men went I know not: pursue after them quickly; for ye will overtake them. ^6But she had brought them up to the roof, and hid them with the stalks of flax, which she had laid in order upon the roof. ^7And the men pursued after them the way to the Jordan unto the fords: and as soon as they that pursued after them were gone out, they shut the gate.

^8And before they were laid down, she came up unto them upon the roof; ^9and she said unto the men, I know that Jehovah hath given you the land, and that the fear of you is fallen upon us, and that all the inhabitants of the land melt away before you. ^10For we have heard how Jehovah dried up the water of the Red Sea before you, when ye came out of Egypt; and what ye did unto the two kings of the Amorites, that were beyond the Jordan, unto Sihon and to Og, whom ye utterly destroyed. ^11And as soon as we had heard it, our hearts did melt, neither did there remain any more spirit in any man, because of you: for Jehovah your God, he is God in heaven above, and on earth beneath. ^12Now therefore, I pray you, swear unto me by Jehovah, since I have dealt kindly with you, that ye also will deal kindly with my father's house, and give me a true token; ^13and that ye will save alive my father, and my mother, and my brethren, and my sisters, and all that they have, and will deliver our lives from death. ^14And the men said unto her, Our life for yours, if ye utter not this our business; and it shall be, when Jehovah giveth us the land, that we will deal kindly and truly with thee.

^15Then she let them down by a cord through the window: for her house was upon the side of the wall, and she dwelt upon the wall. ^16And she said unto them, Get you to the mountain, lest the pursuers light upon you; and hide yourselves there three days, until the pursuers be returned: and afterward may ye go your way. ^17And the men said unto her, We will be guiltless of this thine oath which thou hast made us to swear. ^18Behold, when we come into the land, thou shalt bind this line of scarlet thread in the window which thou didst let us down by: and thou shalt gather unto thee into the house thy father, and thy mother, and thy brethren, and all thy father's household. ^19And it shall be, that whosoever shall go out of the doors of thy house into the street, his blood shall be upon his head, and we shall be guiltless: and whosoever shall be with thee in the house, his blood shall be on our head, if any hand be upon him. ^20But if thou utter this our business, then we shall be guiltless of thine oath which thou hast made us to swear. ^21And she said, According unto your words, so be it. And she sent them away, and they departed: and she bound the scarlet line in the window.

^22And they went, and came unto the mountain, and abode there three days, until the pursuers were returned: and the pursuers sought them throughout all the way, but found them not. ^23Then the two men returned, and descended from the mountain, and passed over, and came to Joshua the son of Nun; and they told him all that had befallen them. ^24And they said unto Joshua, Truly Jehovah hath delivered into our hands all the land; and moreover all the inhabitants of the land do melt away before us.

Joshua 3

3

^1And Joshua rose up early in the morning; and they removed from Shittim, and came to the Jordan, he and all the children of Israel; and they lodged there before they passed over. ^2And it came to pass after three days, that the officers went through the midst of the camp; ^3and they commanded the people, saying, When ye see the ark of the covenant of Jehovah your God, and the priests the Levites bearing it, then ye shall remove from your place, and go after it. ^4Yet there shall be a space between you and it, about two thousand cubits by measure: come not near unto it, that ye may know the way by which ye must go; for ye have not passed this way heretofore. ^5And Joshua said unto the people, Sanctify yourselves; for tomorrow Jehovah will do wonders among you. ^6And Joshua spake unto the priests, saying, Take up the ark of the covenant, and pass over before the people. And they took up the ark of the covenant, and went before the people.

^7And Jehovah said unto Joshua, This day will I begin to magnify thee in the sight of all Israel, that they may know that, as I was with Moses, so I will be with thee. ^8And thou shalt command the priests that bear the ark of the covenant, saying, When ye are come to the brink of the waters of the Jordan, ye shall stand still in the Jordan. ^9And Joshua said unto the children of Israel, Come hither, and hear the words of Jehovah your God. ^10And Joshua said, Hereby ye shall know that the living God is among you, and that he will without fail drive out from before you the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Hivite, and the Perizzite, and the Girgashite, and the Amorite, and the Jebusite. ^11Behold, the ark of the covenant of the Lord of all the earth passeth over before you into the Jordan. ^12Now therefore take you twelve men out of the tribes of Israel, for every tribe a man. ^13And it shall come to pass, when the soles of the feet of the priests that bear the ark of Jehovah, the Lord of all the earth, shall rest in the waters of the Jordan, that the waters of the Jordan shall be cut off, even the waters that come down from above; and they shall stand in one heap.

^14And it came to pass, when the people removed from their tents, to pass over the Jordan, the priests that bare the ark of the covenant being before the people; ^15and when they that bare the ark were come unto the Jordan, and the feet of the priests that bare the ark were dipped in the brink of the water (for the Jordan overfloweth all its banks all the time of harvest,) ^16that the waters which came down from above stood, and rose up in one heap, a great way off, at Adam, the city that is beside Zarethan; and those that went down toward the sea of the Arabah, even the Salt Sea, were wholly cut off: and the people passed over right against Jericho. ^17And the priests that bare the ark of the covenant of Jehovah stood firm on dry ground in the midst of the Jordan; and all Israel passed over on dry ground, until all the nation were passed clean over the Jordan.

Joshua 5

5

^1And it came to pass, when all the kings of the Amorites, that were beyond the Jordan westward, and all the kings of the Canaanites, that were by the sea, heard how that Jehovah had dried up the waters of the Jordan from before the children of Israel, until we were passed over, that their heart melted, neither was there spirit in them any more, because of the children of Israel.

^2At that time Jehovah said unto Joshua, Make thee knives of flint, and circumcise again the children of Israel the second time. ^3And Joshua made him knives of lint, and circumcised the children of Israel at the hill of the foreskins. ^4And this is the cause why Joshua did circumcise: all the people that came forth out of Egypt, that were males, even all the men of war, died in the wilderness by the way, after they came forth out of Egypt. ^5For all the people that came out were circumcised; but all the people that were born in the wilderness by the way as they came forth out of Egypt, they had not circumcised. ^6For the children of Israel walked forty years in the wilderness, till all the nation, even the men of war that came forth out of Egypt, were consumed, because they hearkened not unto the voice of Jehovah: unto whom Jehovah sware that he would not let them see the land which Jehovah sware unto their fathers that he would give us, a land flowing with milk and honey. ^7And their children, whom he raised up in their stead, them did Joshua circumcise: for they were uncircumcised, because they had not circumcised them by the way. ^8And it came to pass, when they had done circumcising all the nation, that they abode in their places in the camp, till they were whole. ^9And Jehovah said unto Joshua, This day have I rolled away the reproach of Egypt from off you. Wherefore the name of that place was called Gilgal, unto this day.

^10And the children of Israel encamped in Gilgal; and they kept the passover on the fourteenth day of the month at even in the plains of Jericho. ^11And they did eat of the produce of the land on the morrow after the passover, unleavened cakes and parched grain, in the selfsame day. ^12And the manna ceased on the morrow, after they had eaten of the produce of the land; neither had the children of Israel manna any more; but they did eat of the fruit of the land of Canaan that year.

^13And it came to pass, when Joshua was by Jericho, that he lifted up his eyes and looked, and, behold, there stood a man over against him with his sword drawn in his hand: and Joshua went unto him, and said unto him, Art thou for us, or for our adversaries? ^14And he said, Nay; but as prince of the host of Jehovah am I now come. And Joshua fell on his face to the earth, and did worship, and said unto him, What saith my lord unto his servant? ^15And the prince of Jehovah's host said unto Joshua, Put off thy shoe from off thy foot; for the place whereon thou standest is holy. And Joshua did so.

Joshua 6

6

^1Now Jericho was straitly shut up because of the children of Israel: none went out, and none came in. ^2And Jehovah said unto Joshua, See, I have given into thy hand Jericho, and the king thereof, and the mighty men of valor. ^3And ye shall compass the city, all the men of war, going about the city once. Thus shalt thou do six days. ^4And seven priests shall bear seven trumpets of rams' horns before the ark: and the seventh day ye shall compass the city seven times, and the priests shall blow the trumpets. ^5And it shall be, that, when they make a long blast with the ram's horn, and when ye hear the sound of the trumpet, all the people shall shout with a great shout; and the wall of the city shall fall down flat, and the people shall go up every man straight before him. ^6And Joshua the son of Nun called the priests, and said unto them, Take up the ark of the covenant, and let seven priests bear seven trumpets of rams' horns before the ark of Jehovah. ^7And they said unto the people, Pass on, and compass the city, and let the armed men pass on before the ark of Jehovah.

^8And it was so, that, when Joshua had spoken unto the people, the seven priests bearing the seven trumpets of rams' horns before Jehovah passed on, and blew the trumpets: and the ark of the covenant of Jehovah followed them. ^9And the armed men went before the priests that blew the trumpets, and the rearward went after the ark, the priests blowing the trumpets as they went. ^10And Joshua commanded the people, saying, Ye shall not shout, nor let your voice be heard, neither shall any word proceed out of your mouth, until the day I bid you shout; then shall ye shout. ^11So he caused the ark of Jehovah to compass the city, going about it once: and they came into the camp, and lodged in the camp.

^12And Joshua rose early in the morning, and the priests took up the ark of Jehovah. ^13And the seven priests bearing the seven trumpets of rams' horns before the ark of Jehovah went on continually, and blew the trumpets: and the armed men went before them; and the rearward came after the ark of Jehovah, the priests blowing the trumpets as they went. ^14And the second day they compassed the city once, and returned into the camp: so they did six days.

^15And it came to pass on the seventh day, that they rose early at the dawning of the day, and compassed the city after the same manner seven times: only on the day they compassed the city seven times. ^16And it came to pass at the seventh time, when the priests blew the trumpets, Joshua said unto the people, Shout; for Jehovah hath given you the city. ^17And the city shall be devoted, even it and all that is therein, to Jehovah: only Rahab the harlot shall live, she and all that are with her in the house, because she hid the messengers that we sent. ^18But as for you, only keep yourselves from the devoted thing, lest when ye have devoted it, ye take of the devoted thing; so would ye make the camp of Israel accursed, and trouble it. ^19But all the silver, and gold, and vessels of brass and iron, are holy unto Jehovah: they shall come into the treasury of Jehovah. ^20So the people shouted, and the priests blew the trumpets; and it came to pass, when the people heard the sound of the trumpet, that the people shouted with a great shout, and the wall fell down flat, so that the people went up into the city, every man straight before him, and they took the city. ^21And they utterly destroyed all that was in the city, both man and woman, both young and old, and ox, and sheep, and ass, with the edge of the sword.

^22And Joshua said unto the two men that had spied out the land, Go into the harlot's house, and bring out thence the woman, and all that she hath, as ye sware unto her. ^23And the young men the spies went in, and brought out Rahab, and her father, and her mother, and her brethren, and all that she had; all her kindred also they brought out; and they set them without the camp of Israel. ^24And they burnt the city with fire, and all that was therein; only the silver, and the gold, and the vessels of brass and of iron, they put into the treasury of the house of Jehovah. ^25But Rahab the harlot, and her father's household, and all that she had, did Joshua save alive; and she dwelt in the midst of Israel unto this day, because she hid the messengers, whom Joshua sent to spy out Jericho. ^26And Joshua charged them with an oath at that time, saying, Cursed be the man before Jehovah, that riseth up and buildeth this city Jericho: with the loss of his first-born shall he lay the foundation thereof, and with the loss of his youngest son shall he set up the gates of it. ^27So Jehovah was with Joshua; and his fame was in all the land.

Joshua 7

7

^1But the children of Israel committed a trespass in the devoted thing; for Achan, the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, took of the devoted thing: and the anger of Jehovah was kindled against the children of Israel.

^2And Joshua sent men from Jericho to Ai, which is beside Beth-aven, on the east side of Beth-el, and spake unto them, saying, Go up and spy out the land. And the men went up and spied out Ai. ^3And they returned to Joshua, and said unto him, Let not all the people go up; but let about two or three thousand men go up and smite Ai; make not all the people to toil thither; for they are but few. ^4So there went up thither of the people about three thousand men: and they fled before the men of Ai. ^5And the men of Ai smote of them about thirty and six men; and they chased them from before the gate even unto Shebarim, and smote them at the descent; and the hearts of the people melted, and became as water.

^6And Joshua rent his clothes, and fell to the earth upon his face before the ark of Jehovah until the evening, he and the elders of Israel; and they put dust upon their heads. ^7And Joshua said, Alas, O Lord Jehovah, wherefore hast thou at all brought this people over the Jordan, to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites, to cause us to perish? would that we had been content and dwelt beyond the Jordan! ^8Oh, Lord, what shall I say, after that Israel hath turned their backs before their enemies! ^9For the Canaanites and all the inhabitants of the land will hear of it, and will compass us round, and cut off our name from the earth: and what wilt thou do for thy great name?

^10And Jehovah said unto Joshua, Get thee up; wherefore art thou thus fallen upon thy face? ^11Israel hath sinned; yea, they have even transgressed my covenant which I commanded them: yea, they have even taken of the devoted thing, and have also stolen, and dissembled also; and they have even put it among their own stuff. ^12Therefore the children of Israel cannot stand before their enemies; they turn their backs before their enemies, because they are become accursed: I will not be with you any more, except ye destroy the devoted thing from among you. ^13Up, sanctify the people, and say, Sanctify yourselves against tomorrow: for thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, There is a devoted thing in the midst of thee, O Israel; thou canst not stand before thine enemies, until ye take away the devoted thing from among you. ^14In the morning therefore ye shall be brought near by your tribes: and it shall be, that the tribe which Jehovah taketh shall come near by families; and the family which Jehovah shall take shall come near by households; and the household which Jehovah shall take shall come near man by man. ^15And it shall be, that he that is taken with the devoted thing shall be burnt with fire, he and all that he hath; because he hath transgressed the covenant of Jehovah, and because he hath wrought folly in Israel.

^16So Joshua rose up early in the morning, and brought Israel near by their tribes; and the tribe of Judah was taken: ^17and he brought near the family of Judah; and he took the family of the Zerahites: and he brought near the family of the Zerahites man by man; and Zabdi was taken: ^18and he brought near his household man by man; and Achan, the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, was taken. ^19And Joshua said unto Achan, My son, give, I pray thee, glory to Jehovah, the God of Israel, and make confession unto him; and tell me now what thou hast done; hide it not from me. ^20And Achan answered Joshua, and said, Of a truth I have sinned against Jehovah, the God of Israel, and thus and thus have I done: ^21when I saw among the spoil a goodly Babylonish mantle, and two hundred shekels of silver, and a wedge of gold of fifty shekels weight, then I coveted them, and took them; and, behold, they are hid in the earth in the midst of my tent, and the silver under it.

^22So Joshua sent messengers, and they ran unto the tent; and, behold, it was hid in his tent, and the silver under it. ^23And they took them from the midst of the tent, and brought them unto Joshua, and unto all the children of Israel; and they laid them down before Jehovah. ^24And Joshua, and all Israel with him, took Achan the son of Zerah, and the silver, and the mantle, and the wedge of gold, and his sons, and his daughters, and his oxen, and his asses, and his sheep, and his tent, and all that he had: and they brought them up unto the valley of Achor. ^25And Joshua said, Why hast thou troubled us? Jehovah shall trouble thee this day. And all Israel stoned him with stones; and they burned them with fire, and stoned them with stones. ^26And they raised over him a great heap of stones, unto this day; and Jehovah turned from the fierceness of his anger. Wherefore the name of that place was called, The valley of Achor, unto this day.

Joshua 8

8

^1And Jehovah said unto Joshua, Fear not, neither be thou dismayed: take all the people of war with thee, and arise, go up to Ai; see, I have given into thy hand the king of Ai, and his people, and his city, and his land; ^2And thou shalt do to Ai and her king as thou didst unto Jericho and her king: only the spoil thereof, and the cattle thereof, shall ye take for a prey unto yourselves: set thee an ambush for the city behind it.

^3So Joshua arose, and all the people of war, to go up to Ai: and Joshua chose out thirty thousand men, the mighty men of valor, and sent them forth by night. ^4And he commanded them, saying, Behold, ye shall lie in ambush against the city, behind the city; go not very far from the city, but be ye all ready: ^5and I, and all the people that are with me, will approach unto the city. And it shall come to pass, when they come out against us, as at the first, that we will flee before them; ^6and they will come out after us, till we have drawn them away from the city; for they will say, They flee before us, as at the first: so we will flee before them; ^7and ye shall rise up from the ambush, and take possession of the city: for Jehovah your God will deliver it into your hand. ^8And it shall be, when ye have seized upon the city, that ye shall set the city on fire; according to the word of Jehovah shall ye do: see, I have commanded you. ^9And Joshua sent them forth; and they went to the ambushment, and abode between Beth-el and Ai, on the west side of Ai: but Joshua lodged that night among the people.

^10And Joshua arose up early in the morning, and mustered the people, and went up, he and the elders of Israel, before the people to Ai. ^11And all the people, even the men of war that were with him, went up, and drew nigh, and came before the city, and encamped on the north side of Ai: now there was a valley between him and Ai. ^12And he took about five thousand men, and set them in ambush between Beth-el and Ai, on the west side of the city. ^13So they set the people, even all the host that was on the north of the city, and their liers-in-wait that were on the west of the city; and Joshua went that night into the midst of the valley. ^14And it came to pass, when the king of Ai saw it, that they hasted and rose up early, and the men of the city went out against Israel to battle, he and all his people, at the time appointed, before the Arabah; but he knew not that there was an ambush against him behind the city. ^15And Joshua and all Israel made as if they were beaten before them, and fled by the way of the wilderness. ^16And all the people that were in the city were called together to pursue after them: and they pursued after Joshua, and were drawn away from the city. ^17And there was not a man left in Ai or Beth-el, that went not out after Israel: and they left the city open, and pursued after Israel.

^18And Jehovah said unto Joshua, Stretch out the javelin that is in thy hand toward Ai; for I will give it into thy hand. And Joshua stretched out the javelin that was in his hand toward the city. ^19And the ambush arose quickly out of their place, and they ran as soon as he had stretched out his hand, and entered into the city, and took it; and they hasted and set the city on fire. ^20And when the men of Ai looked behind them, they saw, and, behold, the smoke of the city ascended up to heaven, and they had no power to flee this way or that way: and the people that fled to the wilderness turned back upon the pursuers. ^21And when Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had taken the city, and that the smoke of the city ascended, then they turned again, and slew the men of Ai. ^22And the others came forth out of the city against them; so they were in the midst of Israel, some on this side, and some on that side: and they smote them, so that they let none of them remain or escape. ^23And the king of Ai they took alive, and brought him to Joshua.

^24And it came to pass, when Israel had made an end of slaying all the inhabitants of Ai in the field, in the wilderness wherein they pursued them, and they were all fallen by the edge of the sword, until they were consumed, that all Israel returned unto Ai, and smote it with the edge of the sword. ^25And all that fell that day, both of men and women, were twelve thousand, even all the men of Ai. ^26For Joshua drew not back his hand, wherewith he stretched out the javelin, until he had utterly destroyed all the inhabitants of Ai. ^27Only the cattle and the spoil of that city Israel took for prey unto themselves, according unto the word of Jehovah which he commanded Joshua. ^28So Joshua burnt Ai, and made it a heap for ever, even a desolation, unto this day. ^29And the king of Ai he hanged on a tree until the eventide: and at the going down of the sun Joshua commanded, and they took his body down from the tree, and cast it at the entrance of the gate of the city, and raised thereon a great heap of stones, unto this day.

^30Then Joshua built an altar unto Jehovah, the God of Israel, in mount Ebal, ^31as Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded the children of Israel, as it is written in the book of the law of Moses, an altar of unhewn stones, upon which no man had lifted up any iron: and they offered thereon burnt-offerings unto Jehovah, and sacrificed peace-offerings. ^32And he wrote there upon the stones a copy of the law of Moses, which he wrote, in the presence of the children of Israel. ^33And all Israel, and their elders and officers, and their judges, stood on this side of the ark and on that side before the priests the Levites, that bare the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, as well the sojourner as the homeborn; half of them in front of mount Gerizim, and half of them in front of mount Ebal; as Moses the servant of Jehovah had commanded at the first, that they should bless the people of Israel. ^34And afterward he read all the words of the law, the blessing and the curse, according to all that is written in the book of the law. ^35There was not a word of all that Moses commanded, which Joshua read not before all the assembly of Israel, and the women, and the little ones, and the sojourners that were among them.

Joshua 9

9

^1And it came to pass, when all the kings that were beyond the Jordan, in the hill-country, and in the lowland, and on all the shore of the great sea in front of Lebanon, the Hittite, and the Amorite, the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, heard thereof; ^2that they gathered themselves together, to fight with Joshua and with Israel, with one accord.

^3But when the inhabitants of Gibeon heard what Joshua had done unto Jericho and to Ai, ^4they also did work wilily, and went and made as if they had been ambassadors, and took old sacks upon their asses, and wine-skins, old and rent and bound up, ^5and old and patched shoes upon their feet, and old garments upon them; and all the bread of their provision was dry and was become mouldy. ^6And they went to Joshua unto the camp at Gilgal, and said unto him, and to the men of Israel, We are come from a far country: now therefore make ye a covenant with us. ^7And the men of Israel said unto the Hivites, Peradventure ye dwell among us; and how shall we make a covenant with you? ^8And they said unto Joshua, We are thy servants. And Joshua said unto them, Who are ye? and from whence come ye? ^9And they said unto him, From a very far country thy servants are come because of the name of Jehovah thy God: for we have heard the fame of him, and all that he did in Egypt, ^10and all that he did to the two kings of the Amorites, that were beyond the Jordan, to Sihon king of Heshbon, and to Og king of Bashan, who was at Ashtaroth. ^11And our elders and all the inhabitants of our country spake to us, saying, Take provision in your hand for the journey, and go to meet them, and say unto them, We are your servants: and now make ye a covenant with us. ^12This our bread we took hot for our provision out of our houses on the day we came forth to go unto you; but now, behold, it is dry, and is become mouldy: ^13and these wine-skins, which we filled, were new; and, behold, they are rent: and these our garments and our shoes are become old by reason of the very long journey. ^14And the men took of their provision, and asked not counsel at the mouth of Jehovah. ^15And Joshua made peace with them, and made a covenant with them, to let them live: and the princes of the congregation sware unto them.

^16And it came to pass at the end of three days after they had made a covenant with them, that they heard that they were their neighbors, and that they dwelt among them. ^17And the children of Israel journeyed, and came unto their cities on the third day. Now their cities were Gibeon, and Chephirah, and Beeroth, and Kiriath-jearim. ^18And the children of Israel smote them not, because the princes of the congregation had sworn unto them by Jehovah, the God of Israel. And all the congregation murmured against the princes. ^19But all the princes said unto all the congregation, We have sworn unto them by Jehovah, the God of Israel: now therefore we may not touch them. ^20This we will do to them, and let them live; lest wrath be upon us, because of the oath which we sware unto them. ^21And the princes said unto them, Let them live: so they became hewers of wood and drawers of water unto all the congregation, as the princes had spoken unto them.

^22And Joshua called for them, and he spake unto them, saying, Wherefore have ye beguiled us, saying, We are very far from you; when ye dwell among us? ^23Now therefore ye are cursed, and there shall never fail to be of you bondmen, both hewers of wood and drawers of water for the house of my God. ^24And they answered Joshua, and said, Because it was certainly told thy servants, how that Jehovah thy God commanded his servant Moses to give you all the land, and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land from before you; therefore we were sore afraid for our lives because of you, and have done this thing. ^25And now, behold, we are in thy hand: as it seemeth good and right unto thee to do unto us, do. ^26And so did he unto them, and delivered them out of the hand of the children of Israel, that they slew them not. ^27And Joshua made them that day hewers of wood and drawers of water for the congregation, and for the altar of Jehovah, unto this day, in the place which he should choose.

Joshua 10

10

^1Now it came to pass, when Adoni-zedek king of Jerusalem heard how Joshua had taken Ai, and had utterly destroyed it; as he had done to Jericho and her king, so he had done to Ai and her king; and how the inhabitants of Gibeon had made peace with Israel, and were among them; ^2that they feared greatly, because Gibeon was a great city, as one of the royal cities, and because it was greater than Ai, and all the men thereof were mighty. ^3Wherefore Adoni-zedek king of Jerusalem sent unto Hoham king of Hebron, and unto Piram king of Jarmuth, and unto Japhia king of Lachish, and unto Debir king of Eglon, saying, ^4Come up unto me, and help me, and let us smite Gibeon; for it hath made peace with Joshua and with the children of Israel. ^5Therefore the five kings of the Amorites, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, the king of Eglon, gathered themselves together, and went up, they and all their hosts, and encamped against Gibeon, and made war against it.

^6And the men of Gibeon sent unto Joshua to the camp to Gilgal, saying, Slack not thy hand from thy servants; come up to us quickly, and save us, and help us: for all the kings of the Amorites that dwell in the hill-country are gathered together against us. ^7So Joshua went up from Gilgal, he, and all the people of war with him, and all the mighty men of valor. ^8And Jehovah said unto Joshua, Fear them not: for I have delivered them into thy hands; there shall not a man of them stand before thee. ^9Joshua therefore came upon them suddenly; for he went up from Gilgal all the night. ^10And Jehovah discomfited them before Israel, and he slew them with a great slaughter at Gibeon, and chased them by the way of the ascent of Beth-horon, and smote them to Azekah, and unto Makkedah. ^11And it came to pass, as they fled from before Israel, while they were at the descent of Beth-horon, that Jehovah cast down great stones from heaven upon them unto Azekah, and they died: they were more who died with the hailstones than they whom the children of Israel slew with the sword.

^12Then spake Joshua to Jehovah in the day when Jehovah delivered up the Amorites before the children of Israel; and he said in the sight of Israel,

Sun, stand thou still upon Gibeon;

And thou, Moon, in the valley of Aijalon.

^13And the sun stood still, and the moon stayed,

Until the nation had avenged themselves of their enemies.

Is not this written in the book of Jashar? And the sun stayed in the midst of heaven, and hasted not to go down about a whole day. ^14And there was no day like that before it or after it, that Jehovah hearkened unto the voice of a man: for Jehovah fought for Israel.

^15And Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, unto the camp to Gilgal.

^16And these five kings fled, and hid themselves in the cave at Makkedah. ^17And it was told Joshua, saying, The five kings are found, hidden in the cave at Makkedah. ^18And Joshua said, Roll great stones unto the mouth of the cave, and set men by it to keep them: ^19but stay not ye; pursue after your enemies, and smite the hindmost of them; suffer them not to enter into their cities: for Jehovah your God hath delivered them into your hand. ^20And it came to pass, when Joshua and the children of Israel had made an end of slaying them with a very great slaughter, till they were consumed, and the remnant which remained of them had entered into the fortified cities, ^21that all the people returned to the camp to Joshua at Makkedah in peace: none moved his tongue against any of the children of Israel.

^22Then said Joshua, Open the mouth of the cave, and bring forth those five kings unto me out of the cave. ^23And they did so, and brought forth those five kings unto him out of the cave, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, the king of Eglon. ^24And it came to pass, when they brought forth those kings unto Joshua, that Joshua called for all the men of Israel, and said unto the chiefs of the men of war that went with him, Come near, put your feet upon the necks of these kings. And they came near, and put their feet upon the necks of them. ^25And Joshua said unto them, Fear not, nor be dismayed; be strong and of good courage: for thus shall Jehovah do to all your enemies against whom ye fight. ^26And afterward Joshua smote them, and put them to death, and hanged them on five trees: and they were hanging upon the trees until the evening. ^27And it came to pass at the time of the going down of the sun, that Joshua commanded, and they took them down off the trees, and cast them into the cave wherein they had hidden themselves, and laid great stones on the mouth of the cave, unto this very day.

^28And Joshua took Makkedah on that day, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and the king thereof: he utterly destroyed them and all the souls that were therein; he left none remaining; and he did to the king of Makkedah as he had done unto the king of Jericho.

^29And Joshua passed from Makkedah, and all Israel with him, unto Libnah, and fought against Libnah: ^30and Jehovah delivered it also, and the king thereof, into the hand of Israel; and he smote it with the edge of the sword, and all the souls that were therein; he left none remaining in it; and he did unto the king thereof as he had done unto the king of Jericho.

^31And Joshua passed from Libnah, and all Israel with him, unto Lachish, and encamped against it, and fought against it: ^32and Jehovah delivered Lachish into the hand of Israel; and he took it on the second day, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and all the souls that were therein, according to all that he had done to Libnah.

^33Then Horam king of Gezer came up to help Lachish; and Joshua smote him and his people, until he had left him none remaining.

^34And Joshua passed from Lachish, and all Israel with him, unto Eglon; and they encamped against it, and fought against it; ^35and they took it on that day, and smote it with the edge of the sword; and all the souls that were therein he utterly destroyed that day, according to all that he had done to Lachish.

^36And Joshua went up from Eglon, and all Israel with him, unto Hebron; and they fought against it: ^37and they took it, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and the king thereof, and all the cities thereof, and all the souls that were therein; he left none remaining, according to all that he had done to Eglon; but he utterly destroyed it, and all the souls that were therein.

^38And Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to Debir, and fought against it: ^39and he took it, and the king thereof, and all the cities thereof; and they smote them with the edge of the sword, and utterly destroyed all the souls that were therein; he left none remaining: as he had done to Hebron, so he did to Debir, and to the king thereof; as he had done also to Libnah, and to the king thereof.

^40So Joshua smote all the land, the hill-country, and the South, and the lowland, and the slopes, and all their kings: he left none remaining, but he utterly destroyed all that breathed, as Jehovah, the God of Israel, commanded. ^41And Joshua smote them from Kadesh-barnea even unto Gaza, and all the country of Goshen, even unto Gibeon. ^42And all these kings and their land did Joshua take at one time, because Jehovah, the God of Israel, fought for Israel. ^43And Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, unto the camp to Gilgal.

Joshua 11

11

^1And it came to pass, when Jabin king of Hazor heard thereof, that he sent to Jobab king of Madon, and to the king of Shimron, and to the king of Achshaph, ^2and to the kings that were on the north, in the hill-country, and in the Arabah south of Chinneroth, and in the lowland, and in the heights of Dor on the west, ^3to the Canaanite on the east and on the west, and the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Jebusite in the hill-country, and the Hivite under Hermon in the land of Mizpah. ^4And they went out, they and all their hosts with them, much people, even as the sand that is upon the sea-shore in multitude, with horses and chariots very many. ^5And all these kings met together; and they came and encamped together at the waters of Merom, to fight with Israel.

^6And Jehovah said unto Joshua, Be not afraid because of them; for to-morrow at this time will I deliver them up all slain before Israel: thou shalt hock their horses, and burn their chariots with fire. ^7So Joshua came, and all the people of war with him, against them by the waters of Merom suddenly, and fell upon them. ^8And Jehovah delivered them into the hand of Israel, and they smote them, and chased them unto great Sidon, and unto Misrephoth-maim, and unto the valley of Mizpeh eastward; and they smote them, until they left them none remaining. ^9And Joshua did unto them as Jehovah bade him: he hocked their horses, and burnt their chariots with fire.

^10And Joshua turned back at that time, and took Hazor, and smote the king thereof with the sword: for Hazor beforetime was the head of all those kingdoms. ^11And they smote all the souls that were therein with the edge of the sword, utterly destroying them; there was none left that breathed: and he burnt Hazor with fire. ^12And all the cities of those kings, and all the kings of them, did Joshua take, and he smote them with the edge of the sword, and utterly destroyed them; as Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded. ^13But as for the cities that stood on their mounds, Israel burned none of them, save Hazor only; that did Joshua burn. ^14And all the spoil of these cities, and the cattle, the children of Israel took for a prey unto themselves; but every man they smote with the edge of the sword, until they had destroyed them, neither left they any that breathed. ^15As Jehovah commanded Moses his servant, so did Moses command Joshua: and so did Joshua; he left nothing undone of all that Jehovah commanded Moses.

^16So Joshua took all that land, the hill-country, and all the South, and all the land of Goshen, and the lowland, and the Arabah, and the hill-country of Israel, and the lowland of the same; ^17from mount Halak, that goeth up to Seir, even unto Baal-gad in the valley of Lebanon under mount Hermon: and all their kings he took, and smote them, and put them to death. ^18Joshua made war a long time with all those kings. ^19There was not a city that made peace with the children of Israel, save the Hivites the inhabitants of Gibeon: they took all in battle. ^20For it was of Jehovah to harden their hearts, to come against Israel in battle, that he might utterly destroy them, that they might have no favor, but that he might destroy them, as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^21And Joshua came at that time, and cut off the Anakim from the hill-country, from Hebron, from Debir, from Anab, and from all the hill-country of Judah, and from all the hill-country of Israel: Joshua utterly destroyed them with their cities. ^22There was none of the Anakim left in the land of the children of Israel: only in Gaza, in Gath, and in Ashdod, did some remain. ^23So Joshua took the whole land, according to all that Jehovah spake unto Moses; and Joshua gave it for an inheritance unto Israel according to their divisions by their tribes. And the land had rest from war.

Joshua 13

13

^1Now Joshua was old and well stricken in years; and Jehovah said unto him, Thou art old and well stricken in years, and there remaineth yet very much land to be possessed. ^2This is the land that yet remaineth: all the regions of the Philistines, and all the Geshurites; ^3from the Shihor, which is before Egypt, even unto the border of Ekron northward, which is reckoned to the Canaanites; the five lords of the Philistines; the Gazites, and the Ashdodites, the Ashkelonites, the Gittites, and the Ekronites; also the Avvim, ^4on the south; all the land of the Canaanites, and Mearah that belongeth to the Sidonians, unto Aphek, to the border of the Amorites; ^5and the land of the Gebalites, and all Lebanon, toward the sunrising, from Baal-gad under mount Hermon unto the entrance of Hamath; ^6all the inhabitants of the hill-country from Lebanon unto Misrephoth-maim, even all the Sidonians; them will I drive out from before the children of Israel: only allot thou it unto Israel for an inheritance, as I have commanded thee. ^7Now therefore divide this land for an inheritance unto the nine tribes, and the half-tribe of Manasseh.

^8With him the Reubenites and the Gadites received their inheritance, which Moses gave them, beyond the Jordan eastward, even as Moses the servant of Jehovah gave them: ^9from Aroer, that is on the edge of the valley of the Arnon, and the city that is in the middle of the valley, and all the plain of Medeba unto Dibon; ^10and all the cities of Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, unto the border of the children of Ammon; ^11and Gilead, and the border of the Geshurites and Maacathites, and all mount Hermon, and all Bashan unto Salecah; ^12all the kingdom of Og in Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth and in Edrei (the same was left of the remnant of the Rephaim); for these did Moses smite, and drove them out. ^13Nevertheless the children of Israel drove not out the Geshurites, nor the Maacathites: but Geshur and Maacath dwell in the midst of Israel unto this day. ^14Only unto the tribe of Levi he gave no inheritance; the offerings of Jehovah, the God of Israel, made by fire are his inheritance, as he spake unto him.

^15And Moses gave unto the tribe of the children of Reuben according to their families. ^16And their border was from Aroer, that is on the edge of the valley of the Arnon, and the city that is in the middle of the valley, and all the plain by Medeba; ^17Heshbon, and all its cities that are in the plain; Dibon, and Bamoth-baal, and Beth-baal-meon, ^18and Jahaz, and Kedemoth, and Mephaath, ^19and Kiriathaim, and Sibmah, and Zereth-shahar in the mount of the valley, ^20and Beth-peor, and the slopes of Pisgah, and Beth-jeshimoth, ^21and all the cities of the plain, and all the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, whom Moses smote with the chiefs of Midian, Evi, and Rekem, and Zur, and Hur, and Reba, the princes of Sihon, that dwelt in the land. ^22Balaam also the son of Beor, the soothsayer, did the children of Israel slay with the sword among the rest of their slain. ^23And the border of the children of Reuben was the Jordan, and the border thereof. This was the inheritance of the children of Reuben according to their families, the cities and the villages thereof.

^24And Moses gave unto the tribe of Gad, unto the children of Gad, according to their families. ^25And their border was Jazer, and all the cities of Gilead, and half the land of the children of Ammon, unto Aroer that is before Rabbah; ^26and from Heshbon unto Ramath-mizpeh, and Betonim; and from Mahanaim unto the border of Debir; ^27and in the valley, Beth-haram, and Beth-nimrah, and Succoth, and Zaphon, the rest of the kingdom of Sihon king of Heshbon, the Jordan and the border thereof, unto the uttermost part of the sea of Chinnereth beyond the Jordan eastward. ^28This is the inheritance of the children of Gad according to their families, the cities and the villages thereof.

^29And Moses gave inheritance unto the half-tribe of Manasseh: and it was for the half-tribe of the children of Manasseh according to their families. ^30And their border was from Mahanaim, all Bashan, all the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, and all the towns of Jair, which are in Bashan, threescore cities: ^31and half Gilead, and Ashtaroth, and Edrei, the cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan, were for the children of Machir the son of Manasseh, even for the half of the children of Machir according to their families.

^32These are the inheritances which Moses distributed in the plains of Moab, beyond the Jordan at Jericho, eastward. ^33But unto the tribe of Levi Moses gave no inheritance: Jehovah, the God of Israel, is their inheritance, as he spake unto them.

Joshua 14

14

^1And these are the inheritances which the children of Israel took in the land of Canaan, which Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers' houses of the tribes of the children of Israel, distributed unto them, ^2by the lot of their inheritance, as Jehovah commanded by Moses, for the nine tribes, and for the half-tribe. ^3For Moses had given the inheritance of the two tribes and the half-tribe beyond the Jordan: but unto the Levites he gave no inheritance among them. ^4For the children of Joseph were two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim: and they gave no portion unto the Levites in the land, save cities to dwell in, with the suburbs thereof for their cattle and for their substance. ^5As Jehovah commanded Moses, so the children of Israel did; and they divided the land.

^6Then the children of Judah drew nigh unto Joshua in Gilgal: and Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite said unto him, Thou knowest the thing that Jehovah spake unto Moses the man of God concerning me and concerning thee in Kadesh-barnea. ^7Forty years old was I when Moses the servant of Jehovah sent me from Kadesh-barnea to spy out the land; and I brought him word again as it was in my heart. ^8Nevertheless my brethren that went up with me made the heart of the people melt; but I wholly followed Jehovah my God. ^9And Moses sware on that day, saying, Surely the land whereon thy foot hath trodden shall be an inheritance to thee and to thy children for ever, because thou hast wholly followed Jehovah my God. ^10And now, behold, Jehovah hath kept me alive, as he spake, these forty and five years, from the time that Jehovah spake this word unto Moses, while Israel walked in the wilderness: and now, lo, I am this day fourscore and five years old. ^11As yet I am as strong this day as I as in the day that Moses sent me: as my strength was then, even so is my strength now, for war, and to go out and to come in. ^12Now therefore give me this hill-country, whereof Jehovah spake in that day; for thou heardest in that day how the Anakim were there, and cities great and fortified: it may be that Jehovah will be with me, and I shall drive them out, as Jehovah spake.

^13And Joshua blessed him; and he gave Hebron unto Caleb the son of Jephunneh for an inheritance. ^14Therefore Hebron became the inheritance of Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite unto this day; because that he wholly followed Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^15Now the name of Hebron beforetime was Kiriath-arba; which Arba was the greatest man among the Anakim. And the land had rest from war.

Joshua 15

15

^1And the lot for the tribe of the children of Judah according to their families was unto the border of Edom, even to the wilderness of Zin southward, at the uttermost part of the south. ^2And their south border was from the uttermost part of the Salt Sea, from the bay that looketh southward; ^3and it went out southward of the ascent of Akrabbim, and passed along to Zin, and went up by the south of Kadesh-barnea, and passed along by Hezron, and went up to Addar, and turned about to Karka; ^4and it passed along to Azmon, and went out at the brook of Egypt; and the goings out of the border were at the sea: this shall be your south border. ^5And the east border was the Salt Sea, even unto the end of the Jordan. And the border of the north quarter was from the bay of the sea at the end of the Jordan; ^6and the border went up to Beth-hoglah, and passed along by the north of Beth-arabah; and the border went up to the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben; ^7and the border went up to Debir from the valley of Achor, and so northward, looking toward Gilgal, that is over against the ascent of Adummim, which is on the south side of the river; and the border passed along to the waters of En-shemesh, and the goings out thereof were at En-rogel; ^8and the border went up by the valley of the son of Hinnom unto the side of the Jebusite southward (the same is Jerusalem); and the border went up to the top of the mountain that lieth before the valley of Hinnom westward, which is at the uttermost part of the vale of Rephaim northward; ^9and the border extended from the top of the mountain unto the fountain of the waters of Nephtoah, and went out to the cities of mount Ephron; and the border extended to Baalah (the same is Kiriath-jearim); ^10and the border turned about from Baalah westward unto mount Seir, and passed along unto the side of mount Jearim on the north (the same is Chesalon), and went down to Beth-shemesh, and passed along by Timnah; ^11and the border went out unto the side of Ekron northward; and the border extended to Shikkeron, and passed along to mount Baalah, and went out at Jabneel; and the goings out of the border were at the sea. ^12And the west border was to the great sea, and the border thereof. This is the border of the children of Judah round about according to their families.

^13And unto Caleb the son of Jephunneh he gave a portion among the children of Judah, according to the commandment of Jehovah to Joshua, even Kiriath-arba, which Arba was the father of Anak (the same is Hebron). ^14And Caleb drove out thence the three sons of Anak: Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai, the children of Anak. ^15And he went up thence against the inhabitants of Debir: now the name of Debir beforetime was Kiriath-sepher. ^16And Caleb said, He that smiteth Kiriath-sepher, and taketh it, to him will I give Achsah my daughter to wife. ^17And Othniel the son of Kenaz, the brother of Caleb, took it: and he gave him Achsah his daughter to wife. ^18And it came to pass, when she came unto him, that she moved him to ask of her father a field: and she alighted from off her ass; and Caleb said, What wouldest thou? ^19And she said, Give me a blessing; for that thou hast set me in the land of the South, give me also springs of water. And he gave her the upper springs and the nether springs.

^20This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Judah according to their families.

^21And the uttermost cities of the tribe of the children of Judah toward the border of Edom in the South were Kabzeel, and Eder, and Jagur, ^22and Kinah, and Dimonah, and Adadah, ^23and Kedesh, and Hazor, and Ithnan, ^24Ziph, and Telem, and Bealoth, ^25and Hazor-hadattah, and Kerioth-hezron (the same is Hazor), ^26Amam, and Shema, and Moladah, ^27and Hazar-gaddah, and Heshmon, and Beth-pelet, ^28and Hazar-shual, and Beer-sheba, and Biziothiah, ^29Baalah, and Iim, and Ezem, ^30and Eltolad, and Chesil, and Hormah, ^31and Ziklag, and Madmannah, and Sansannah, ^32and Lebaoth, and Shilhim, and Ain, and Rimmon: all the cities are twenty and nine, with their villages.

^33In the lowland, Eshtaol, and Zorah, and Ashnah, ^34and Zanoah, and En-gannim, Tappuah, and Enam, ^35Jarmuth, and Adullam, Socoh, and Azekah, ^36and Shaaraim, and Adithaim, and Gederah, and Gederothaim; fourteen cities with their villages.

^37Zenan, and Hadashah, and Migdal-gad, ^38and Dilean, and Mizpeh, and Joktheel, ^39Lachish, and Bozkath, and Eglon, ^40and Cabbon, and Lahmam, and Chitlish, ^41and Gederoth, Beth-dagon, and Naamah, and Makkedah; sixteen cities with their villages.

^42Libnah, and Ether, and Ashan, ^43and Iphtah, and Ashnah, and Nezib, ^44and Keilah, and Achzib, and Mareshah; nine cities with their villages.

^45Ekron, with its towns and its villages; ^46from Ekron even unto the sea, all that were by the side of Ashdod, with their villages.

^47Ashdod, its towns and its villages; Gaza, its towns and its villages; unto the brook of Egypt, and the great sea, and the border thereof.

^48And in the hill-country, Shamir, and Jattir, and Socoh, ^49and Dannah, and Kiriath-sannah (the same is Debir), ^50and Anab, and Eshtemoh, and Anim, ^51and Goshen, and Holon, and Giloh; eleven cities with their villages.

^52Arab, and Dumah, and Eshan, ^53and Janim, and Beth-tappuah, and Aphekah, ^54and Humtah, and Kiriath-arba (the same is Hebron), and Zior; nine cities with their villages.

^55Maon, Carmel, and Ziph, and Jutah, ^56and Jezreel, and Jokdeam, and Zanoah, ^57Kain, Gibeah, and Timnah; ten cities with their villages.

^58Halhul, Beth-zur, and Gedor, ^59and Maarath, and Beth-anoth, and Eltekon; six cities with their villages.

^60Kiriath-baal (the same is Kiriath-jearim), and Rabbah; two cities with their villages.

^61In the wilderness, Beth-arabah, Middin, and Secacah, ^62and Nibshan, and the City of Salt, and En-gedi; six cities with their villages.

^63And as for the Jebusites, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the children of Judah could not drive them out: but the Jebusites dwell with the children of Judah at Jerusalem unto this day.

Joshua 17

17

^1And this was the lot for the tribe of Manasseh; for he was the first-born of Joseph. As for Machir the first-born of Manasseh, the father of Gilead, because he was a man of war, therefore he had Gilead and Bashan. ^2So the lot was for the rest of the children of Manasseh according to their families: for the children of Abiezer, and for the children of Helek, and for the children of Asriel, and for the children of Shechem, and for the children of Hepher, and for the children of Shemida: these were the male children of Manasseh the son of Joseph according to their families. ^3But Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, had no sons, but daughters: and these are the names of his daughters: Mahlah, and Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. ^4And they came near before Eleazar the priest, and before Joshua the son of Nun, and before the princes, saying, Jehovah commanded Moses to give us an inheritance among our brethren: therefore according to the commandment of Jehovah he gave them an inheritance among the brethren of their father. ^5And there fell ten parts to Manasseh, besides the land of Gilead and Bashan, which is beyond the Jordan; ^6because the daughters of Manasseh had an inheritance among his sons. And the land of Gilead belonged unto the rest of the sons of Manasseh.

^7And the border of Manasseh was from Asher to Michmethath, which is before Shechem; and the border went along to the right hand, unto the inhabitants of En-tappuah. ^8The land of Tappuah belonged to Manasseh; but Tappuah on the border of Manasseh belonged to the children of Ephraim. ^9And the border went down unto the brook of Kanah, southward of the brook: these cities belonged to Ephraim among the cities of Manasseh: and the border of Manasseh was on the north side of the brook, and the goings out thereof were at the sea: ^10southward it was Ephraim's, and northward it was Manasseh's, and the sea was his border; and they reached to Asher on the north, and to Issachar on the east. ^11And Manasseh had in Issachar and in Asher Beth-shean and its towns, and Ibleam and its towns, and the inhabitants of Dor and its towns, and the inhabitants of En-dor and its towns, and the inhabitants of Taanach and its towns, and the inhabitants of Megiddo and its towns, even the three heights. ^12Yet the children of Manasseh could not drive out the inhabitants of those cities; but the Canaanites would dwell in that land. ^13And it came to pass, when the children of Israel were waxed strong, that they put the Canaanites to taskwork, and did not utterly drive them out.

^14And the children of Joseph spake unto Joshua, saying, Why hast thou given me but one lot and one part for an inheritance, seeing I am a great people, forasmuch as hitherto Jehovah hath blessed me? ^15And Joshua said unto them, If thou be a great people, get thee up to the forest, and cut down for thyself there in the land of the Perizzites and of the Rephaim; since the hill-country of Ephraim is too narrow for thee. ^16And the children of Joseph said, The hill-country is not enough for us: and all the Canaanites that dwell in the land of the valley have chariots of iron, both they who are in Beth-shean and its towns, and they who are in the valley of Jezreel. ^17And Joshua spake unto the house of Joseph, even to Ephraim and to Manasseh, saying, Thou art a great people, and hast great power; thou shalt not have one lot only: ^18but the hill-country shall be thine; for though it is a forest, thou shalt cut it down, and the goings out thereof shall be thine; for thou shalt drive out the Canaanites, though they have chariots of iron, and though they are strong.

Joshua 18

18

^1And the whole congregation of the children of Israel assembled themselves together at Shiloh, and set up the tent of meeting there: and the land was subdued before them. ^2And there remained among the children of Israel seven tribes, which had not yet divided their inheritance. ^3And Joshua said unto the children of Israel, How long are ye slack to go in to possess the land, which Jehovah, the God of your fathers, hath given you? ^4Appoint for you three men of each tribe: and I will send them, and they shall arise, and walk through the land, and describe it according to their inheritance; and they shall come unto me. ^5And they shall divide it into seven portions: Judah shall abide in his border on the south, and the house of Joseph shall abide in their border on the north. ^6And ye shall describe the land into seven portions, and bring the description hither to me; and I will cast lots for you here before Jehovah our God. ^7For the Levites have no portion among you; for the priesthood of Jehovah is their inheritance: and Gad and Reuben and the half-tribe of Manasseh have received their inheritance beyond the Jordan eastward, which Moses the servant of Jehovah gave them.

^8And the men arose, and went: and Joshua charged them that went to describe the land, saying, Go and walk through the land, and describe it, and come again to me; and I will cast lots for you here before Jehovah in Shiloh. ^9And the men went and passed through the land, and described it by cities into seven portions in a book; and they came to Joshua unto the camp at Shiloh. ^10And Joshua cast lots for them in Shiloh before Jehovah: and there Joshua divided the land unto the children of Israel according to their divisions.

^11And the lot of the tribe of the children of Benjamin came up according to their families: and the border of their lot went out between the children of Judah and the children of Joseph. ^12And their border on the north quarter was from the Jordan; and the border went up to the side of Jericho on the north, and went up through the hill-country westward; and the goings out thereof were at the wilderness of Beth-aven. ^13And the border passed along from thence to Luz, to the side of Luz (the same is Beth-el), southward; and the border went down to Ataroth-addar, by the mountain that lieth on the south of Beth-horon the nether. ^14And the border extended thence, and turned about on the west quarter southward, from the mountain that lieth before Beth-horon southward; and the goings out thereof were at Kiriath-baal (the same is Kiriath-jearim), a city of the children of Judah: this was the west quarter. ^15And the south quarter was from the uttermost part of Kiriath-jearim; and the border went out westward, and went out to the fountain of the waters of Nephtoah; ^16and the border went down to the uttermost part of the mountain that lieth before the valley of the son of Hinnom, which is in the vale of Rephaim northward; and it went down to the valley of Hinnom, to the side of the Jebusite southward, and went down to En-rogel; ^17and it extended northward, and went out at En-shemesh, and went out to Geliloth, which is over against the ascent of Adummim; and it went down to the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben; ^18and it passed along to the side over against the Arabah northward, and went down unto the Arabah; ^19and the border passed along to the side of Beth-hoglah northward; and the goings out of the border were at the north bay of the Salt Sea, at the south end of the Jordan: this was the south border. ^20And the Jordan was the border of it on the east quarter. This was the inheritance of the children of Benjamin, by the borders thereof round about, according to their families.

^21Now the cities of the tribe of the children of Benjamin according to their families were Jericho, and Beth-hoglah, and Emek-keziz, ^22and Beth-arabah, and Zemaraim, and Beth-el, ^23and Avvim, and Parah, and Ophrah, ^24and Chephar-ammoni, and Ophni, and Geba; twelve cities with their villages: ^25Gibeon, and Ramah, and Beeroth, ^26and Mizpeh, and Chephirah, and Mozah, ^27and Rekem, and Irpeel, and Taralah, ^28and Zelah, Eleph, and the Jebusite (the same is Jerusalem), Gibeath, and Kiriath; fourteen cities with their villages. This is the inheritance of the children of Benjamin according to their families.

Joshua 19

19

^1And the second lot came out for Simeon, even for the tribe of the children of Simeon according to their families: and their inheritance was in the midst of the inheritance of the children of Judah. ^2And they had for their inheritance Beer-sheba, or Sheba, and Moladah, ^3and Hazar-shual, and Balah, and Ezem, ^4and Eltolad, and Bethul, and Hormah, ^5and Ziklag, and Beth-marcaboth, and Hazar-susah, ^6and Beth-lebaoth, and Sharuhen; thirteen cities with their villages: ^7Ain, Rimmon, and Ether, and Ashan; four cities with their villages: ^8and all the villages that were round about these cities to Baalath-beer, Ramah of the South. This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Simeon according to their families. ^9Out of the part of the children of Judah was the inheritance of the children of Simeon; for the portion of the children of Judah was too much for them: therefore the children of Simeon had inheritance in the midst of their inheritance.

^10And the third lot came up for the children of Zebulun according to their families; and the border of their inheritance was unto Sarid; ^11and their border went up westward, even to Maralah, and reached to Dabbesheth; and it reached to the brook that is before Jokneam; ^12and it turned from Sarid eastward toward the sunrising unto the border of Chisloth-tabor; and it went out to Daberath, and went up to Japhia; ^13and from thence it passed along eastward to Gath-hepher, to Eth-kazin; and it went out at Rimmon which stretcheth unto Neah; ^14and the border turned about it on the north to Hannathon; and the goings out thereof were at the valley of Iphtah-el; ^15and Kattath, and Nahalal, and Shimron, and Idalah, and Bethlehem: twelve cities with their villages. ^16This is the inheritance of the children of Zebulun according to their families, these cities with their villages.

^17The fourth lot came out for Issachar, even for the children of Issachar according to their families. ^18And their border was unto Jezreel, and Chesulloth, and Shunem, ^19and Hapharaim, and Shion, and Anaharath, ^20and Rabbith, and Kishion, and Ebez, ^21and Remeth, and Engannim, and En-haddah, and Beth-pazzez, ^22and the border reached to Tabor, and Shahazumah, and Beth-shemesh; and the goings out of their border were at the Jordan: sixteen cities with their villages. ^23This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Issachar according to their families, the cities with their villages.

^24And the fifth lot came out for the tribe of the children of Asher according to their families. ^25And their border was Helkath, and Hali, and Beten, and Achshaph, ^26and Allammelech, and Amad, and Mishal; and it reached to Carmel westward, and to Shihor-libnath; ^27and it turned toward the sunrising to Beth-dagon, and reached to Zebulun, and to the valley of Iphtah-el northward to Beth-emek and Neiel; and it went out to Cabul on the left hand, ^28and Ebron, and Rehob, and Hammon, and Kanah, even unto great Sidon; ^29and the border turned to Ramah, and to the fortified city of Tyre; and the border turned to Hosah; and the goings out thereof were at the sea by the region of Achzib; ^30Ummah also, and Aphek, and Rehob: twenty and two cities with their villages. ^31This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Asher according to their families, these cities with their villages.

^32The sixth lot came out for the children of Naphtali, even for the children of Naphtali according to their families. ^33And their border was from Heleph, from the oak in Zaanannim, and Adaminekeb, and Jabneel, unto Lakkum; and the goings out thereof were at the Jordan; ^34and the border turned westward to Aznoth-tabor, and went out from thence to Hukkok; and it reached to Zebulun on the south, and reached to Asher on the west, and to Judah at the Jordan toward the sunrising. ^35And the fortified cities were Ziddim, Zer, and Hammath, Rakkath, and Chinnereth, ^36and Adamah, and Ramah, and Hazor, ^37and Kedesh, and Edrei, and En-hazor, ^38And Iron, and Migdal-el, Horem, and Beth-anath, and Beth-shemesh; nineteen cities with their villages. ^39This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Naphtali according to their families, the cities with their villages.

^40The seventh lot came out for the tribe of the children of Dan according to their families. ^41And the border of their inheritance was Zorah, and Eshtaol, and Ir-shemesh, ^42and Shaalabbin, and Aijalon, and Ithlah, ^43and Elon, and Timnah, and Ekron, ^44and Eltekeh, and Gibbethon, and Baalath, ^45and Jehud, and Bene-berak, and Gath-rimmon, ^46and Me-jarkon, and Rakkon, with the border over against Joppa. ^47And the border of the children of Dan went out beyond them; for the children of Dan went up and fought against Leshem, and took it, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and possessed it, and dwelt therein, and called Leshem, Dan, after the name of Dan their father. ^48This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Dan according to their families, these cities with their villages.

^49So they made an end of distributing the land for inheritance by the borders thereof; and the children of Israel gave an inheritance to Joshua the son of Nun in the midst of them: ^50according to the commandment of Jehovah they gave him the city which he asked, even Timnath-serah in the hill-country of Ephraim; and he built the city, and dwelt therein.

^51These are the inheritances, which Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers' houses of the tribes of the children of Israel, distributed for inheritance by lot in Shiloh before Jehovah, at the door of the tent of meeting. So they made an end of dividing the land.

Joshua 21

21

^1Then came near the heads of fathers' houses of the Levites unto Eleazar the priest, and unto Joshua the son of Nun, and unto the heads of fathers' houses of the tribes of the children of Israel; ^2and they spake unto them at Shiloh in the land of Canaan, saying, Jehovah commanded Moses to give us cities to dwell in, with the suburbs thereof for our cattle. ^3And the children of Israel gave unto the Levites out of their inheritance, according to the commandment of Jehovah, these cities with their suburbs.

^4And the lot came out for the families of the Kohathites: and the children of Aaron the priest, who were of the Levites, had by lot out of the tribe of Judah, and out of the tribe of the Simeonites, and out of the tribe of Benjamin, thirteen cities.

^5And the rest of the children of Kohath had by lot out of the families of the tribe of Ephraim, and out of the tribe of Dan, and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, ten cities.

^6And the children of Gershon had by lot out of the families of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities.

^7The children of Merari according to their families had out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities.

^8And the children of Israel gave by lot unto the Levites these cities with their suburbs, as Jehovah commanded by Moses. ^9And they gave out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, these cities which are here mentioned by name: ^10and they were for the children of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites, who were of the children of Levi; for theirs was the first lot. ^11And they gave them Kiriath-arba, which Arba was the father of Anak (the same is Hebron), in the hill-country of Judah, with the suburbs thereof round about it. ^12But the fields of the city, and the villages thereof, gave they to Caleb the son of Jephunneh for his possession.

^13And unto the children of Aaron the priest they gave Hebron with its suburbs, the city of refuge for the manslayer, and Libnah with its suburbs, ^14and Jattir with its suburbs, and Eshtemoa with its suburbs, ^15and Holon with its suburbs, and Debir with its suburbs, ^16and Ain with its suburbs, and Juttah with its suburbs, and Beth-shemesh with its suburbs; nine cities out of those two tribes. ^17And out of the tribe of Benjamin, Gibeon with its suburbs, Geba with its suburbs, ^18Anathoth with its suburbs, and Almon with its suburbs; four cities. ^19All the cities of the children of Aaron, the priests, were thirteen cities with their suburbs.

^20And the families of the children of Kohath, the Levites, even the rest of the children of Kohath, they had the cities of their lot out of the tribe of Ephraim. ^21And they gave them Shechem with its suburbs in the hill-country of Ephraim, the city of refuge for the manslayer, and Gezer with its suburbs, ^22and Kibzaim with its suburbs, and Beth-horon with its suburbs; four cities. ^23And out of the tribe of Dan, Elteke with its suburbs, Gibbethon with its suburbs, ^24Aijalon with its suburbs, Gath-rimmon with its suburbs; four cities. ^25And out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Taanach with its suburbs, and Gath-rimmon with its suburbs; two cities. ^26All the cities of the families of the rest of the children of Kohath were ten with their suburbs.

^27And unto the children of Gershon, of the families of the Levites, out of the half-tribe of Manasseh they gave Golan in Bashan with its suburbs, the city of refuge for the manslayer, and Be-eshterah with its suburbs; two cities. ^28And out of the tribe of Issachar, Kishion with its suburbs, Daberath with its suburbs, ^29Jarmuth with its suburbs, En-gannim with its suburbs; four cities. ^30And out of the tribe of Asher, Mishal with its suburbs, Abdon with its suburbs, ^31Helkath with its suburbs, and Rehob with its suburbs; four cities. ^32And out of the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with its suburbs, the city of refuge for the manslayer, and Hammoth-dor with its suburbs, and Kartan with its suburbs; three cities. ^33All the cities of the Gershonites according to their families were thirteen cities with their suburbs.

^34And unto the families of the children of Merari, the rest of the Levites, out of the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam with its suburbs, and Kartah with its suburbs, ^35Dimnah with its suburbs, Nahalal with its suburbs; four cities. ^36And out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer with its suburbs, and Jahaz with its suburbs, ^37Kedemoth with its suburbs, and Mephaath with its suburbs; four cities. ^38And out of the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with its suburbs, the city of refuge for the manslayer, and Mahanaim with its suburbs, ^39Heshbon with its suburbs, Jazer with its suburbs; four cities in all. ^40All these were the cities of the children of Merari according to their families, even the rest of the families of the Levites; and their lot was twelve cities.

^41All the cities of the Levites in the midst of the possession of the children of Israel were forty and eight cities with their suburbs. ^42These cities were every one with their suburbs round about them: thus it was with all these cities.

^43So Jehovah gave unto Israel all the land which he sware to give unto their fathers; and they possessed it, and dwelt therein. ^44And Jehovah gave them rest round about, according to all that he sware unto their fathers: and there stood not a man of all their enemies before them; Jehovah delivered all their enemies into their hand. ^45There failed not aught of any good thing which Jehovah had spoken unto the house of Israel; all came to pass.

Joshua 22

22

^1Then Joshua called the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, ^2and said unto them, Ye have kept all that Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded you, and have hearkened unto my voice in all that I commanded you: ^3ye have not left your brethren these many days unto this day, but have kept the charge of the commandment of Jehovah your God. ^4And now Jehovah your God hath given rest unto your brethren, as he spake unto them: therefore now turn ye, and get you unto your tents, unto the land of your possession, which Moses the servant of Jehovah gave you beyond the Jordan. ^5Only take diligent heed to do the commandment and the law which Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded you, to love Jehovah your God, and to walk in all his ways, and to keep his commandments, and to cleave unto him, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul. ^6So Joshua blessed them, and sent them away; and they went unto their tents.

^7Now to the one half-tribe of Manasseh Moses had given inheritance in Bashan; but unto the other half gave Joshua among their brethren beyond the Jordan westward; moreover when Joshua sent them away unto their tents, he blessed them, ^8and spake unto them, saying, Return with much wealth unto your tents, and with very much cattle, with silver, and with gold, and with brass, and with iron, and with very much raiment: divide the spoil of your enemies with your brethren. ^9And the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh returned, and departed from the children of Israel out of Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan, to go unto the land of Gilead, to the land of their possession, whereof they were possessed, according to the commandment of Jehovah by Moses.

^10And when they came unto the region about the Jordan, that is in the land of Canaan, the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh built there an altar by the Jordan, a great altar to look upon. ^11And the children of Israel heard say, Behold, the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh have built an altar in the forefront of the land of Canaan, in the region about the Jordan, on the side that pertaineth to the children of Israel. ^12And when the children of Israel heard of it, the whole congregation of the children of Israel gathered themselves together at Shiloh, to go up against them to war.

^13And the children of Israel sent unto the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and to the half-tribe of Manasseh, into the land of Gilead, Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, ^14and with him ten princes, one prince of a fathers' house for each of the tribes of Israel; and they were every one of them head of their fathers' houses among the thousands of Israel. ^15And they came unto the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and to the half-tribe of Manasseh, unto the land of Gilead, and they spake with them, saying, ^16Thus saith the whole congregation of Jehovah, What trespass is this that ye have committed against the God of Israel, to turn away this day from following Jehovah, in that ye have builded you an altar, to rebel this day against Jehovah? ^17Is the iniquity of Peor too little for us, from which we have not cleansed ourselves unto this day, although there came a plague upon the congregation of Jehovah, ^18that ye must turn away this day from following Jehovah? and it will be, seeing ye rebel to-day against Jehovah, that to-morrow he will be wroth with the whole congregation of Israel. ^19Howbeit, if the land of your possession be unclean, then pass ye over unto the land of the possession of Jehovah, wherein Jehovah's tabernacle dwelleth, and take possession among us: but rebel not against Jehovah, nor rebel against us, in building you an altar besides the altar of Jehovah our God. ^20Did not Achan the son of Zerah commit a trespass in the devoted thing, and wrath fell upon all the congregation of Israel? and that man perished not alone in his iniquity.

^21Then the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh answered, and spake unto the heads of the thousands of Israel, ^22The Mighty One, God, Jehovah, the Mighty One, God, Jehovah, he knoweth; and Israel he shall know: if it be in rebellion, or if in trespass against Jehovah (save thou us not this day,) ^23that we have built us an altar to turn away from following Jehovah; or if to offer thereon burnt-offering or meal-offering, or if to offer sacrifices of peace-offerings thereon, let Jehovah himself require it; ^24and if we have not rather out of carefulness done this, and of purpose, saying, In time to come your children might speak unto our children, saying, What have ye to do with Jehovah, the God of Israel? ^25for Jehovah hath made the Jordan a border between us and you, ye children of Reuben and children of Gad; ye have no portion in Jehovah: so might your children make our children cease from fearing Jehovah. ^26Therefore we said, Let us now prepare to build us an altar, not for burnt-offering, nor for sacrifice: ^27but it shall be a witness between us and you, and between our generations after us, that we may do the service of Jehovah before him with our burnt-offerings, and with our sacrifices, and with our peace-offerings; that your children may not say to our children in time to come, Ye have no portion in Jehovah. ^28Therefore said we, It shall be, when they so say to us or to our generations in time to come, that we shall say, Behold the pattern of the altar of Jehovah, which our fathers made, not for burnt-offering, nor for sacrifice; but it is a witness between us and you. ^29Far be it from us that we should rebel against Jehovah, and turn away this day from following Jehovah, to build an altar for burnt-offering, for meal-offering, or for sacrifice, besides the altar of Jehovah our God that is before his tabernacle.

^30And when Phinehas the priest, and the princes of the congregation, even the heads of the thousands of Israel that were with him, heard the words that the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the children of Manasseh spake, it pleased them well. ^31And Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest said unto the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and to the children of Manasseh, This day we know that Jehovah is in the midst of us, because ye have not committed this trespass against Jehovah: now have ye delivered the children of Israel out of the hand of Jehovah. ^32And Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, and the princes, returned from the children of Reuben, and from the children of Gad, out of the land of Gilead, unto the land of Canaan, to the children of Israel, and brought them word again. ^33And the thing pleased the children of Israel; and the children of Israel blessed God, and spake no more of going up against them to war, to destroy the land wherein the children of Reuben and the children of Gad dwelt. ^34And the children of Reuben and the children of Gad called the altar Ed: For, said they, it is a witness between us that Jehovah is God.

Joshua 23

23

^1And it came to pass after many days, when Jehovah had given rest unto Israel from all their enemies round about, and Joshua was old and well stricken in years; ^2that Joshua called for all Israel, for their elders and for their heads, and for their judges and for their officers, and said unto them, I am old and well stricken in years: ^3and ye have seen all that Jehovah your God hath done unto all these nations because of you; for Jehovah your God, he it is that hath fought for you. ^4Behold, I have allotted unto you these nations that remain, to be an inheritance for your tribes, from the Jordan, with all the nations that I have cut off, even unto the great sea toward the going down of the sun. ^5And Jehovah your God, he will thrust them out from before you, and drive them from out of your sight; and ye shall possess their land, as Jehovah your God spake unto you. ^6Therefore be ye very courageous to keep and to do all that is written in the book of the law of Moses, that ye turn not aside therefrom to the right hand or to the left; ^7that ye come not among these nations, these that remain among you; neither make mention of the name of their gods, nor cause to swear by them, neither serve them, nor bow down yourselves unto them; ^8but cleave unto Jehovah your God, as ye have done unto this day. ^9For Jehovah hath driven out from before you great nations and strong: but as for you, no man hath stood before you unto this day. ^10One man of you shall chase a thousand; for Jehovah your God, he it is that fighteth for you, as he spake unto you. ^11Take good heed therefore unto yourselves, that ye love Jehovah your God. ^12Else if ye do at all go back, and cleave unto the remnant of these nations, even these that remain among you, and make marriages with them, and go in unto them, and they to you; ^13know for a certainty that Jehovah your God will no more drive these nations from out of your sight; but they shall be a snare and a trap unto you, and a scourge in your sides, and thorns in your eyes, until ye perish from off this good land which Jehovah your God hath given you.

^14And, behold, this day I am going the way of all the earth: and ye know in all your hearts and in all your souls, that not one thing hath failed of all the good things which Jehovah your God spake concerning you; all are come to pass unto you, not one thing hath failed thereof. ^15And it shall come to pass, that as all the good things are come upon you of which Jehovah your God spake unto you, so will Jehovah bring upon you all the evil things, until he have destroyed you from off this good land which Jehovah your God hath given you. ^16When ye transgress the covenant of Jehovah your God, which he commanded you, and go and serve other gods, and bow down yourselves to them; then will the anger of Jehovah be kindled against you, and ye shall perish quickly from off the good land which he hath given unto you.

Joshua 24

24

^1And Joshua gathered all the tribes of Israel to Shechem, and called for the elders of Israel, and for their heads, and for their judges, and for their officers; and they presented themselves before God. ^2And Joshua said unto all the people, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Your fathers dwelt of old time beyond the River, even Terah, the father of Abraham, and the father of Nahor: and they served other gods. ^3And I took your father Abraham from beyond the River, and led him throughout all the land of Canaan, and multiplied his seed, and gave him Isaac. ^4And I gave unto Isaac Jacob and Esau: and I gave unto Esau mount Seir, to possess it: and Jacob and his children went down into Egypt. ^5And I sent Moses and Aaron, and I plagued Egypt, according to that which I did in the midst thereof: and afterward I brought you out. ^6And I brought your fathers out of Egypt: and ye came unto the sea; and the Egyptians pursued after your fathers with chariots and with horsemen unto the Red Sea. ^7And when they cried out unto Jehovah, he put darkness between you and the Egyptians, and brought the sea upon them, and covered them; and your eyes saw what I did in Egypt: and ye dwelt in the wilderness many days. ^8And I brought you into the land of the Amorites, that dwelt beyond the Jordan: and they fought with you; and I gave them into your hand, and ye possessed their land; and I destroyed them from before you. ^9Then Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab, arose and fought against Israel: and he sent and called Balaam the son of Beor to curse you; ^10but I would not hearken unto Balaam; therefore he blessed you still: so I delivered you out of his hand. ^11And ye went over the Jordan, and came unto Jericho: and the men of Jericho fought against you, the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Girgashite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite; and I delivered them into your hand. ^12And I sent the hornet before you, which drove them out from before you, even the two kings of the Amorites; not with thy sword, nor with thy bow. ^13And I gave you a land whereon thou hadst not labored, and cities which ye built not, and ye dwell therein; of vineyards and oliveyards which ye planted not do ye eat.

^14Now therefore fear Jehovah, and serve him in sincerity and in truth; and put away the gods which your fathers served beyond the River, and in Egypt; and serve ye Jehovah. ^15And if it seem evil unto you to serve Jehovah, choose you this day whom ye will serve; whether the gods which your fathers served that were beyond the River, or the gods of the Amorites, in whose land ye dwell: but as for me and my house, we will serve Jehovah.

^16And the people answered and said, Far be it from us that we should forsake Jehovah, to serve other gods; ^17for Jehovah our God, he it is that brought us and our fathers up out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage, and that did those great signs in our sight, and preserved us in all the way wherein we went, and among all the peoples through the midst of whom we passed; ^18and Jehovah drove out from before us all the peoples, even the Amorites that dwelt in the land: therefore we also will serve Jehovah; for he is our God.

^19And Joshua said unto the people, Ye cannot serve Jehovah; for he is a holy God; he is a jealous God; he will not forgive your transgression nor your sins. ^20If ye forsake Jehovah, and serve foreign gods, then he will turn and do you evil, and consume you, after that he hath done you good. ^21And the people said unto Joshua, Nay; but we will serve Jehovah. ^22And Joshua said unto the people, Ye are witnesses against yourselves that ye have chosen you Jehovah, to serve him. And they said, We are witnesses. ^23Now therefore put away, said he, the foreign gods which are among you, and incline your heart unto Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^24And the people said unto Joshua, Jehovah our God will we serve, and unto his voice will we hearken. ^25So Joshua made a covenant with the people that day, and set them a statute and an ordinance in Shechem. ^26And Joshua wrote these words in the book of the law of God; and he took a great stone, and set it up there under the oak that was by the sanctuary of Jehovah. ^27And Joshua said unto all the people, Behold, this stone shall be a witness against us; for it hath heard all the words of Jehovah which he spake unto us: it shall be therefore a witness against you, lest ye deny your God. ^28So Joshua sent the people away, every man unto his inheritance.

^29And it came to pass after these things, that Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of Jehovah, died, being a hundred and ten years old. ^30And they buried him in the border of his inheritance in Timnathserah, which is in the hill-country of Ephraim, on the north of the mountain of Gaash. ^31And Israel served Jehovah all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders that outlived Joshua, and had known all the work of Jehovah, that he had wrought for Israel.

^32And the bones of Joseph, which the children of Israel brought up out of Egypt, buried they in Shechem, in the parcel of ground which Jacob bought of the sons of Hamor the father of Shechem for a hundred pieces of money: and they became the inheritance of the children of Joseph. ^33And Eleazar the son of Aaron died; and they buried him in the hill of Phinehas his son, which was given him in the hill-country of Ephraim.

Judges 3

3

^1Now these are the nations which Jehovah left, to prove Israel by them, even as many of Israel as had not known all the wars of Canaan; ^2only that the generations of the children of Israel might know, to teach them war, at the least such as beforetime knew nothing thereof: ^3namely, the five lords of the Philistines, and all the Canaanites, and the Sidonians, and the Hivites that dwelt in mount Lebanon, from mount Baal-hermon unto the entrance of Hamath. ^4And they were left, to prove Israel by them, to know whether they would hearken unto the commandments of Jehovah, which he commanded their fathers by Moses. ^5And the children of Israel dwelt among the Canaanites, the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites: ^6and they took their daughters to be their wives, and gave their own daughters to their sons and served their gods.

^7And the children of Israel did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and forgat Jehovah their God, and served the Baalim and the Asheroth. ^8Therefore the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of Cushan-rishathaim king of Mesopotamia: and the children of Israel served Cushan-rishathaim eight years. ^9And when the children of Israel cried unto Jehovah, Jehovah raised up a saviour to the children of Israel, who saved them, even Othniel the son of Kenaz, Caleb's younger brother. ^10And the Spirit of Jehovah came upon him, and he judged Israel; and he went out to war, and Jehovah delivered Cushan-rishathaim king of Mesopotamia into his hand: and his hand prevailed against Cushan-rishathaim. ^11And the land had rest forty years. And Othniel the son of Kenaz died.

^12And the children of Israel again did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah: and Jehovah strengthened Eglon the king of Moab against Israel, because they had done that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah. ^13And he gathered unto him the children of Ammon and Amalek; and he went and smote Israel, and they possessed the city of palm-trees. ^14And the children of Israel served Eglon the king of Moab eighteen years.

^15But when the children of Israel cried unto Jehovah, Jehovah raised them up a saviour, Ehud the son of Gera, the Benjamite, a man left-handed. And the children of Israel sent tribute by him unto Eglon the king of Moab. ^16And Ehud made him a sword which had two edges, a cubit in length; and he girded it under his raiment upon his right thigh. ^17And he offered the tribute unto Eglon king of Moab: now Eglon was a very fat man. ^18And when he had made an end of offering the tribute, he sent away the people that bare the tribute. ^19But he himself turned back from the quarries that were by Gilgal, and said, I have a secret errand unto thee, O king. And he said, Keep silence. And all that stood by him went out from him. ^20And Ehud came unto him; and he was sitting by himself alone in the cool upper room. And Ehud said, I have a message from God unto thee. And he arose out of his seat. ^21And Ehud put forth his left hand, and took the sword from his right thigh, and thrust it into his body: ^22and the haft also went in after the blade; and the fat closed upon the blade, for he drew not the sword out of his body; and it came out behind. ^23Then Ehud went forth into the porch, and shut the doors of the upper room upon him, and locked them.

^24Now when he was gone out, his servants came; and they saw, and, behold, the doors of the upper room were locked; and they said, Surely he is covering his feet in the upper chamber. ^25And they tarried till they were ashamed; and, behold, he opened not the doors of the upper room: therefore they took the key, and opened them, and, behold, their lord was fallen down dead on the earth.

^26And Ehud escaped while they tarried, and passed beyond the quarries, and escaped unto Seirah. ^27And it came to pass, when he was come, that he blew a trumpet in the hill-country of Ephraim; and the children of Israel went down with him from the hill-country, and he before them. ^28And he said unto them, Follow after me; for Jehovah hath delivered your enemies the Moabites into your hand. And they went down after him, and took the fords of the Jordan against the Moabites, and suffered not a man to pass over. ^29And they smote of Moab at that time about ten thousand men, every lusty man, and every man of valor; and there escaped not a man. ^30So Moab was subdued that day under the hand of Israel. And the land had rest fourscore years.

^31And after him was Shamgar the son of Anath, who smote of the Philistines six hundred men with an ox-goad: and he also saved Israel.

Judges 4

4

^1And the children of Israel again did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, when Ehud was dead. ^2And Jehovah sold them into the hand of Jabin king of Canaan, that reigned in Hazor; the captain of whose host was Sisera, who dwelt in Harosheth of the Gentiles. ^3And the children of Israel cried unto Jehovah: for he had nine hundred chariots of iron; and twenty years he mightily oppressed the children of Israel.

^4Now Deborah, a prophetess, the wife of Lappidoth, she judged Israel at that time. ^5And she dwelt under the palm-tree of Deborah between Ramah and Beth-el in the hill-country of Ephraim: and the children of Israel came up to her for judgment. ^6And she sent and called Barak the son of Abinoam out of Kedesh-naphtali, and said unto him, Hath not Jehovah, the God of Israel, commanded, saying, Go and draw unto mount Tabor, and take with thee ten thousand men of the children of Naphtali and of the children of Zebulun? ^7And I will draw unto thee, to the river Kishon, Sisera, the captain of Jabin's army, with his chariots and his multitude; and I will deliver him into thy hand. ^8And Barak said unto her, If thou wilt go with me, then I will go; but if thou wilt not go with me, I will not go. ^9And she said, I will surely go with thee: notwithstanding, the journey that thou takest shall not be for thine honor; for Jehovah will sell Sisera into the hand of a woman. And Deborah arose, and went with Barak to Kedesh. ^10And Barak called Zebulun and Naphtali together to Kedesh; and there went up ten thousand men at his feet: and Deborah went up with him.

^11Now Heber the Kenite had separated himself from the Kenites, even from the children of Hobab the brother-in-law of Moses, and had pitched his tent as far as the oak in Zaanannim, which is by Kedesh.

^12And they told Sisera that Barak the son of Abinoam was gone up to mount Tabor. ^13And Sisera gathered together all his chariots, even nine hundred chariots of iron, and all the people that were with him, from Harosheth of the Gentiles, unto the river Kishon. ^14And Deborah said unto Barak, Up; for this is the day in which Jehovah hath delivered Sisera into thy hand; is not Jehovah gone out before thee? So Barak went down from mount Tabor, and ten thousand men after him. ^15And Jehovah discomfited Sisera, and all his chariots, and all his host, with the edge of the sword before Barak; and Sisera alighted from his chariot, and fled away on his feet. ^16But Barak pursued after the chariots, and after the host, unto Harosheth of the Gentiles: and all the host of Sisera fell by the edge of the sword; there was not a man left.

^17Howbeit Sisera fled away on his feet to the tent of Jael the wife of Heber the Kenite; for there was peace between Jabin the king of Hazor and the house of Heber the Kenite. ^18And Jael went out to meet Sisera, and said unto him, Turn in, my lord, turn in to me; fear not. And he turned in unto her into the tent, and she covered him with a rug. ^19And he said unto her, Give me, I pray thee, a little water to drink; for I am thirsty. And she opened a bottle of milk, and gave him drink, and covered him. ^20And he said unto her, Stand in the door of the tent, and it shall be, when any man doth come and inquire of thee, and say, Is there any man here? that thou shalt say, No. ^21Then Jael Heber's wife took a tent-pin, and took a hammer in her hand, and went softly unto him, and smote the pin into his temples, and it pierced through into the ground; for he was in a deep sleep; so he swooned and died. ^22And, behold, as Barak pursued Sisera, Jael came out to meet him, and said unto him, Come, and I will show thee the man whom thou seekest. And he came unto her; and, behold, Sisera lay dead, and the tent-pin was in his temples.

^23So God subdued on that day Jabin the king of Canaan before the children of Israel. ^24And the hand of the children of Israel prevailed more and more against Jabin the king of Canaan, until they had destroyed Jabin king of Canaan.

Judges 6

6

^1And the children of Israel did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah: and Jehovah delivered them into the hand of Midian seven years. ^2And the hand of Midian prevailed against Israel; and because of Midian the children of Israel made them the dens which are in the mountains, and the caves, and the strongholds. ^3And so it was, when Israel had sown, that the Midianites came up, and the Amalekites, and the children of the east; they came up against them; ^4and they encamped against them, and destroyed the increase of the earth, till thou come unto Gaza, and left no sustenance in Israel, neither sheep, nor ox, nor ass. ^5For they came up with their cattle and their tents; they came in as locusts for multitude; both they and their camels were without number: and they came into the land to destroy it. ^6And Israel was brought very low because of Midian; and the children of Israel cried unto Jehovah.

^7And it came to pass, when the children of Israel cried unto Jehovah because of Midian, ^8that Jehovah sent a prophet unto the children of Israel: and he said unto them, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, I brought you up from Egypt, and brought you forth out of the house of bondage; ^9and I delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all that oppressed you, and drove them out from before you, and gave you their land; ^10and I said unto you, I am Jehovah your God; ye shall not fear the gods of the Amorites, in whose land ye dwell. But ye have not hearkened unto my voice.

^11And the angel of Jehovah came, and sat under the oak which was in Ophrah, that pertained unto Joash the Abiezrite: and his son Gideon was beating out wheat in the winepress, to hide it from the Midianites. ^12And the angel of Jehovah appeared unto him, and said unto him, Jehovah is with thee, thou mighty man of valor. ^13And Gideon said unto him, Oh, my lord, if Jehovah is with us, why then is all this befallen us? and where are all his wondrous works which our fathers told us of, saying, Did not Jehovah bring us up from Egypt? but now Jehovah hath cast us off, and delivered us into the hand of Midian. ^14And Jehovah looked upon him, and said, Go in this thy might, and save Israel from the hand of Midian: have not I sent thee? ^15And he said unto him, Oh, Lord, wherewith shall I save Israel? behold, my family is the poorest in Manasseh, and I am the least in my father's house. ^16And Jehovah said unto him, Surely I will be with thee, and thou shalt smite the Midianites as one man. ^17And he said unto him, If now I have found favor in thy sight, then show me a sign that it is thou that talkest with me. ^18Depart not hence, I pray thee, until I come unto thee, and bring forth my present, and lay it before thee. And he said, I will tarry until thou come again.

^19And Gideon went in, and made ready a kid, and unleavened cakes of an ephah of meal: the flesh he put in a basket, and he put the broth in a pot, and brought it out unto him under the oak, and presented it. ^20And the angel of God said unto him, Take the flesh and the unleavened cakes, and lay them upon this rock, and pour out the broth. And he did so. ^21Then the angel of Jehovah put forth the end of the staff that was in his hand, and touched the flesh and the unleavened cakes; and there went up fire out of the rock, and consumed the flesh and the unleavened cakes; and the angel of Jehovah departed out of his sight. ^22And Gideon saw that he was the angel of Jehovah; and Gideon said, Alas, O Lord Jehovah! forasmuch as I have seen the angel of Jehovah face to face. ^23And Jehovah said unto him, Peace be unto thee; fear not: thou shalt not die. ^24Then Gideon built an altar there unto Jehovah, and called it Jehovah-shalom: unto this day it is yet in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.

^25And it came to pass the same night, that Jehovah said unto him, Take thy father's bullock, even the second bullock seven years old, and throw down the altar of Baal that thy father hath, and cut down the Asherah that is by it; ^26and build an altar unto Jehovah thy God upon the top of this stronghold, in the orderly manner, and take the second bullock, and offer a burnt-offering with the wood of the Asherah which thou shalt cut down. ^27Then Gideon took ten men of his servants, and did as Jehovah had spoken unto him: and it came to pass, because he feared his father's household and the men of the city, so that he could not do it by day, that he did it by night.

^28And when the men of the city arose early in the morning, behold, the altar of Baal was broken down, and the Asherah was cut down that was by it, and the second bullock was offered upon the altar that was built. ^29And they said one to another, Who hath done this thing? And when they inquired and asked, they said, Gideon the son of Joash hath done this thing. ^30Then the men of the city said unto Joash, Bring out thy son, that he may die, because he hath broken down the altar of Baal, and because he hath cut down the Asherah that was by it. ^31And Joash said unto all that stood against him, Will ye contend for Baal? Or will ye save him? he that will contend for him, let him be put to death whilst it is yet morning: if he be a god, let him contend for himself, because one hath broken down his altar. ^32Therefore on that day he called him Jerubbaal, saying, Let Baal contend against him, because he hath broken down his altar.

^33Then all the Midianites and the Amalekites and the children of the east assembled themselves together; and they passed over, and encamped in the valley of Jezreel. ^34But the Spirit of Jehovah came upon Gideon; and he blew a trumpet; and Abiezer was gathered together after him. ^35And he sent messengers throughout all Manasseh; and they also were gathered together after him: and he sent messengers unto Asher, and unto Zebulun, and unto Naphtali; and they came up to meet them.

^36And Gideon said unto God, If thou wilt save Israel by my hand, as thou hast spoken, ^37behold, I will put a fleece of wool on the threshing-floor; if there be dew on the fleece only, and it be dry upon all the ground, then shall I know that thou wilt save Israel by my hand, as thou hast spoken. ^38And it was so; for he rose up early on the morrow, and pressed the fleece together, and wrung the dew out of the fleece, a bowlful of water. ^39And Gideon said unto God, Let not thine anger be kindled against me, and I will speak but this once: let me make trial, I pray thee, but this once with the fleece; let it now be dry only upon the fleece, and upon all the ground let there be dew. ^40And God did so that night: for it was dry upon the fleece only, and there was dew on all the ground.

Judges 7

7

^1Then Jerubbaal, who is Gideon, and all the people that were with him, rose up early, and encamped beside the spring of Harod: and the camp of Midian was on the north side of them, by the hill of Moreh, in the valley.

^2And Jehovah said unto Gideon, The people that are with thee are too many for me to give the Midianites into their hand, lest Israel vaunt themselves against me, saying, Mine own hand hath saved me. ^3Now therefore proclaim in the ears of the people, saying, Whosoever is fearful and trembling, let him return and depart from mount Gilead. And there returned of the people twenty and two thousand; and there remained ten thousand.

^4And Jehovah said unto Gideon, The people are yet too many; bring them down unto the water, and I will try them for thee there: and it shall be, that of whom I say unto thee, This shall go with thee, the same shall go with thee; and of whomsoever I say unto thee, This shall not go with thee, the same shall not go. ^5So he brought down the people unto the water: and Jehovah said unto Gideon, Every one that lappeth of the water with his tongue, as a dog lappeth, him shalt thou set by himself; likewise every one that boweth down upon his knees to drink. ^6And the number of them that lapped, putting their hand to their mouth, was three hundred men: but all the rest of the people bowed down upon their knees to drink water. ^7And Jehovah said unto Gideon, By the three hundred men that lapped will I save you, and deliver the Midianites into thy hand; and let all the people go every man unto his place. ^8So the people took victuals in their hand, and their trumpets; and he sent all the men of Israel every man unto his tent, but retained the three hundred men: and the camp of Midian was beneath him in the valley.

^9And it came to pass the same night, that Jehovah said unto him, Arise, get thee down into the camp; for I have delivered it into thy hand. ^10But if thou fear to go down, go thou with Purah thy servant down to the camp: ^11and thou shalt hear what they say; and afterward shall thy hands be strengthened to go down into the camp. Then went he down with Purah his servant unto the outermost part of the armed men that were in the camp. ^12And the Midianites and the Amalekites and all the children of the east lay along in the valley like locusts for multitude; and their camels were without number, as the sand which is upon the sea-shore for multitude. ^13And when Gideon was come, behold, there was a man telling a dream unto his fellow; and he said, Behold, I dreamed a dream; and, lo, a cake of barley bread tumbled into the camp of Midian, and came unto the tent, and smote it so that it fell, and turned it upside down, so that the tent lay flat. ^14And his fellow answered and said, This is nothing else save the sword of Gideon the son of Joash, a man of Israel: into his hand God hath delivered Midian, and all the host.

^15And it was so, when Gideon heard the telling of the dream, and the interpretation thereof, that he worshipped; and he returned into the camp of Israel, and said, Arise; for Jehovah hath delivered into your hand the host of Midian. ^16And he divided the three hundred men into three companies, and he put into the hands of all of them trumpets, and empty pitchers, with torches within the pitchers. ^17And he said unto them, Look on me, and do likewise: and, behold, when I come to the outermost part of the camp, it shall be that, as I do, so shall ye do. ^18When I blow the trumpet, I and all that are with me, then blow ye the trumpets also on every side of all the camp, and say, For Jehovah and for Gideon.

^19So Gideon, and the hundred men that were with him, came unto the outermost part of the camp in the beginning of the middle watch, when they had but newly set the watch: and they blew the trumpets, and brake in pieces the pitchers that were in their hands. ^20And the three companies blew the trumpets, and brake the pitchers, and held the torches in their left hands, and the trumpets in their right hands wherewith to blow; and they cried, The sword of Jehovah and of Gideon. ^21And they stood every man in his place round about the camp; and all the host ran; and they shouted, and put them to flight. ^22And they blew the three hundred trumpets, and Jehovah set every man's sword against his fellow, and against all the host; and the host fled as far as Beth-shittah toward Zererah, as far as the border of Abel-meholah, by Tabbath. ^23And the men of Israel were gathered together out of Naphtali, and out of Asher, and out of all Manasseh, and pursued after Midian.

^24And Gideon sent messengers throughout all the hill-country of Ephraim, saying, Come down against Midian, and take before them the waters, as far as Beth-barah, even the Jordan. So all the men of Ephraim were gathered together, and took the waters as far as Beth-barah, even the Jordan. ^25And they took the two princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb; and they slew Oreb at the rock of Oreb, and Zeeb they slew at the winepress of Zeeb, and pursued Midian: and they brought the heads of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon beyond the Jordan.

Judges 8

8

^1And the men of Ephraim said unto him, Why hast thou served us thus, that thou calledst us not, when thou wentest to fight with Midian? And they did chide with him sharply. ^2And he said unto them, What have I now done in comparison with you? Is not the gleaning of the grapes of Ephraim better than the vintage of Abiezer? ^3God hath delivered into your hand the princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb: and what was I able to do in comparison with you? Then their anger was abated toward him, when he had said that.

^4And Gideon came to the Jordan, and passed over, he, and the three hundred men that were with him, faint, yet pursuing. ^5And he said unto the men of Succoth, Give, I pray you, loaves of bread unto the people that follow me; for they are faint, and I am pursuing after Zebah and Zalmunna, the kings of Midian. ^6And the princes of Succoth said, Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna now in thy hand, that we should give bread unto thine army? ^7And Gideon said, Therefore when Jehovah hath delivered Zebah and Zalmunna into my hand, then I will tear your flesh with the thorns of the wilderness and with briers. ^8And he went up thence to Penuel, and spake unto them in like manner; and the men of Penuel answered him as the men of Succoth had answered. ^9And he spake also unto the men of Penuel, saying, When I come again in peace, I will break down this tower.

^10Now Zebah and Zalmunna were in Karkor, and their hosts with them, about fifteen thousand men, all that were left of all the host of the children of the east; for there fell a hundred and twenty thousand men that drew sword. ^11And Gideon went up by the way of them that dwelt in tents on the east of Nobah and Jogbehah, and smote the host; for the host was secure. ^12And Zebah and Zalmunna fled; and he pursued after them; and he took the two kings of Midian, Zebah and Zalmunna, and discomfited all the host.

^13And Gideon the son of Joash returned from the battle from the ascent of Heres. ^14And he caught a young man of the men of Succoth, and inquired of him: and he described for him the princes of Succoth, and the elders thereof, seventy and seven men. ^15And he came unto the men of Succoth, and said, Behold Zebah and Zalmunna, concerning whom ye did taunt me, saying, Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna now in thy hand, that we should give bread unto thy men that are weary? ^16And he took the elders of the city, and thorns of the wilderness and briers, and with them he taught the men of Succoth. ^17And he brake down the tower of Penuel, and slew the men of the city.

^18Then said he unto Zebah and Zalmunna, What manner of men were they whom ye slew at Tabor? And they answered, As thou art, so were they; each one resembled the children of a king. ^19And he said, They were my brethren, the sons of my mother: as Jehovah liveth, if ye had saved them alive, I would not slay you. ^20And he said unto Jether his first-born, Up, and slay them. But the youth drew not his sword; for he feared, because he was yet a youth. ^21Then Zebah and Zalmunna said, Rise thou, and fall upon us; for as the man is, so is his strength. And Gideon arose, and slew Zebah and Zalmunna, and took the crescents that were on their camels' necks.

^22Then the men of Israel said unto Gideon, Rule thou over us, both thou, and thy son, and thy son's son also; for thou hast saved us out of the hand of Midian. ^23And Gideon said unto them, I will not rule over you, neither shall my son rule over you: Jehovah shall rule over you. ^24And Gideon said unto them, I would make a request of you, that ye would give me every man the ear-rings of his spoil. (For they had golden ear-rings, because they were Ishmaelites.) ^25And they answered, We will willingly give them. And they spread a garment, and did cast therein every man the ear-rings of his spoil. ^26And the weight of the golden ear-rings that he requested was a thousand and seven hundred shekels of gold, besides the crescents, and the pendants, and the purple raiment that was on the kings of Midian, and besides the chains that were about their camels' necks. ^27And Gideon made an ephod thereof, and put it in his city, even in Ophrah: and all Israel played the harlot after it there; and it became a snare unto Gideon, and to his house. ^28So Midian was subdued before the children of Israel, and they lifted up their heads no more. And the land had rest forty years in the days of Gideon.

^29And Jerubbaal the son of Joash went and dwelt in his own house. ^30And Gideon had threescore and ten sons of his body begotten; for he had many wives. ^31And his concubine that was in Shechem, she also bare him a son, and he called his name Abimelech. ^32And Gideon the son of Joash died in a good old age, and was buried in the sepulchre of Joash his father, in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.

^33And it came to pass, as soon as Gideon was dead, that the children of Israel turned again, and played the harlot after the Baalim, and made Baal-berith their god. ^34And the children of Israel remembered not Jehovah their God, who had delivered them out of the hand of all their enemies on every side; ^35neither showed they kindness to the house of Jerubbaal, who is Gideon, according to all the goodness which he had showed unto Israel.

Judges 9

9

^1And Abimelech the son of Jerubbaal went to Shechem unto his mother's brethren, and spake with them, and with all the family of the house of his mother's father, saying, ^2Speak, I pray you, in the ears of all the men of Shechem, Whether is better for you, that all the sons of Jerubbaal, who are threescore and ten persons, rule over you, or that one rule over you? remember also that I am your bone and your flesh. ^3And his mother's brethren spake of him in the ears of all the men of Shechem all these words: and their hearts inclined to follow Abimelech; for they said, He is our brother. ^4And they gave him threescore and ten pieces of silver out of the house of Baal-berith, wherewith Abimelech hired vain and light fellows, who followed him. ^5And he went unto his father's house at Ophrah, and slew his brethren the sons of Jerubbaal, being threescore and ten persons, upon one stone: but Jotham the youngest son of Jerubbaal was left; for he hid himself. ^6And all the men of Shechem assembled themselves together, and all the house of Millo, and went and made Abimelech king, by the oak of the pillar that was in Shechem.

^7And when they told it to Jotham, he went and stood on the top of mount Gerizim, and lifted up his voice, and cried, and said unto them, Hearken unto me, ye men of Shechem, that God may hearken unto you. ^8The trees went forth on a time to anoint a king over them; and they said unto the olive-tree, Reign thou over us. ^9But the olive-tree said unto them, Should I leave my fatness, wherewith by me they honor God and man, and go to wave to and fro over the trees? ^10And the trees said to the fig-tree, Come thou, and reign over us. ^11But the fig-tree said unto them, Should I leave my sweetness, and my good fruit, and go to wave to and fro over the trees? ^12And the trees said unto the vine, Come thou, and reign over us. ^13And the vine said unto them, Should I leave my new wine, which cheereth God and man, and go to wave to and fro over the trees? ^14Then said all the trees unto the bramble, Come thou, and reign over us. ^15And the bramble said unto the trees, If in truth ye anoint me king over you, then come and take refuge in my shade; and if not, let fire come out of the bramble, and devour the cedars of Lebanon. ^16Now therefore, if ye have dealt truly and uprightly, in that ye have made Abimelech king, and if ye have dealt well with Jerubbaal and his house, and have done unto him according to the deserving of his hands ^17(for my father fought for you, and adventured his life, and delivered you out of the hand of Midian: ^18and ye are risen up against my father's house this day, and have slain his sons, threescore and ten persons, upon one stone, and have made Abimelech, the son of his maid-servant, king over the men of Shechem, because he is your brother); ^19if ye then have dealt truly and uprightly with Jerubbaal and with his house this day, then rejoice ye in Abimelech, and let him also rejoice in you: ^20but if not, let fire come out from Abimelech, and devour the men of Shechem, and the house of Millo; and let fire come out from the men of Shechem, and from the house of Millo, and devour Abimelech. ^21And Jotham ran away, and fled, and went to Beer, and dwelt there, for fear of Abimelech his brother.

^22And Abimelech was prince over Israel three years. ^23And God sent an evil spirit between Abimelech and the men of Shechem; and the men of Shechem dealt treacherously with Abimelech: ^24that the violence done to the threescore and ten sons of Jerubbaal might come, and that their blood might be laid upon Abimelech their brother, who slew them, and upon the men of Shechem, who strengthened his hands to slay his brethren. ^25And the men of Shechem set liers-in-wait for him on the tops of the mountains, and they robbed all that came along that way by them: and it was told Abimelech.

^26And Gaal the son of Ebed came with his brethren, and went over to Shechem; and the men of Shechem put their trust in him. ^27And they went out into the field, and gathered their vineyards, and trod the grapes, and held festival, and went into the house of their god, and did eat and drink, and cursed Abimelech. ^28And Gaal the son of Ebed said, Who is Abimelech, and who is Shechem, that we should serve him? is not he the son of Jerubbaal? and Zebul his officer? serve ye the men of Hamor the father of Shechem: but why should we serve him? ^29And would that this people were under my hand! then would I remove Abimelech. And he said to Abimelech, Increase thine army, and come out.

^30And when Zebul the ruler of the city heard the words of Gaal the son of Ebed, his anger was kindled. ^31And he sent messengers unto Abimelech craftily, saying, Behold, Gaal the son of Ebed and his brethren are come to Shechem; and, behold, they constrain the city to take part against thee. ^32Now therefore, up by night, thou and the people that are with thee, and lie in wait in the field: ^33and it shall be, that in the morning, as soon as the sun is up, thou shalt rise early, and rush upon the city; and, behold, when he and the people that are with him come out against thee, then mayest thou do to them as thou shalt find occasion.

^34And Abimelech rose up, and all the people that were with him, by night, and they laid wait against Shechem in four companies. ^35And Gaal the son of Ebed went out, and stood in the entrance of the gate of the city: and Abimelech rose up, and the people that were with him, from the ambushment. ^36And when Gaal saw the people, he said to Zebul, Behold, there come people down from the tops of the mountains. And Zebul said unto him, Thou seest the shadow of the mountains as if they were men. ^37And Gaal spake again and said, See, there come people down by the middle of the land, and one company cometh by the way of the oak of Meonenim. ^38Then said Zebul unto him, Where is now thy mouth, that thou saidst, Who is Abimelech, that we should serve him? is not this the people that thou hast despised? go out now, I pray, and fight with them. ^39And Gaal went out before the men of Shechem, and fought with Abimelech. ^40And Abimelech chased him, and he fled before him, and there fell many wounded, even unto the entrance of the gate.

^41And Abimelech dwelt at Arumah: and Zebul drove out Gaal and his brethren, that they should not dwell in Shechem. ^42And it came to pass on the morrow, that the people went out into the field; and they told Abimelech. ^43And he took the people, and divided them into three companies, and laid wait in the field; and he looked, and, behold, the people came forth out of the city; And he rose up against them, and smote them. ^44And Abimelech, and the companies that were with him, rushed forward, and stood in the entrance of the gate of the city: and the two companies rushed upon all that were in the field, and smote them. ^45And Abimelech fought against the city all that day; and he took the city, and slew the people that were therein: and he beat down the city, and sowed it with salt.

^46And when all the men of the tower of Shechem heard thereof, they entered into the stronghold of the house of Elberith. ^47And it was told Abimelech that all the men of the tower of Shechem were gathered together. ^48And Abimelech gat him up to mount Zalmon, he and all the people that were with him; and Abimelech took an axe in his hand, and cut down a bough from the trees, and took it up, and laid it on his shoulder: and he said unto the people that were with him, What ye have seen me do, make haste, and do as I have done. ^49And all the people likewise cut down every man his bough, and followed Abimelech, and put them to the stronghold, and set the stronghold on fire upon them; so that all the men of the tower of Shechem died also, about a thousand men and women.

^50Then went Abimelech to Thebez, and encamped against Thebez, and took it. ^51But there was a strong tower within the city, and thither fled all the men and women, and all they of the city, and shut themselves in, and gat them up to the roof of the tower. ^52And Abimelech came unto the tower, and fought against it, and drew near unto the door of the tower to burn it with fire. ^53And a certain woman cast an upper millstone upon Abimelech's head, and brake his skull. ^54Then he called hastily unto the young man his armorbearer, and said unto him, Draw thy sword, and kill me, that men say not of me, A woman slew him. And his young man thrust him through, and he died. ^55And when the men of Israel saw that Abimelech was dead, they departed every man unto his place. ^56Thus God requited the wickedness of Abimelech, which he did unto his father, in slaying his seventy brethren; ^57and all the wickedness of the men of Shechem did God requite upon their heads: and upon them came the curse of Jotham the son of Jerubbaal.

Judges 10

10

^1And after Abimelech there arose to save Israel Tola the son of Puah, the son of Dodo, a man of Issachar; and he dwelt in Shamir in the hill-country of Ephraim. ^2And he judged Israel twenty and three years, and died, and was buried in Shamir.

^3And after him arose Jair, the Gileadite; and he judged Israel twenty and two years. ^4And he had thirty sons that rode on thirty ass colts, and they had thirty cities, which are called Havvoth-jair unto this day, which are in the land of Gilead. ^5And Jair died, and was buried in Kamon.

^6And the children of Israel again did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and served the Baalim, and the Ashtaroth, and the gods of Syria, and the gods of Sidon, and the gods of Moab, and the gods of the children of Ammon, and the gods of the Philistines; and they forsook Jehovah, and served him not. ^7And the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of the Philistines, and into the hand of the children of Ammon. ^8And they vexed and oppressed the children of Israel that year: eighteen years oppressed they all the children of Israel that were beyond the Jordan in the land of the Amorites, which is in Gilead. ^9And the children of Ammon passed over the Jordan to fight also against Judah, and against Benjamin, and against the house of Ephraim; so that Israel was sore distressed.

^10And the children of Israel cried unto Jehovah, saying, We have sinned against thee, even because we have forsaken our God, and have served the Baalim. ^11And Jehovah said unto the children of Israel, Did not I save you from the Egyptians, and from the Amorites, from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines? ^12The Sidonians also, and the Amalekites, and the Maonites, did oppress you; and ye cried unto me, and I saved you out of their hand. ^13Yet ye have forsaken me, and served other gods: wherefore I will save you no more. ^14Go and cry unto the gods which ye have chosen; let them save you in the time of your distress. ^15And the children of Israel said unto Jehovah, We have sinned: do thou unto us whatsoever seemeth good unto thee; only deliver us, we pray thee, this day. ^16And they put away the foreign gods from among them, and served Jehovah; and his soul was grieved for the misery of Israel.

^17Then the children of Ammon were gathered together, and encamped in Gilead. And the children of Israel assembled themselves together, and encamped in Mizpah. ^18And the people, the princes of Gilead, said one to another, What man is he that will begin to fight against the children of Ammon? he shall be head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.

Judges 11

11

^1Now Jephthah the Gileadite was a mighty man of valor, and he was the son of a harlot: and Gilead begat Jephthah. ^2And Gilead's wife bare him sons; and when his wife's sons grew up, they drove out Jephthah, and said unto him, Thou shalt not inherit in our father's house; for thou art the son of another woman. ^3Then Jephthah fled from his brethren, and dwelt in the land of Tob: and there were gathered vain fellows to Jephthah, and they went out with him.

^4And it came to pass after a while, that the children of Ammon made war against Israel. ^5And it was so, that, when the children of Ammon made war against Israel, the elders of Gilead went to fetch Jephthah out of the land of Tob; ^6and they said unto Jephthah, Come and be our chief, that we may fight with the children of Ammon. ^7And Jephthah said unto the elders of Gilead, Did not ye hate me, and drive me out of my father's house? and why are ye come unto me now when ye are in distress? ^8And the elders of Gilead said unto Jephthah, Therefore are we turned again to thee now, that thou mayest go with us, and fight with the children of Ammon; and thou shalt be our head over all the inhabitants of Gilead. ^9And Jephthah said unto the elders of Gilead, If ye bring me home again to fight with the children of Ammon, and Jehovah deliver them before me, shall I be your head? ^10And the elders of Gilead said unto Jephthah, Jehovah shall be witness between us; surely according to thy word so will we do. ^11Then Jephthah went with the elders of Gilead, and the people made him head and chief over them: and Jephthah spake all his words before Jehovah in Mizpah.

^12And Jephthah sent messengers unto the king of the children of Ammon, saying, What hast thou to do with me, that thou art come unto me to fight against my land? ^13And the king of the children of Ammon answered unto the messengers of Jephthah, Because Israel took away my land, when he came up out of Egypt, from the Arnon even unto the Jabbok, and unto the Jordan: now therefore restore those lands again peaceably. ^14And Jephthah sent messengers again unto the king of the children of Ammon; ^15and he said unto him, Thus saith Jephthah: Israel took not away the land of Moab, nor the land of the children of Ammon, ^16but when they came up from Egypt, and Israel went through the wilderness unto the Red Sea, and came to Kadesh; ^17then Israel sent messengers unto the king of Edom, saying, Let me, I pray thee, pass through thy land; but the king of Edom hearkened not. And in like manner he sent unto the king of Moab; but he would not: and Israel abode in Kadesh. ^18Then they went through the wilderness, and went around the land of Edom, and the land of Moab, and came by the east side of the land of Moab, and they encamped on the other side of the Arnon; but they came not within the border of Moab, for the Arnon was the border of Moab. ^19And Israel sent messengers unto Sihon king of the Amorites, the king of Heshbon; and Israel said unto him, Let us pass, we pray thee, through thy land unto my place. ^20But Sihon trusted not Israel to pass through his border; but Sihon gathered all his people together, and encamped in Jahaz, and fought against Israel. ^21And Jehovah, the God of Israel, delivered Sihon and all his people into the hand of Israel, and they smote them: so Israel possessed all the land of the Amorites, the inhabitants of that country. ^22And they possessed all the border of the Amorites, from the Arnon even unto the Jabbok, and from the wilderness even unto the Jordan. ^23So now Jehovah, the God of Israel, hath dispossessed the Amorites from before his people Israel, and shouldest thou possess them? ^24Wilt not thou possess that which Chemosh thy god giveth thee to possess? So whomsoever Jehovah our God hath dispossessed from before us, them will we possess. ^25And now art thou anything better than Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab? did he ever strive against Israel, or did he ever fight against them? ^26While Israel dwelt in Heshbon and its towns, and in Aroer and its towns, and in all the cities that are along by the side of the Arnon, three hundred years; wherefore did ye not recover them within that time? ^27I therefore have not sinned against thee, but thou doest me wrong to war against me: Jehovah, the Judge, be judge this day between the children of Israel and the children of Ammon. ^28Howbeit the king of the children of Ammon hearkened not unto the words of Jephthah which he sent him.

^29Then the Spirit of Jehovah came upon Jephthah, and he passed over Gilead and Manasseh, and passed over Mizpeh of Gilead, and from Mizpeh of Gilead he passed over unto the children of Ammon. ^30And Jephthah vowed a vow unto Jehovah, and said, If thou wilt indeed deliver the children of Ammon into my hand, ^31then it shall be, that whatsoever cometh forth from the doors of my house to meet me, when I return in peace from the children of Ammon, it shall be Jehovah's, and I will offer it up for a burnt-offering. ^32So Jephthah passed over unto the children of Ammon to fight against them; and Jehovah delivered them into his hand. ^33And he smote them from Aroer until thou come to Minnith, even twenty cities, and unto Abelcheramim, with a very great slaughter. So the children of Ammon were subdued before the children of Israel.

^34And Jephthah came to Mizpah unto his house; and, behold, his daughter came out to meet him with timbrels and with dances: and she was his only child; besides her he had neither son nor daughter. ^35And it came to pass, when he saw her, that he rent his clothes, and said, Alas, my daughter! thou hast brought me very low, and thou art one of them that trouble me; for I have opened my mouth unto Jehovah, and I cannot go back. ^36And she said unto him, My father, thou hast opened thy mouth unto Jehovah; do unto me according to that which hath proceeded out of thy mouth, forasmuch as Jehovah hath taken vengeance for thee on thine enemies, even on the children of Ammon. ^37And she said unto her father, Let this thing be done for me: let me alone two months, that I may depart and go down upon the mountains, and bewail my virginity, I and my companions. ^38And he said, Go. And he sent her away for two months: and she departed, she and her companions, and bewailed her virginity upon the mountains. ^39And it came to pass at the end of two months, that she returned unto her father, who did with her according to his vow which he had vowed: and she knew not man. And it was a custom in Israel, ^40that the daughters of Israel went yearly to celebrate the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite four days in a year.

Judges 12

12

^1And the men of Ephraim were gathered together, and passed northward; and they said unto Jephthah, Wherefore passedst thou over to fight against the children of Ammon, and didst not call us to go with thee? we will burn thy house upon thee with fire. ^2And Jephthah said unto them, I and my people were at great strife with the children of Ammon; and when I called you, ye saved me not out of their hand. ^3And when I saw that ye saved me not, I put my life in my hand, and passed over against the children of Ammon, and Jehovah delivered them into my hand: wherefore then are ye come up unto me this day, to fight against me? ^4Then Jephthah gathered together all the men of Gilead, and fought with Ephraim; and the men of Gilead smote Ephraim, because they said, Ye are fugitives of Ephraim, ye Gileadites, in the midst of Ephraim, and in the midst of Manasseh. ^5And the Gileadites took the fords of the Jordan against the Ephraimites. And it was so, that, when any of the fugitives of Ephraim said, Let me go over, the men of Gilead said unto him, Art thou an Ephraimite? If he said, Nay; ^6then said they unto him, Say now Shibboleth; and he said Sibboleth; for he could not frame to pronounce it right: then they laid hold on him, and slew him at the fords of the Jordan. And there fell at that time of Ephraim forty and two thousand.

^7And Jephthah judged Israel six years. Then died Jephthah the Gileadite, and was buried in one of the cities of Gilead.

^8And after him Ibzan of Beth-lehem judged Israel. ^9And he had thirty sons; and thirty daughters he sent abroad, and thirty daughters he brought in from abroad for his sons. And he judged Israel seven years. ^10And Ibzan died, and was buried at Beth-lehem. ^11And after him Elon the Zebulunite judged Israel; and he judged Israel ten years. ^12And Elon the Zebulunite died, and was buried in Aijalon in the land of Zebulun.

^13And after him Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite judged Israel. ^14And he had forty sons and thirty sons' sons, that rode on threescore and ten ass colts: and he judged Israel eight years. ^15And Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite died, and was buried in Pirathon in the land of Ephraim, in the hill-country of the Amalekites.

Judges 13

13

^1And the children of Israel again did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah; and Jehovah delivered them into the hand of the Philistines forty years.

^2And there was a certain man of Zorah, of the family of the Danites, whose name was Manoah; and his wife was barren, and bare not. ^3And the angel of Jehovah appeared unto the woman, and said unto her, Behold now, thou art barren, and bearest not; but thou shalt conceive, and bear a son. ^4Now therefore beware, I pray thee, and drink no wine nor strong drink, and eat not any unclean thing: ^5for, lo, thou shalt conceive, and bear a son; and no razor shall come upon his head; for the child shall be a Nazirite unto God from the womb: and he shall begin to save Israel out of the hand of the Philistines. ^6Then the woman came and told her husband, saying, A man of God came unto me, and his countenance was like the countenance of the angel of God, very terrible; and I asked him not whence he was, neither told he me his name: ^7but he said unto me, Behold, thou shalt conceive, and bear a son; and now drink no wine nor strong drink, and eat not any unclean thing; for the child shall be a Nazirite unto God from the womb to the day of his death.

^8Then Manoah entreated Jehovah, and said, Oh, Lord, I pray thee, let the man of God whom thou didst send come again unto us, and teach us what we shall do unto the child that shall be born. ^9And God hearkened to the voice of Manoah; and the angel of God came again unto the woman as she sat in the field: but Manoah her husband was not with her. ^10And the woman made haste, and ran, and told her husband, and said unto him, Behold, the man hath appeared unto me, that came unto me the other day. ^11And Manoah arose, and went after his wife, and came to the man, and said unto him, Art thou the man that spakest unto the woman? And he said, I am. ^12And Manoah said, Now let thy words come to pass: what shall be the ordering of the child, and how shall we do unto him? ^13And the angel of Jehovah said unto Manoah, Of all that I said unto the woman let her beware. ^14She may not eat of anything that cometh of the vine, neither let her drink wine or strong drink, nor eat any unclean thing; all that I commanded her let her observe.

^15And Manoah said unto the angel of Jehovah, I pray thee, let us detain thee, that we may make ready a kid for thee. ^16And the angel of Jehovah said unto Manoah, Though thou detain me, I will not eat of thy bread; and if thou wilt make ready a burnt-offering, thou must offer it unto Jehovah. For Manoah knew not that he was the angel of Jehovah. ^17And Manoah said unto the angel of Jehovah, What is thy name, that, when thy words come to pass, we may do thee honor? ^18And the angel of Jehovah said unto him, Wherefore askest thou after my name, seeing it is wonderful? ^19So Manoah took the kid with the meal-offering, and offered it upon the rock unto Jehovah: and the angel did wondrously, and Manoah and his wife looked on. ^20For it came to pass, when the flame went up toward heaven from off the altar, that the angel of Jehovah ascended in the flame of the altar: and Manoah and his wife looked on; and they fell on their faces to the ground.

^21But the angel of Jehovah did no more appear to Manoah or to his wife. Then Manoah knew that he was the angel of Jehovah. ^22And Manoah said unto his wife, We shall surely die, because we have seen God. ^23But his wife said unto him, If Jehovah were pleased to kill us, he would not have received a burnt-offering and a meal-offering at our hand, neither would he have showed us all these things, nor would at this time have told such things as these. ^24And the woman bare a son, and called his name Samson: and the child grew, and Jehovah blessed him. ^25And the Spirit of Jehovah began to move him in Mahaneh-dan, between Zorah and Eshtaol.

Judges 14

14

^1And Samson went down to Timnah, and saw a woman in Timnah of the daughters of the Philistines. ^2And he came up, and told his father and his mother, and said, I have seen a woman in Timnah of the daughters of the Philistines: now therefore get her for me to wife. ^3Then his father and his mother said unto him, Is there never a woman among the daughters of thy brethren, or among all my people, that thou goest to take a wife of the uncircumcised Philistines? And Samson said unto his father, Get her for me; for she pleaseth me well. ^4But his father and his mother knew not that it was of Jehovah; for he sought an occasion against the Philistines. Now at that time the Philistines had rule over Israel.

^5Then went Samson down, and his father and his mother, to Timnah, and came to the vineyards of Timnah: and, behold, a young lion roared against him. ^6And the Spirit of Jehovah came mightily upon him, and he rent him as he would have rent a kid; and he had nothing in his hand: but he told not his father or his mother what he had done. ^7And he went down, and talked with the woman, and she pleased Samson well. ^8And after a while he returned to take her; and he turned aside to see the carcass of the lion: and, behold, there was a swarm of bees in the body of the lion, and honey. ^9And he took it into his hands, and went on, eating as he went; and he came to his father and mother, and gave unto them, and they did eat: but he told them not that he had taken the honey out of the body of the lion.

^10And his father went down unto the woman: and Samson made there a feast; for so used the young men to do. ^11And it came to pass, when they saw him, that they brought thirty companions to be with him. ^12And Samson said unto them, Let me now put forth a riddle unto you: if ye can declare it unto me within the seven days of the feast, and find it out, then I will give you thirty linen garments and thirty changes of raiment; ^13but if ye cannot declare it unto me, then shall ye give me thirty linen garments and thirty changes of raiment. And they said unto him, Put forth thy riddle, that we may hear it. ^14And he said unto them,

Out of the eater came forth food,

And out of the strong came forth sweetness.

And they could not in three days declare the riddle. ^15And it came to pass on the seventh day, that they said unto Samson's wife, Entice thy husband, that he may declare unto us the riddle, lest we burn thee and thy father's house with fire: have ye called us to impoverish us? is it not so? ^16And Samson's wife wept before him, and said, Thou dost but hate me, and lovest me not: thou hast put forth a riddle unto the children of my people, and hast not told it me. And he said unto her, Behold, I have not told it my father nor my mother, and shall I tell thee? ^17And she wept before him the seven days, while their feast lasted: and it came to pass on the seventh day, that he told her, because she pressed him sore; and she told the riddle to the children of her people. ^18And the men of the city said unto him on the seventh day before the sun went down, What is sweeter than honey? and what is stronger than a lion? And he said unto them,

If ye had not plowed with my heifer,

Ye had not found out my riddle.

^19And the Spirit of Jehovah came mightily upon him, and he went down to Ashkelon, and smote thirty men of them, and took their spoil, and gave the changes of raiment unto them that declared the riddle. And his anger was kindled, and he went up to his father's house. ^20But Samson's wife was given to his companion, whom he had used as his friend.

Judges 15

15

^1But it came to pass after a while, in the time of wheat harvest, that Samson visited his wife with a kid; and he said, I will go in to my wife into the chamber. But her father would not suffer him to go in. ^2And her father said, I verily thought that thou hadst utterly hated her; therefore I gave her to thy companion: is not her younger sister fairer than she? take her, I pray thee, instead of her. ^3And Samson said unto them, This time shall I be blameless in regard of the Philistines, when I do them a mischief. ^4And Samson went and caught three hundred foxes, and took firebrands, and turned tail to tail, and put a firebrand in the midst between every two tails. ^5And when he had set the brands on fire, he let them go into the standing grain of the Philistines, and burnt up both the shocks and the standing grain, and also the oliveyards. ^6Then the Philistines said, Who hath done this? And they said, Samson, the son-in-law of the Timnite, because he hath taken his wife, and given her to his companion. And the Philistines came up, and burnt her and her father with fire. ^7And Samson said unto them, If ye do after this manner, surely I will be avenged of you, and after that I will cease. ^8And he smote them hip and thigh with a great slaughter: and he went down and dwelt in the cleft of the rock of Etam.

^9Then the Philistines went up, and encamped in Judah, and spread themselves in Lehi. ^10And the men of Judah said, Why are ye come up against us? And they said, To bind Samson are we come up, to do to him as he hath done to us. ^11Then three thousand men of Judah went down to the cleft of the rock of Etam, and said to Samson, Knowest thou not that the Philistines are rulers over us? what then is this that thou hast done unto us? And he said unto them, As they did unto me, so have I done unto them. ^12And they said unto him, We are come down to bind thee, that we may deliver thee into the hand of the Philistines. And Samson said unto them, Swear unto me, that ye will not fall upon me yourselves. ^13And they spake unto him, saying, No; but we will bind thee fast, and deliver thee into their hand: but surely we will not kill thee. And they bound him with two new ropes, and brought him up from the rock.

^14When he came unto Lehi, the Philistines shouted as they met him: and the Spirit of Jehovah came mightily upon him, and the ropes that were upon his arms became as flax that was burnt with fire, and his bands dropped from off his hands. ^15And he found a fresh jawbone of an ass, and put forth his hand, and took it, and smote a thousand men therewith. ^16And Samson said,

With the jawbone of an ass, heaps upon heaps,

With the jawbone of an ass have I smitten a thousand men.

^17And it came to pass, when he had made an end of speaking, that he cast away the jawbone out of his hand; and that place was called Ramath-lehi. ^18And he was sore athirst, and called on Jehovah, and said, Thou hast given this great deliverance by the hand of thy servant; and now shall I die for thirst, and fall into the hand of the uncircumcised. ^19But God clave the hollow place that is in Lehi, and there came water thereout; and when he had drunk, his spirit came again, and he revived: wherefore the name thereof was called En-hakkore, which is in Lehi, unto this day. ^20And he judged Israel in the days of the Philistines twenty years.

Judges 16

16

^1And Samson went to Gaza, and saw there a harlot, and went in unto her. ^2And it was told the Gazites, saying, Samson is come hither. And they compassed him in, and laid wait for him all night in the gate of the city, and were quiet all the night, saying, Let be till morning light, then we will kill him. ^3And Samson lay till midnight, and arose at midnight, and laid hold of the doors of the gate of the city, and the two posts, and plucked them up, bar and all, and put them upon his shoulders, and carried them up to the top of the mountain that is before Hebron.

^4And it came to pass afterward, that he loved a woman in the valley of Sorek, whose name was Delilah. ^5And the lords of the Philistines came up unto her, and said unto her, Entice him, and see wherein his great strength lieth, and by what means we may prevail against him, that we may bind him to afflict him: and we will give thee every one of us eleven hundred pieces of silver. ^6And Delilah said to Samson, Tell me, I pray thee, wherein thy great strength lieth, and wherewith thou mightest be bound to afflict thee. ^7And Samson said unto her, If they bind me with seven green withes that were never dried, then shall I become weak, and be as another man. ^8Then the lords of the Philistines brought up to her seven green withes which had not been dried, and she bound him with them. ^9Now she had liers-in-wait abiding in the inner chamber. And she said unto him, The Philistines are upon thee, Samson. And he brake the withes, as a string of tow is broken when it toucheth the fire. So his strength was not known.

^10And Delilah said unto Samson, Behold, thou hast mocked me, and told me lies: now tell me, I pray thee, wherewith thou mightest be bound. ^11And he said unto her, If they only bind me with new ropes wherewith no work hath been done, then shall I become weak, and be as another man. ^12So Delilah took new ropes, and bound him therewith, and said unto him, The Philistines are upon thee, Samson. And the liers-in-wait were abiding in the inner chamber. And he brake them off his arms like a thread.

^13And Delilah said unto Samson, Hitherto thou hast mocked me, and told me lies: tell me wherewith thou mightest be bound. And he said unto her, If thou weavest the seven locks of my head with the web. ^14And she fastened it with the pin, and said unto him, The Philistines are upon thee, Samson. And he awaked out of his sleep, and plucked away the pin of the beam, and the web.

^15And she said unto him, How canst thou say, I love thee, when thy heart is not with me? thou hast mocked me these three times, and hast not told me wherein thy great strength lieth. ^16And it came to pass, when she pressed him daily with her words, and urged him, that his soul was vexed unto death. ^17And he told her all his heart, and said unto her, There hath not come a razor upon my head; for I have been a Nazirite unto God from my mother's womb: if I be shaven, then my strength will go from me, and I shall become weak, and be like any other man. ^18And when Delilah saw that he had told her all his heart, she sent and called for the lords of the Philistines, saying, Come up this once, for he hath told me all his heart. Then the lords of the Philistines came up unto her, and brought the money in their hand. ^19And she made him sleep upon her knees; and she called for a man, and shaved off the seven locks of his head; and she began to afflict him, and his strength went from him. ^20And she said, The Philistines are upon thee, Samson. And he awoke out of his sleep, and said, I will go out as at other times, and shake myself free. But he knew not that Jehovah was departed from him. ^21And the Philistines laid hold on him, and put out his eyes; and they brought him down to Gaza, and bound him with fetters of brass; and he did grind in the prison-house. ^22Howbeit the hair of his head began to grow again after he was shaven.

^23And the lords of the Philistines gathered them together to offer a great sacrifice unto Dagon their god, and to rejoice; for they said, Our god hath delivered Samson our enemy into our hand. ^24And when the people saw him, they praised their god; for they said, Our god hath delivered into our hand our enemy, and the destroyer of our country, who hath slain many of us. ^25And it came to pass, when their hearts were merry, that they said, Call for Samson, that he may make us sport. And they called for Samson out of the prison-house; and he made sport before them. And they set him between the pillars: ^26and Samson said unto the lad that held him by the hand, Suffer me that I may feel the pillars whereupon the house resteth, that I may lean upon them. ^27Now the house was full of men and women; and all the lords of the Philistines were there; and there were upon the roof about three thousand men and women, that beheld while Samson made sport.

^28And Samson called unto Jehovah, and said, O Lord Jehovah, remember me, I pray thee, and strengthen me, I pray thee, only this once, O God, that I may be at once avenged of the Philistines for my two eyes. ^29And Samson took hold of the two middle pillars upon which the house rested, and leaned upon them, the one with his right hand, and the other with his left. ^30And Samson said, Let me die with the Philistines. And he bowed himself with all his might; and the house fell upon the lords, and upon all the people that were therein. So the dead that he slew at his death were more than they that he slew in his life. ^31Then his brethren and all the house of his father came down, and took him, and brought him up, and buried him between Zorah and Eshtaol in the burying-place of Manoah his father. And he judged Israel twenty years.

Judges 17

17

^1And there was a man of the hill-country of Ephraim, whose name was Micah. ^2And he said unto his mother, The eleven hundred pieces of silver that were taken from thee, about which thou didst utter a curse, and didst also speak it in mine ears, behold, the silver is with me; I took it. And his mother said, Blessed be my son of Jehovah. ^3And he restored the eleven hundred pieces of silver to his mother; and his mother said, I verily dedicate the silver unto Jehovah from my hand for my son, to make a graven image and a molten image: now therefore I will restore it unto thee. ^4And when he restored the money unto his mother, his mother took two hundred pieces of silver, and gave them to the founder, who made thereof a graven image and a molten image: and it was in the house of Micah. ^5And the man Micah had a house of gods, and he made an ephod, and teraphim, and consecrated one of his sons, who became his priest. ^6In those days there was no king in Israel: every man did that which was right in his own eyes.

^7And there was a young man out of Beth-lehem-judah, of the family of Judah, who was a Levite; and he sojourned there. ^8And the man departed out of the city, out of Beth-lehem-judah, to sojourn where he could find a place, and he came to the hill-country of Ephraim to the house of Micah, as he journeyed. ^9And Micah said unto him, Whence comest thou? And he said unto him, I am a Levite of Beth-lehem-judah, and I go to sojourn where I may find a place. ^10And Micah said unto him, Dwell with me, and be unto me a father and a priest, and I will give thee ten pieces of silver by the year, and a suit of apparel, and thy victuals. So the Levite went in. ^11And the Levite was content to dwell with the man; and the young man was unto him as one of his sons. ^12And Micah consecrated the Levite, and the young man became his priest, and was in the house of Micah. ^13Then said Micah, Now know I that Jehovah will do me good, seeing I have a Levite to my priest.

Judges 18

18

^1In those days there was no king in Israel: and in those days the tribe of the Danites sought them an inheritance to dwell in; for unto that day their inheritance had not fallen unto them among the tribes of Israel. ^2And the children of Dan sent of their family five men from their whole number, men of valor, from Zorah, and from Eshtaol, to spy out the land, and to search it; and they said unto them, Go, search the land. And they came to the hill-country of Ephraim, unto the house of Micah, and lodged there. ^3When they were by the house of Micah, they knew the voice of the young man the Levite; and they turned aside thither, and said unto him, Who brought thee hither? and what doest thou in this place? and what hast thou here? ^4And he said unto them, Thus and thus hath Micah dealt with me, and he hath hired me, and I am become his priest. ^5And they said unto him, Ask counsel, we pray thee, of God, that we may know whether our way which we go shall be prosperous. ^6And the priest said unto them, Go in peace: before Jehovah is your way wherein ye go.

^7Then the five men departed, and came to Laish, and saw the people that were therein, how they dwelt in security, after the manner of the Sidonians, quiet and secure; for there was none in the land, possessing authority, that might put them to shame in anything, and they were far from the Sidonians, and had no dealings with any man. ^8And they came unto their brethren to Zorah and Eshtaol: and their brethren said unto them, What say ye? ^9And they said, Arise, and let us go up against them; for we have seen the land, and, behold, it is very good: and are ye still? be not slothful to go and to enter in to possess the land. ^10When ye go, ye shall come unto a people secure, and the land is large; for God hath given it into your hand, a place where there is no want of anything that is in the earth.

^11And there set forth from thence of the family of the Danites, out of Zorah and out of Eshtaol, six hundred men girt with weapons of war. ^12And they went up, and encamped in Kiriath-jearim, in Judah: wherefore they called that place Mahaneh-dan, unto this day; behold, it is behind Kiriath-jearim. ^13And they passed thence unto the hill-country of Ephraim, and came unto the house of Micah.

^14Then answered the five men that went to spy out the country of Laish, and said unto their brethren, Do ye know that there is in these houses an ephod, and teraphim, and a graven image, and a molten image? now therefore consider what ye have to do. ^15And they turned aside thither, and came to the house of the young man the Levite, even unto the house of Micah, and asked him of his welfare. ^16And the six hundred men girt with their weapons of war, who were of the children of Dan, stood by the entrance of the gate. ^17And the five men that went to spy out the land went up, and came in thither, and took the graven image, and the ephod, and the teraphim, and the molten image: and the priest stood by the entrance of the gate with the six hundred men girt with weapons of war. ^18And when these went into Micah's house, and fetched the graven image, the ephod, and the teraphim, and the molten image, the priest said unto them, What do ye? ^19And they said unto him, Hold thy peace, lay thy hand upon thy mouth, and go with us, and be to us a father and a priest: is it better for thee to be priest unto the house of one man, or to be priest unto a tribe and a family in Israel? ^20And the priest's heart was glad, and he took the ephod, and the teraphim, and the graven image, and went in the midst of the people.

^21So they turned and departed, and put the little ones and the cattle and the goods before them. ^22When they were a good way from the house of Micah, the men that were in the houses near to Micah's house were gathered together, and overtook the children of Dan. ^23And they cried unto the children of Dan. And they turned their faces, and said unto Micah, What aileth thee, that thou comest with such a company? ^24And he said, ye have taken away my gods which I made, and the priest, and are gone away, and what have I more? and how then say ye unto me, What aileth thee? ^25And the children of Dan said unto him, Let not thy voice be heard among us, lest angry fellows fall upon you, and thou lose thy life, with the lives of thy household. ^26And the children of Dan went their way: and when Micah saw that they were too strong for him, he turned and went back unto his house.

^27And they took that which Micah had made, and the priest whom he had, and came unto Laish, unto a people quiet and secure, and smote them with the edge of the sword; and they burnt the city with fire. ^28And there was no deliverer, because it was far from Sidon, and they had no dealings with any man; and it was in the valley that lieth by Beth-rehob. And they built the city, and dwelt therein. ^29And they called the name of the city Dan, after the name of Dan their father, who was born unto Israel: howbeit the name of the city was Laish at the first. ^30And the children of Dan set up for themselves the graven image: and Jonathan, the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, he and his sons were priests to the tribe of the Danites until the day of the captivity of the land. ^31So they set them up Micah's graven image which he made, all the time that the house of God was in Shiloh.

Judges 19

19

^1And it came to pass in those days, when there was no king in Israel, that there was a certain Levite sojourning on the farther side of the hill-country of Ephraim, who took to him a concubine out of Beth-lehem-judah. ^2And his concubine played the harlot against him, and went away from him unto her father's house to Beth-lehem-judah, and was there the space of four months. ^3And her husband arose, and went after her, to speak kindly unto her, to bring her again, having his servant with him, and a couple of asses: and she brought him into her father's house; and when the father of the damsel saw him, he rejoiced to meet him. ^4And his father-in-law, the damsel's father, retained him; and he abode with him three days: so they did eat and drink, and lodged there. ^5And it came to pass on the fourth day, that they arose early in the morning, and he rose up to depart: and the damsel's father said unto his son-in-law, Strengthen thy heart with a morsel of bread, and afterward ye shall go your way. ^6So they sat down, and did eat and drink, both of them together: and the damsel's father said unto the man, Be pleased, I pray thee, to tarry all night, and let thy heart be merry. ^7And the man rose up to depart; but his father-in-law urged him, and he lodged there again. ^8And he arose early in the morning on the fifth day to depart; and the damsel's father said, Strengthen thy heart, I pray thee, and tarry ye until the day declineth; and they did eat, both of them. ^9And when the man rose up to depart, he, and his concubine, and his servant, his father-in-law, the damsel's father, said unto him, Behold, now the day draweth toward evening, I pray you tarry all night: behold, the day groweth to an end, lodge here, that thy heart may be merry; and to-morrow get you early on your way, that thou mayest go home.

^10But the man would not tarry that night, but he rose up and departed, and came over against Jebus (the same is Jerusalem): and there were with him a couple of asses saddled; his concubine also was with him. ^11When they were by Jebus, the day was far spent; and the servant said unto his master, Come, I pray thee, and let us turn aside into this city of the Jebusites, and lodge in it. ^12And his master said unto him, We will not turn aside into the city of a foreigner, that is not of the children of Israel; but we will pass over to Gibeah. ^13And he said unto his servant, Come and let us draw near to one of these places; and we will lodge in Gibeah, or in Ramah. ^14So they passed on and went their way; and the sun went down upon them near to Gibeah, which belongeth to Benjamin. ^15And they turned aside thither, to go in to lodge in Gibeah: and he went in, and sat him down in the street of the city; for there was no man that took them into his house to lodge.

^16And, behold, there came an old man from his work out of the field at even: now the man was of the hill-country of Ephraim, and he sojourned in Gibeah; but the men of the place were Benjamites. ^17And he lifted up his eyes, and saw the wayfaring man in the street of the city; and the old man said, Whither goest thou? and whence comest thou? ^18And he said unto him, We are passing from Beth-lehem-judah unto the farther side of the hill-country of Ephraim; from thence am I, and I went to Beth-lehem-judah: and I am now going to the house of Jehovah; and there is no man that taketh me into his house. ^19Yet there is both straw and provender for our asses; and there is bread and wine also for me, and for thy handmaid, and for the young man that is with thy servants: there is no want of anything. ^20And the old man said, Peace be unto thee; howsoever let all thy wants lie upon me; only lodge not in the street. ^21So he brought him into his house, and gave the asses fodder; and they washed their feet, and did eat and drink.

^22As they were making their hearts merry, behold, the men of the city, certain base fellows, beset the house round about, beating at the door; and they spake to the master of the house, the old man, saying, Bring forth the man that came into thy house, that we may know him. ^23And the man, the master of the house, went out unto them, and said unto them, Nay, my brethren, I pray you, do not so wickedly; seeing that this man is come into my house, do not this folly. ^24Behold, here is my daughter a virgin, and his concubine; them I will bring out now, and humble ye them, and do with them what seemeth good unto you: but unto this man do not any such folly. ^25But the men would not hearken to him: so the man laid hold on his concubine, and brought her forth unto them; and they knew her, and abused her all the night until the morning: and when the day began to spring, they let her go. ^26Then came the woman in the dawning of the day, and fell down at the door of the man's house where her lord was, till it was light.

^27And her lord rose up in the morning, and opened the doors of the house, and went out to go his way; and, behold, the woman his concubine was fallen down at the door of the house, with her hands upon the threshold. ^28And he said unto her, Up, and let us be going; but none answered: then he took her up upon the ass; and the man rose up, and gat him unto his place. ^29And when he was come into his house, he took a knife, and laid hold on his concubine, and divided her, limb by limb, into twelve pieces, and sent her throughout all the borders of Israel. ^30And it was so, that all that saw it said, There was no such deed done nor seen from the day that the children of Israel came up out of the land of Egypt unto this day: consider it, take counsel, and speak.

Judges 20

20

^1Then all the children of Israel went out, and the congregation was assembled as one man, from Dan even to Beer-sheba, with the land of Gilead, unto Jehovah at Mizpah. ^2And the chiefs of all the people, even of all the tribes of Israel, presented themselves in the assembly of the people of God, four hundred thousand footmen that drew sword. ^3(Now the children of Benjamin heard that the children of Israel were gone up to Mizpah.) And the children of Israel said, Tell us, how was this wickedness brought to pass? ^4And the Levite, the husband of the woman that was murdered, answered and said, I came into Gibeah that belongeth to Benjamin, I and my concubine, to lodge. ^5And the men of Gibeah rose against me, and beset the house round about me by night; me they thought to have slain, and my concubine they forced, and she is dead. ^6And I took my concubine, and cut her in pieces, and sent her throughout all the country of the inheritance of Israel; for they have committed lewdness and folly in Israel. ^7Behold, ye children of Israel, all of you, give here your advice and counsel.

^8And all the people arose as one man, saying, We will not any of us go to his tent, neither will we any of us turn unto his house. ^9But now this is the thing which we will do to Gibeah: we will go up against it by lot; ^10and we will take ten men of a hundred throughout all the tribes of Israel, and a hundred of a thousand, and a thousand out of ten thousand, to fetch victuals for the people, that they may do, when they come to Gibeah of Benjamin, according to all the folly that they have wrought in Israel. ^11So all the men of Israel were gathered against the city, knit together as one man.

^12And the tribes of Israel sent men through all the tribe of Benjamin, saying, What wickedness is this that is come to pass among you? ^13Now therefore deliver up the men, the base fellows, that are in Gibeah, that we may put them to death, and put away evil from Israel. But Benjamin would not hearken to the voice of their brethren the children of Israel. ^14And the children of Benjamin gathered themselves together out of the cities unto Gibeah, to go out to battle against the children of Israel. ^15And the children of Benjamin were numbered on that day out of the cities twenty and six thousand men that drew sword, besides the inhabitants of Gibeah, who were numbered seven hundred chosen men. ^16Among all this people there were seven hundred chosen men lefthanded; every one could sling stones at a hair-breadth, and not miss.

^17And the men of Israel, besides Benjamin, were numbered four hundred thousand men that drew sword: all these were men of war. ^18And the children of Israel arose, and went up to Beth-el, and asked counsel of God; and they said, Who shall go up for us first to battle against the children of Benjamin? And Jehovah said, Judah shall go up first.

^19And the children of Israel rose up in the morning, and encamped against Gibeah. ^20And the men of Israel went out to battle against Benjamin; and the men of Israel set the battle in array against them at Gibeah. ^21And the children of Benjamin came forth out of Gibeah, and destroyed down to the ground of the Israelites on that day twenty and two thousand men. ^22And the people, the men of Israel, encouraged themselves, and set the battle again in array in the place where they set themselves in array the first day. ^23And the children of Israel went up and wept before Jehovah until even; and they asked of Jehovah, saying, Shall I again draw nigh to battle against the children of Benjamin my brother? And Jehovah said, Go up against him.

^24And the children of Israel came near against the children of Benjamin the second day. ^25And Benjamin went forth against them out of Gibeah the second day, and destroyed down to the ground of the children of Israel again eighteen thousand men; all these drew the sword. ^26Then all the children of Israel, and all the people, went up, and came unto Beth-el, and wept, and sat there before Jehovah, and fasted that day until even; and they offered burnt-offerings and peace-offerings before Jehovah. ^27And the children of Israel asked of Jehovah (for the ark of the covenant of God was there in those days, ^28and Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron, stood before it in those days), saying, Shall I yet again go out to battle against the children of Benjamin my brother, or shall I cease? And Jehovah said, Go up; for to-morrow I will deliver him into thy hand.

^29And Israel set liers-in-wait against Gibeah round about. ^30And the children of Israel went up against the children of Benjamin on the third day, and set themselves in array against Gibeah, as at other times. ^31And the children of Benjamin went out against the people, and were drawn away from the city; and they began to smite and kill of the people, as at other times, in the highways, of which one goeth up to Beth-el, and the other to Gibeah, in the field, about thirty men of Israel. ^32And the children of Benjamin said, They are smitten down before us, as at the first. But the children of Israel said, Let us flee, and draw them away from the city unto the highways. ^33And all the men of Israel rose up out of their place, and set themselves in array at Baal-tamar: and the liers-in-wait of Israel brake forth out of their place, even out of Maareh-geba. ^34And there came over against Gibeah ten thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and the battle was sore; but they knew not that evil was close upon them. ^35And Jehovah smote Benjamin before Israel; and the children of Israel destroyed of Benjamin that day twenty and five thousand and a hundred men: all these drew the sword.

^36So the children of Benjamin saw that they were smitten; for the men of Israel gave place to Benjamin, because they trusted unto the liers-in-wait whom they had set against Gibeah. ^37And the liers-in-wait hasted, and rushed upon Gibeah; and the liers-in-wait drew themselves along, and smote all the city with the edge of the sword. ^38Now the appointed sign between the men of Israel and the liers-in-wait was, that they should make a great cloud of smoke rise up out of the city. ^39And the men of Israel turned in the battle, and Benjamin began to smite and kill of the men of Israel about thirty persons; for they said, Surely they are smitten down before us, as in the first battle. ^40But when the cloud began to arise up out of the city in a pillar of smoke, the Benjamites looked behind them; and, behold, the whole of the city went up in smoke to heaven. ^41And the men of Israel turned, and the men of Benjamin were dismayed; for they saw that evil was come upon them. ^42Therefore they turned their backs before the men of Israel unto the way of the wilderness; but the battle followed hard after them; and they that came out of the cities destroyed them in the midst thereof. ^43They inclosed the Benjamites round about, and chased them, and trod them down at their resting-place, as far as over against Gibeah toward the sunrising. ^44And there fell of Benjamin eighteen thousand men; all these were men of valor. ^45And they turned and fled toward the wilderness unto the rock of Rimmon: and they gleaned of them in the highways five thousand men, and followed hard after them unto Gidom, and smote of them two thousand men. ^46So that all who fell that day of Benjamin were twenty and five thousand men that drew the sword; all these were men of valor. ^47But six hundred men turned and fled toward the wilderness unto the rock of Rimmon, and abode in the rock of Rimmon four months. ^48And the men of Israel turned again upon the children of Benjamin, and smote them with the edge of the sword, both the entire city, and the cattle, and all that they found: moreover all the cities which they found they set on fire.

Judges 21

21

^1Now the men of Israel had sworn in Mizpah, saying, There shall not any of us give his daughter unto Benjamin to wife. ^2And the people came to Beth-el, and sat there till even before God, and lifted up their voices, and wept sore. ^3And they said, O Jehovah, the God of Israel, why is this come to pass in Israel, that there should be to-day one tribe lacking in Israel? ^4And it came to pass on the morrow, that the people rose early, and built there an altar, and offered burnt-offerings and peace-offerings. ^5And the children of Israel said, Who is there among all the tribes of Israel that came not up in the assembly unto Jehovah? For they had made a great oath concerning him that came not up unto Jehovah to Mizpah, saying, He shall surely be put to death. ^6And the children of Israel repented them for Benjamin their brother, and said, There is one tribe cut off from Israel this day. ^7How shall we do for wives for them that remain, seeing we have sworn by Jehovah that we will not give them of our daughters to wives?

^8And they said, What one is there of the tribes of Israel that came not up unto Jehovah to Mizpah? And, behold, there came none to the camp from Jabesh-gilead to the assembly. ^9For when the people were numbered, behold, there were none of the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead there. ^10And the congregation sent thither twelve thousand men of the valiantest, and commanded them, saying, Go and smite the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead with the edge of the sword, with the women and the little ones. ^11And this is the thing that ye shall do: ye shall utterly destroy every male, and every woman that hath lain by man. ^12And they found among the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead four hundred young virgins, that had not known man by lying with him; and they brought them unto the camp to Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan.

^13And the whole congregation sent and spake to the children of Benjamin that were in the rock of Rimmon, and proclaimed peace unto them. ^14And Benjamin returned at that time; and they gave them the women whom they had saved alive of the women of Jabesh-gilead: and yet so they sufficed them not. ^15And the people repented them for Benjamin, because that Jehovah had made a breach in the tribes of Israel.

^16Then the elders of the congregation said, How shall we do for wives for them that remain, seeing the women are destroyed out of Benjamin? ^17And they said, There must be an inheritance for them that are escaped of Benjamin, that a tribe be not blotted out from Israel. ^18Howbeit we may not give them wives of our daughters, for the children of Israel had sworn, saying, Cursed be he that giveth a wife to Benjamin. ^19And they said, Behold, there is a feast of Jehovah from year to year in Shiloh, which is on the north of Beth-el, on the east side of the highway that goeth up from Beth-el to Shechem, and on the south of Lebonah. ^20And they commanded the children of Benjamin, saying, Go and lie in wait in the vineyards, ^21and see, and, behold, if the daughters of Shiloh come out to dance in the dances, then come ye out of the vineyards, and catch you every man his wife of the daughters of Shiloh, and go to the land of Benjamin. ^22And it shall be, when their fathers or their brethren come to complain unto us, that we will say unto them, Grant them graciously unto us, because we took not for each man of them his wife in battle, neither did ye give them unto them, else would ye now be guilty. ^23And the children of Benjamin did so, and took them wives, according to their number, of them that danced, whom they carried off: and they went and returned unto their inheritance, and built the cities, and dwelt in them. ^24And the children of Israel departed thence at that time, every man to his tribe and to his family, and they went out from thence every man to his inheritance.

^25In those days there was no king in Israel: every man did that which was right in his own eyes.

Lamentations 2

2

^1How hath the Lord covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger!

He hath cast down from heaven unto the earth the beauty of Israel,

And hath not remembered his footstool in the day of his anger.

^2The Lord hath swallowed up all the habitations of Jacob, and hath not pitied:

He hath thrown down in his wrath the strongholds of the daughter of Judah;

He hath brought them down to the ground; he hath profaned the kingdom and the princes thereof.

^3He hath cut off in fierce anger all the horn of Israel;

He hath drawn back his right hand from before the enemy:

And he hath burned up Jacob like a flaming fire, which devoureth round about.

^4He hath bent his bow like an enemy, he hath stood with his right hand as an adversary,

And hath slain all that were pleasant to the eye:

In the tent of the daughter of Zion he hath poured out his wrath like fire.

^5The Lord is become as an enemy, he hath swallowed up Israel;

He hath swallowed up all her palaces, he hath destroyed his strongholds;

And he hath multiplied in the daughter of Judah mourning and lamentation.

^6And he hath violently taken away his tabernacle, as if it were of a garden; he hath destroyed his place of assembly:

Jehovah hath caused solemn assembly and sabbath to be forgotten in Zion,

And hath despised in the indignation of his anger the king and the priest.

^7The Lord hath cast off his altar, he hath abhorred his sanctuary;

He hath given up into the hand of the enemy the walls of her palaces:

They have made a noise in the house of Jehovah, as in the day of a solemn assembly.

^8Jehovah hath purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion;

He hath stretched out the line, he hath not withdrawn his hand from destroying;

And he hath made the rampart and wall to lament; they languish together.

^9Her gates are sunk into the ground; he hath destroyed and broken her bars:

Her king and her princes are among the nations where the law is not;

Yea, her prophets find no vision from Jehovah.

^10The elders of the daughter of Zion sit upon the ground, they keep silence;

They have cast up dust upon their heads; they have girded themselves with sackcloth:

The virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground.

^11Mine eyes do fail with tears, my heart is troubled;

My liver is poured upon the earth, because of the destruction of the daughter of my people,

Because the young children and the sucklings swoon in the streets of the city.

^12They say to their mothers, Where is grain and wine?

When they swoon as the wounded in the streets of the city,

When their soul is poured out into their mothers' bosom.

^13What shall I testify unto thee? what shall I liken to thee, O daughter of Jerusalem?

What shall I compare to thee, that I may comfort thee, O virgin daughter of Zion?

For thy breach is great like the sea: who can heal thee?

^14Thy prophets have seen for thee false and foolish visions;

And they have not uncovered thine iniquity, to bring back thy captivity,

But have seen for thee false oracles and causes of banishment.

^15All that pass by clap their hands at thee;

They hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, saying,

Is this the city that men called The perfection of beauty, The joy of the whole earth?

^16All thine enemies have opened their mouth wide against thee;

They hiss and gnash the teeth; they say, We have swallowed her up;

Certainly this is the day that we looked for; we have found, we have seen it.

^17Jehovah hath done that which he purposed; he hath fulfilled his word that he commanded in the days of old;

He hath thrown down, and hath not pitied:

And he hath caused the enemy to rejoice over thee; he hath exalted the horn of thine adversaries.

^18Their heart cried unto the Lord:

O wall of the daughter of Zion, let tears run down like a river day and night;

Give thyself no respite; let not the apple of thine eye cease.

^19Arise, cry out in the night, at the beginning of the watches;

Pour out thy heart like water before the face of the Lord:

Lift up thy hands toward him for the life of thy young children, that faint for hunger at the head of every street.

^20See, O Jehovah, and behold to whom thou hast done thus!

Shall the women eat their fruit, the children that are dandled in the hands?

Shall the priest and the prophet be slain in the sanctuary of the Lord?

^21The youth and the old man lie on the ground in the streets;

My virgins and my young men are fallen by the sword:

Thou hast slain them in the day of thine anger; thou hast slaughtered, and not pitied.

^22Thou hast called, as in the day of a solemn assembly, my terrors on every side;

And there was none that escaped or remained in the day of Jehovah's anger:

Those that I have dandled and brought up hath mine enemy consumed.

Lamentations 4

4

^1How is the gold become dim! how is the most pure gold changed!

The stones of the sanctuary are poured out at the head of every street.

^2The precious sons of Zion, comparable to fine gold,

How are they esteemed as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of the potter!

^3Even the jackals draw out the breast, they give suck to their young ones:

The daughter of my people is become cruel, like the ostriches in the wilderness.

^4The tongue of the sucking child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth for thirst:

The young children ask bread, and no man breaketh it unto them.

^5They that did feed delicately are desolate in the streets:

They that were brought up in scarlet embrace dunghills.

^6For the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the sin of Sodom,

That was overthrown as in a moment, and no hands were laid upon her.

^7Her nobles were purer than snow, they were whiter than milk;

They were more ruddy in body than rubies, their polishing was as of sapphire.

^8Their visage is blacker than a coal; they are not known in the streets:

Their skin cleaveth to their bones; it is withered, it is become like a stick.

^9They that are slain with the sword are better than they that are slain with hunger;

For these pine away, stricken through, for want of the fruits of the field.

^10The hands of the pitiful women have boiled their own children;

They were their food in the destruction of the daughter of my people.

^11Jehovah hath accomplished his wrath, he hath poured out his fierce anger;

And he hath kindled a fire in Zion, which hath devoured the foundations thereof.

^12The kings of the earth believed not, neither all the inhabitants of the world,

That the adversary and the enemy would enter into the gates of Jerusalem.

^13It is because of the sins of her prophets, and the iniquities of her priests,

That have shed the blood of the just in the midst of her.

^14They wander as blind men in the streets, they are polluted with blood,

So that men cannot touch their garments.

^15Depart ye, they cried unto them, Unclean! depart, depart, touch not!

When they fled away and wandered, men said among the nations, They shall no more sojourn here.

^16The anger of Jehovah hath scattered them; he will no more regard them:

They respected not the persons of the priests, they favored not the elders.

^17Our eyes do yet fail in looking for our vain help:

In our watching we have watched for a nation that could not save.

^18They hunt our steps, so that we cannot go in our streets:

Our end is near, our days are fulfilled; for our end is come.

^19Our pursuers were swifter than the eagles of the heavens:

They chased us upon the mountains, they laid wait for us in the wilderness.

^20The breath of our nostrils, the anointed of Jehovah, was taken in their pits;

Of whom we said, Under his shadow we shall live among the nations.

^21Rejoice and be glad, O daughter of Edom, that dwellest in the land of Uz:

The cup shall pass through unto thee also; thou shalt be drunken, and shalt make thyself naked.

^22The punishment of thine iniquity is accomplished, O daughter of Zion; he will no more carry thee away into captivity:

He will visit thine iniquity, O daughter of Edom; he will uncover thy sins.

Leviticus 2

2

^1And when any one offereth an oblation of a meal-offering unto Jehovah, his oblation shall be of fine flour; and he shall pour oil upon it, and put frankincense thereon: ^2and he shall bring it to Aaron's sons the priests; and he shall take thereout his handful of the fine flour thereof, and of the oil thereof, with all the frankincense thereof; and the priest shall burn it as the memorial thereof upon the altar, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah: ^3and that which is left of the meal-offering shall be Aaron's and his sons': it is a thing most holy of the offerings of Jehovah made by fire.

^4And when thou offerest an oblation of a meal-offering baken in the oven, it shall be unleavened cakes of fine flour mingled with oil, or unleavened wafers anointed with oil. ^5And if thy oblation be a meal-offering of the baking-pan, it shall be of fine flour unleavened, mingled with oil. ^6Thou shalt part it in pieces, and pour oil thereon: it is a meal-offering. ^7And if thy oblation be a meal-offering of the frying-pan, it shall be made of fine flour with oil. ^8And thou shalt bring the meal-offering that is made of these things unto Jehovah: and it shall be presented unto the priest, and he shall bring it unto the altar. ^9And the priest shall take up from the meal-offering the memorial thereof, and shall burn it upon the altar, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah. ^10And that which is left of the meal-offering shall be Aaron's and his sons': it is a thing most holy of the offerings of Jehovah made by fire.

^11No meal-offering, which ye shall offer unto Jehovah, shall be made with leaven; for ye shall burn no leaven, nor any honey, as an offering made by fire unto Jehovah. ^12As an oblation of first -fruits ye shall offer them unto Jehovah: but they shall not come up for a sweet savor on the altar. ^13And every oblation of thy meal-offering shalt thou season with salt; neither shalt thou suffer the salt of the covenant of thy God to be lacking from thy meal-offering: with all thine oblations thou shalt offer salt.

^14And if thou offer a meal-offering of first-fruits unto Jehovah, thou shalt offer for the meal-offering of thy first-fruits grain in the ear parched with fire, bruised grain of the fresh ear. ^15And thou shalt put oil upon it, and lay frankincense thereon: it is a meal-offering. ^16And the priest shall burn the memorial of it, part of the bruised grain thereof, and part of the oil thereof, with all the frankincense thereof: it is an offering made by fire unto Jehovah.

Leviticus 3

3

^1And if his oblation be a sacrifice of peace-offerings; if he offer of the herd, whether male or female, he shall offer it without blemish before Jehovah. ^2And he shall lay his hand upon the head of his oblation, and kill it at the door of the tent of meeting: and Aaron's sons the priests shall sprinkle the blood upon the altar round about. ^3And he shall offer of the sacrifice of peace-offerings an offering made by fire unto Jehovah; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards, ^4and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the caul upon the liver, with the kidneys, shall he take away. ^5And Aaron's sons shall burn it on the altar upon the burnt-offering, which is upon the wood that is on the fire: it is an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah.

^6And if his oblation for a sacrifice of peace-offerings unto Jehovah be of the flock; male or female, he shall offer it without blemish. ^7If he offer a lamb for his oblation, then shall he offer it before Jehovah; ^8and he shall lay his hand upon the head of his oblation, and kill it before the tent of meeting: and Aaron's sons shall sprinkle the blood thereof upon the altar round about. ^9And he shall offer of the sacrifice of peace-offerings an offering made by fire unto Jehovah; the fat thereof, the fat tail entire, he shall take away hard by the backbone; and the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards, ^10and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the loins, and the caul upon the liver, with the kidneys, shall he take away. ^11And the priest shall burn it upon the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire unto Jehovah.

^12And if his oblation be a goat, then he shall offer it before Jehovah: ^13and he shall lay his hand upon the head of it, and kill it before the tent of meeting; and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle the blood thereof upon the altar round about. ^14And he shall offer thereof his oblation, even an offering made by fire unto Jehovah; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards, ^15and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the loins, and the caul upon the liver, with the kidneys, shall he take away. ^16And the priest shall burn them upon the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire, for a sweet savor; all the fat is Jehovah's. ^17It shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations in all your dwellings, that ye shall eat neither fat nor blood.

Leviticus 4

4

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If any one shall sin unwittingly, in any of the things which Jehovah hath commanded not to be done, and shall do any one of them: ^3if the anointed priest shall sin so as to bring guilt on the people, then let him offer for his sin, which he hath sinned, a young bullock without blemish unto Jehovah for a sin-offering. ^4And he shall bring the bullock unto the door of the tent of meeting before Jehovah; and he shall lay his hand upon the head of the bullock, and kill the bullock before Jehovah. ^5And the anointed priest shall take of the blood of the bullock, and bring it to the tent of meeting: ^6and the priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle of the blood seven times before Jehovah, before the veil of the sanctuary. ^7And the priest shall put of the blood upon the horns of the altar of sweet incense before Jehovah, which is in the tent of meeting; and all the blood of the bullock shall he pour out at the base of the altar of burnt-offering, which is at the door of the tent of meeting. ^8And all the fat of the bullock of the sin-offering he shall take off from it; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards, ^9and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the loins, and the caul upon the liver, with the kidneys, shall he take away, ^10as it is taken off from the ox of the sacrifice of peace-offerings: and the priest shall burn them upon the altar of burnt-offering. ^11And the skin of the bullock, and all its flesh, with its head, and with its legs, and its inwards, and its dung, ^12even the whole bullock shall he carry forth without the camp unto a clean place, where the ashes are poured out, and burn it on wood with fire: where the ashes are poured out shall it be burnt.

^13And if the whole congregation of Israel err, and the thing be hid from the eyes of the assembly, and they have done any of the things which Jehovah hath commanded not to be done, and are guilty; ^14when the sin wherein they have sinned is known, then the assembly shall offer a young bullock for a sin-offering, and bring it before the tent of meeting. ^15And the elders of the congregation shall lay their hands upon the head of the bullock before Jehovah; and the bullock shall be killed before Jehovah. ^16And the anointed priest shall bring of the blood of the bullock to the tent of meeting: ^17and the priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle it seven times before Jehovah, before the veil. ^18And he shall put of the blood upon the horns of the altar which is before Jehovah, that is in the tent of meeting; and all the blood shall he pour out at the base of the altar of burnt-offering, which is at the door of the tent of meeting. ^19And all the fat thereof shall he take off from it, and burn it upon the altar. ^20Thus shall he do with the bullock; as he did with the bullock of the sin-offering, so shall he do with this; and the priest shall make atonement for them, and they shall be forgiven. ^21And he shall carry forth the bullock without the camp, and burn it as he burned the first bullock: it is the sin-offering for the assembly.

^22When a ruler sinneth, and doeth unwittingly any one of all the things which Jehovah his God hath commanded not to be done, and is guilty; ^23if his sin, wherein he hath sinned, be made known to him, he shall bring for his oblation a goat, a male without blemish. ^24And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the goat, and kill it in the place where they kill the burnt-offering before Jehovah: it is a sin-offering. ^25And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin-offering with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt-offering; and the blood thereof shall he pour out at the base of the altar of burnt-offering. ^26And all the fat thereof shall he burn upon the altar, as the fat of the sacrifice of peace-offerings; and the priest shall make atonement for him as concerning his sin, and he shall be forgiven.

^27And if any one of the common people sin unwittingly, in doing any of the things which Jehovah hath commanded not to be done, and be guilty; ^28if his sin, which he hath sinned, be made known to him, then he shall bring for his oblation a goat, a female without blemish, for his sin which he hath sinned. ^29And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the sin-offering, and kill the sin-offering in the place of burnt-offering. ^30And the priest shall take of the blood thereof with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt-offering; and all the blood thereof shall he pour out at the base of the altar. ^31And all the fat thereof shall he take away, as the fat is taken away from off the sacrifice of peace-offerings; and the priest shall burn it upon the altar for a sweet savor unto Jehovah; and the priest shall make atonement for him, and he shall be forgiven.

^32And if he bring a lamb as his oblation for a sin-offering, he shall bring it a female without blemish. ^33And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the sin-offering, and kill it for a sin-offering in the place where they kill the burnt-offering. ^34And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin-offering with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt-offering; and all the blood thereof shall he pour out at the base of the altar: ^35and all the fat thereof shall he take away, as the fat of the lamb is taken away from the sacrifice of peace-offerings; and the priest shall burn them on the altar, upon the offerings of Jehovah made by fire; and the priest shall make atonement for him as touching his sin that he hath sinned, and he shall be forgiven.

Leviticus 5

5

^1And if any one sin, in that he heareth the voice of adjuration, he being a witness, whether he hath seen or known, if he do not utter it, then he shall bear his iniquity. ^2Or if any one touch any unclean thing, whether it be the carcass of an unclean beast, or the carcass of unclean cattle, or the carcass of unclean creeping things, and it be hidden from him, and he be unclean, then he shall be guilty. ^3Or if he touch the uncleanness of man, whatsoever his uncleanness be wherewith he is unclean, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth of it, then he shall be guilty. ^4Or if any one swear rashly with his lips to do evil, or to do good, whatsoever it be that a man shall utter rashly with an oath, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth of it, then he shall be guilty in one of these things. ^5And it shall be, when he shall be guilty in one of these things, that he shall confess that wherein he hath sinned: ^6and he shall bring his trespass-offering unto Jehovah for his sin which he hath sinned, a female from the flock, a lamb or a goat, for a sin-offering; and the priest shall make atonement for him as concerning his sin.

^7And if his means suffice not for a lamb, then he shall bring his trespass-offering for that wherein he hath sinned, two turtle-doves, or two young pigeons, unto Jehovah; one for a sin-offering, and the other for a burnt-offering. ^8And he shall bring them unto the priest, who shall offer that which is for the sin-offering first, and wring off its head from its neck, but shall not divide it asunder: ^9and he shall sprinkle of the blood of the sin-offering upon the side of the altar; and the rest of the blood shall be drained out at the base of the altar: it is a sin-offering. ^10And he shall offer the second for a burnt-offering, according to the ordinance; and the priest shall make atonement for him as concerning his sin which he hath sinned, and he shall be forgiven.

^11But if his means suffice not for two turtle-doves, or two young pigeons, then he shall bring his oblation for that wherein he hath sinned, the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a sin-offering: he shall put no oil upon it, neither shall he put any frankincense thereon; for it is a sin-offering. ^12And he shall bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take his handful of it as the memorial thereof, and burn it on the altar, upon the offerings of Jehovah made by fire: it is a sin-offering. ^13And the priest shall make atonement for him as touching his sin that he hath sinned in any of these things, and he shall be forgiven: and the remnant shall be the priest's, as the meal-offering.

^14And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^15If any one commit a trespass, and sin unwittingly, in the holy things of Jehovah; then he shall bring his trespass-offering unto Jehovah, a ram without blemish out of the flock, according to thy estimation in silver by shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary, for a trespass-offering: ^16and he shall make restitution for that which he hath done amiss in the holy thing, and shall add the fifth part thereto, and give it unto the priest; and the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass-offering, and he shall be forgiven.

^17And if any one sin, and do any of the things which Jehovah hath commanded not to be done; though he knew it not, yet is he guilty, and shall bear his iniquity. ^18And he shall bring a ram without blemish out of the flock, according to thy estimation, for a trespass-offering, unto the priest; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning the thing wherein he erred unwittingly and knew it not, and he shall be forgiven. ^19It is a trespass-offering: he is certainly guilty before Jehovah.

Leviticus 6

6

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2If any one sin, and commit a trespass against Jehovah, and deal falsely with his neighbor in a matter of deposit, or of bargain, or of robbery, or have oppressed his neighbor, ^3or have found that which was lost, and deal falsely therein, and swear to a lie; in any of all these things that a man doeth, sinning therein; ^4then it shall be, if he hath sinned, and is guilty, that he shall restore that which he took by robbery, or the thing which he hath gotten by oppression, or the deposit which was committed to him, or the lost thing which he found, ^5or any thing about which he hath sworn falsely; he shall even restore it in full, and shall add the fifth part more thereto: unto him to whom it appertaineth shall he give it, in the day of his being found guilty. ^6And he shall bring his trespass-offering unto Jehovah, a ram without blemish out of the flock, according to thy estimation, for a trespass-offering, unto the priest: ^7and the priest shall make atonement for him before Jehovah; and he shall be forgiven concerning whatsoever he doeth so as to be guilty thereby.

^8And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^9Command Aaron and his sons, saying, This is the law of the burnt-offering: the burnt-offering shall be on the hearth upon the altar all night unto the morning; and the fire of the altar shall be kept burning thereon. ^10And the priest shall put on his linen garment, and his linen breeches shall he put upon his flesh; and he shall take up the ashes whereto the fire hath consumed the burnt-offering on the altar, and he shall put them beside the altar. ^11And he shall put off his garments, and put on other garments, and carry forth the ashes without the camp unto a clean place. ^12And the fire upon the altar shall be kept burning thereon, it shall not go out; and the priest shall burn wood on it every morning: and he shall lay the burnt-offering in order upon it, and shall burn thereon the fat of the peace-offerings. ^13Fire shall be kept burning upon the altar continually; it shall not go out.

^14And this is the law of the meal-offering: the sons of Aaron shall offer it before Jehovah, before the altar. ^15And he shall take up therefrom his handful, of the fine flour of the meal-offering, and of the oil thereof, and all the frankincense which is upon the meal-offering, and shall burn it upon the altar for a sweet savor, as the memorial thereof, unto Jehovah. ^16And that which is left thereof shall Aaron and his sons eat: it shall be eaten without leaven in a holy place; in the court of the tent of meeting they shall eat it. ^17It shall not be baken with leaven. I have given it as their portion of my offerings made by fire; it is most holy, as the sin-offering, and as the trespass-offering. ^18Every male among the children of Aaron shall eat of it, as his portion for ever throughout your generations, from the offerings of Jehovah made by fire: whosoever toucheth them shall be holy.

^19And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^20This is the oblation of Aaron and of his sons, which they shall offer unto Jehovah in the day when he is anointed: the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a meal-offering perpetually, half of it in the morning, and half thereof in the evening. ^21On a baking-pan it shall be made with oil; when it is soaked, thou shalt bring it in: in baken pieces shalt thou offer the meal-offering for a sweet savor unto Jehovah. ^22And the anointed priest that shall be in his stead from among his sons shall offer it: by a statute for ever it shall be wholly burnt unto Jehovah. ^23And every meal-offering of the priest shall be wholly burnt: it shall not be eaten.

^24And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^25Speak unto Aaron and to his sons, saying, This is the law of the sin-offering: in the place where the burnt-offering is killed shall the sin-offering be killed before Jehovah: it is most holy. ^26The priest that offereth it for sin shall eat it: in a holy place shall it be eaten, in the court of the tent of meeting. ^27Whatsoever shall touch the flesh thereof shall be holy; and when there is sprinkled of the blood thereof upon any garment, thou shalt wash that whereon it was sprinkled in a holy place. ^28But the earthen vessel wherein it is boiled shall be broken; and if it be boiled in a brazen vessel, it shall be scoured, and rinsed in water. ^29Every male among the priests shall eat thereof: it is most holy. ^30And no sin-offering, whereof any of the blood is brought into the tent of meeting to make atonement in the holy place, shall be eaten: it shall be burnt with fire.

Leviticus 7

7

^1And this is the law of the trespass-offering: it is most holy. ^2In the place where they kill the burnt-offering shall they kill the trespass-offering; and the blood thereof shall he sprinkle upon the altar round about. ^3And he shall offer of it all the fat thereof: the fat tail, and the fat that covereth the inwards, ^4and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the caul upon the liver, with the kidneys, shall he take away; ^5and the priest shall burn them upon the altar for an offering made by fire unto Jehovah: it is a trespass-offering. ^6Every male among the priests shall eat thereof: it shall be eaten in a holy place: it is most holy. ^7As is the sin-offering, so is the trespass-offering; there is one law for them: the priest that maketh atonement therewith, he shall have it. ^8And the priest that offereth any man's burnt-offering, even the priest shall have to himself the skin of the burnt-offering which he hath offered. ^9And every meal-offering that is baken in the oven, and all that is dressed in the frying-pan, and on the baking-pan, shall be the priest's that offereth it. ^10And every meal-offering, mingled with oil, or dry, shall all the sons of Aaron have, one as well as another.

^11And this is the law of the sacrifice of peace-offerings, which one shall offer unto Jehovah. ^12If he offer it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer with the sacrifice of thanksgiving unleavened cakes mingled with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil, and cakes mingled with oil, of fine flour soaked. ^13With cakes of leavened bread he shall offer his oblation with the sacrifice of his peace-offerings for thanksgiving. ^14And of it he shall offer one out of each oblation for a heave-offering unto Jehovah; it shall be the priest's that sprinkleth the blood of the peace-offerings.

^15And the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace-offerings for thanksgiving shall be eaten on the day of his oblation; he shall not leave any of it until the morning. ^16But if the sacrifice of his oblation be a vow, or a freewill-offering, it shall be eaten on the day that he offereth his sacrifice; and on the morrow that which remaineth of it shall be eaten: ^17but that which remaineth of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day shall be burnt with fire. ^18And if any of the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace-offerings be eaten on the third day, it shall not be accepted, neither shall it be imputed unto him that offereth it: it shall be an abomination, and the soul that eateth of it shall bear his iniquity.

^19And the flesh that toucheth any unclean thing shall not be eaten; it shall be burnt with fire. And as for the flesh, every one that is clean shall eat thereof: ^20but the soul that eateth of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace-offerings, that pertain unto Jehovah, having his uncleanness upon him, that soul shall be cut off from his people. ^21And when any one shall touch any unclean thing, the uncleanness of man, or an unclean beast, or any unclean abomination, and eat of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace-offerings, which pertain unto Jehovah, that soul shall be cut off from his people.

^22And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^23Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, Ye shall eat no fat, of ox, or sheep, or goat. ^24And the fat of that which dieth of itself, and the fat of that which is torn of beasts, may be used for any other service; but ye shall in no wise eat of it. ^25For whosoever eateth the fat of the beast, of which men offer an offering made by fire unto Jehovah, even the soul that eateth it shall be cut off from his people. ^26And ye shall eat no manner of blood, whether it be of bird or of beast, in any of your dwellings. ^27Whosoever it be that eateth any blood, that soul shall be cut off from his people.

^28And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^29Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, He that offereth the sacrifice of his peace-offerings unto Jehovah shall bring his oblation unto Jehovah out of the sacrifice of his peace-offerings: ^30his own hands shall bring the offerings of Jehovah made by fire; the fat with the breast shall he bring, that the breast may be waved for a wave-offering before Jehovah. ^31And the priest shall burn the fat upon the altar; but the breast shall be Aaron's and his sons'. ^32And the right thigh shall ye give unto the priest for a heave-offering out of the sacrifices of your peace-offerings. ^33He among the sons of Aaron that offereth the blood of the peace-offerings, and the fat, shall have the right thigh for a portion. ^34For the wave-breast and the heave-thigh have I taken of the children of Israel out of the sacrifices of their peace-offerings, and have given them unto Aaron the priest and unto his sons as their portion for ever from the children of Israel.

^35This is the anointing-portion of Aaron, and the anointing-portion of his sons, out of the offerings of Jehovah made by fire, in the day when he presented them to minister unto Jehovah in the priest's office; ^36which Jehovah commanded to be given them of the children of Israel, in the day that he anointed them. It is their portion for ever throughout their generations.

^37This is the law of the burnt-offering, of the meal-offering, and of the sin-offering, and of the trespass-offering, and of the consecration, and of the sacrifice of peace-offerings; ^38which Jehovah commanded Moses in mount Sinai, in the day that he commanded the children of Israel to offer their oblations unto Jehovah, in the wilderness of Sinai.

Leviticus 8

8

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Take Aaron and his sons with him, and the garments, and the anointing oil, and the bullock of the sin-offering, and the two rams, and the basket of unleavened bread; ^3and assemble thou all the congregation at the door of the tent of meeting. ^4And Moses did as Jehovah commanded him; and the congregation was assembled at the door of the tent of meeting. ^5And Moses said unto the congregation, This is the thing which Jehovah hath commanded to be done.

^6And Moses brought Aaron and his sons, and washed them with water. ^7And he put upon him the coat, and girded him with the girdle, and clothed him with the robe, and put the ephod upon him, and he girded him with the skilfully woven band of the ephod, and bound it unto him therewith. ^8And he placed the breastplate upon him: and in the breastplate he put the Urim and the Thummim. ^9And he set the mitre upon his head; and upon the mitre, in front, did he set the golden plate, the holy crown; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^10And Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle and all that was therein, and sanctified them. ^11And he sprinkled thereof upon the altar seven times, and anointed the altar and all its vessels, and the laver and its base, to sanctify them. ^12And he poured of the anointing oil upon Aaron's head, and anointed him, to sanctify him. ^13And Moses brought Aaron's sons, and clothed them with coats, and girded them with girdles, and bound head-tires upon them; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^14And he brought the bullock of the sin-offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the bullock of the sin-offering. ^15And he slew it; and Moses took the blood, and put it upon the horns of the altar round about with his finger, and purified the altar, and poured out the blood at the base of the altar, and sanctified it, to make atonement for it. ^16And he took all the fat that was upon the inwards, and the caul of the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat; and Moses burned it upon the altar. ^17But the bullock, and its skin, and its flesh, and its dung, he burnt with fire without the camp; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^18And he presented the ram of the burnt-offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram. ^19And he killed it; and Moses sprinkled the blood upon the altar round about. ^20And he cut the ram into its pieces; and Moses burnt the head, and the pieces, and the fat. ^21And he washed the inwards and the legs with water; and Moses burnt the whole ram upon the altar: it was a burnt-offering for a sweet savor: it was an offering made by fire unto Jehovah; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^22And he presented the other ram, the ram of consecration: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram. ^23And he slew it; and Moses took of the blood thereof, and put it upon the tip of Aaron's right ear, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot. ^24And he brought Aaron's sons; and Moses put of the blood upon the tip of their right ear, and upon the thumb of their right hand, and upon the great toe of their right foot: and Moses sprinkled the blood upon the altar round about. ^25And he took the fat, and the fat tail, and all the fat that was upon the inwards, and the caul of the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat, and the right thigh: ^26and out of the basket of unleavened bread, that was before Jehovah, he took one unleavened cake, and one cake of oiled bread, and one wafer, and placed them on the fat, and upon the right thigh: ^27and he put the whole upon the hands of Aaron, and upon the hands of his sons, and waved them for a wave-offering before Jehovah. ^28And Moses took them from off their hands, and burnt them on the altar upon the burnt-offering: they were a consecration for a sweet savor: it was an offering made by fire unto Jehovah. ^29And Moses took the breast, and waved it for a wave-offering before Jehovah: it was Moses' portion of the ram of consecration; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^30And Moses took of the anointing oil, and of the blood which was upon the altar, and sprinkled it upon Aaron, upon his garments, and upon his sons, and upon his sons' garments with him, and sanctified Aaron, his garments, and his sons, and his sons' garments with him.

^31And Moses said unto Aaron and to his sons, Boil the flesh at the door of the tent of meeting: and there eat it and the bread that is in the basket of consecration, as I commanded, saying, Aaron and his sons shall eat it. ^32And that which remaineth of the flesh and of the bread shall ye burn with fire. ^33And ye shall not go out from the door of the tent of meeting seven days, until the days of your consecration be fulfilled: for he shall consecrate you seven days. ^34As hath been done this day, so Jehovah hath commanded to do, to make atonement for you. ^35And at the door of the tent of meeting shall ye abide day and night seven days, and keep the charge of Jehovah, that ye die not: for so I am commanded. ^36And Aaron and his sons did all the things which Jehovah commanded by Moses.

Leviticus 9

9

^1And it came to pass on the eighth day, that Moses called Aaron and his sons, and the elders of Israel; ^2and he said unto Aaron, Take thee a calf of the herd for a sin-offering, and a ram for a burnt-offering, without blemish, and offer them before Jehovah. ^3And unto the children of Israel thou shalt speak, saying, Take ye a he-goat for a sin-offering; and a calf and a lamb, both a year old, without blemish, for a burnt-offering; ^4and an ox and a ram for peace-offerings, to sacrifice before Jehovah; and a meal-offering mingled with oil: for to-day Jehovah appeareth unto you. ^5And they brought that which Moses commanded before the tent of meeting: and all the congregation drew near and stood before Jehovah. ^6And Moses said, This is the thing which Jehovah commanded that ye should do: and the glory of Jehovah shall appear unto you. ^7And Moses said unto Aaron, Draw near unto the altar, and offer thy sin-offering, and thy burnt-offering, and make atonement for thyself, and for the people; and offer the oblation of the people, and make atonement for them; as Jehovah commanded.

^8So Aaron drew near unto the altar, and slew the calf of the sin-offering, which was for himself. ^9And the sons of Aaron presented the blood unto him; and he dipped his finger in the blood, and put it upon the horns of the altar, and poured out the blood at the base of the altar: ^10but the fat, and the kidneys, and the caul from the liver of the sin-offering, he burnt upon the altar; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^11And the flesh and the skin he burnt with fire without the camp.

^12And he slew the burnt-offering; and Aaron's sons delivered unto him the blood, and he sprinkled it upon the altar round about. ^13And they delivered the burnt-offering unto him, piece by piece, and the head: and he burnt them upon the altar. ^14And he washed the inwards and the legs, and burnt them upon the burnt-offering on the altar.

^15And he presented the people's oblation, and took the goat of the sin-offering which was for the people, and slew it, and offered it for sin, as the first. ^16And he presented the burnt-offering, and offered it according to the ordinance. ^17And he presented the meal-offering, and filled his hand therefrom, and burnt it upon the altar, besides the burnt-offering of the morning.

^18He slew also the ox and the ram, the sacrifice of peace-offerings, which was for the people: and Aaron's sons delivered unto him the blood, which he sprinkled upon the altar round about, ^19and the fat of the ox and of the ram, the fat tail, and that which covereth the inwards, and the kidneys, and the caul of the liver: ^20and they put the fat upon the breasts, and he burnt the fat upon the altar: ^21and the breasts and the right thigh Aaron waved for a wave-offering before Jehovah; as Moses commanded.

^22And Aaron lifted up his hands toward the people, and blessed them; and he came down from offering the sin-offering, and the burnt-offering, and the peace-offerings. ^23And Moses and Aaron went into the tent of meeting, and came out, and blessed the people: and the glory of Jehovah appeared unto all the people. ^24And there came forth fire from before Jehovah, and consumed upon the altar the burnt-offering and the fat: and when all the people saw it, they shouted, and fell on their faces.

Leviticus 10

10

^1And Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, took each of them his censer, and put fire therein, and laid incense thereon, and offered strange fire before Jehovah, which he had not commanded them. ^2And there came forth fire from before Jehovah, and devoured them, and they died before Jehovah. ^3Then Moses said unto Aaron, This is it that Jehovah spake, saying, I will be sanctified in them that come nigh me, and before all the people I will be glorified. And Aaron held his peace. ^4And Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said unto them, Draw near, carry your brethren from before the sanctuary out of the camp. ^5So they drew near, and carried them in their coats out of the camp, as Moses had said. ^6And Moses said unto Aaron, and unto Eleazar and unto Ithamar, his sons, Let not the hair of your heads go loose, neither rend your clothes; that ye die not, and that he be not wroth with all the congregation: but let your brethren, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning which Jehovah hath kindled. ^7And ye shall not go out from the door of the tent of meeting, lest ye die; for the anointing oil of Jehovah is upon you. And they did according to the word of Moses.

^8And Jehovah spake unto Aaron, saying, ^9Drink no wine nor strong drink, thou, nor thy sons with thee, when ye go into the tent of meeting, that ye die not: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations: ^10and that ye may make a distinction between the holy and the common, and between the unclean and the clean; ^11and that ye may teach the children of Israel all the statutes which Jehovah hath spoken unto them by Moses.

^12And Moses spake unto Aaron, and unto Eleazar and unto Ithamar, his sons that were left, Take the meal-offering that remaineth of the offerings of Jehovah made by fire, and eat it without leaven beside the altar; for it is most holy; ^13and ye shall eat it in a holy place, because it is thy portion, and thy sons' portion, of the offerings of Jehovah made by fire: for so I am commanded. ^14And the wave-breast and the heave-thigh shall ye eat in a clean place, thou, and thy sons, and thy daughters with thee: for they are given as thy portion, and thy sons' portion, out of the sacrifices of the peace-offerings of the children of Israel. ^15The heave-thigh and the wave-breast shall they bring with the offerings made by fire of the fat, to wave it for a wave-offering before Jehovah: and it shall be thine, and thy sons' with thee, as a portion for ever; as Jehovah hath commanded.

^16And Moses diligently sought the goat of the sin-offering, and, behold, it was burnt: and he was angry with Eleazar and with Ithamar, the sons of Aaron that were left, saying, ^17Wherefore have ye not eaten the sin-offering in the place of the sanctuary, seeing it is most holy, and he hath given it you to bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make atonement for them before Jehovah? ^18Behold, the blood of it was not brought into the sanctuary within: ye should certainly have eaten it in the sanctuary, as I commanded. ^19And Aaron spake unto Moses, Behold, this day have they offered their sin-offering and their burnt-offering before Jehovah; and there have befallen me such things as these: and if I had eaten the sin-offering to-day, would it have been well-pleasing in the sight of Jehovah? ^20And when Moses heard that, it was well-pleasing in his sight.

Leviticus 11

11

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses and to Aaron, saying unto them, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, These are the living things which ye may eat among all the beasts that are on the earth. ^3Whatsoever parteth the hoof, and is clovenfooted, and cheweth the cud, among the beasts, that may ye eat. ^4Nevertheless these shall ye not eat of them that chew the cud, or of them that part the hoof: the camel, because he cheweth the cud but parteth not the hoof, he is unclean unto you. ^5And the coney, because he cheweth the cud but parteth not the hoof, he is unclean unto you. ^6And the hare, because she cheweth the cud but parteth not the hoof, she is unclean unto you. ^7And the swine, because he parteth the hoof, and is clovenfooted, but cheweth not the cud, he is unclean unto you. ^8Of their flesh ye shall not eat, and their carcasses ye shall not touch; they are unclean unto you.

^9These may ye eat of all that are in the waters: whatsoever hath fins and scales in the waters, in the seas, and in the rivers, that may ye eat. ^10And all that have not fins and scales in the seas, and in the rivers, of all that move in the waters, and of all the living creatures that are in the waters, they are an abomination unto you, ^11and they shall be an abomination unto you; ye shall not eat of their flesh, and their carcasses ye shall have in abomination. ^12Whatsoever hath no fins nor scales in the waters, that is an abomination unto you.

^13And these ye shall have in abomination among the birds; they shall not be eaten, they are an abomination: the eagle, and the gier-eagle, and the ospray, ^14and the kite, and the falcon after its kind, ^15every raven after its kind, ^16and the ostrich, and the night-hawk, and the seamew, and the hawk after its kind, ^17and the little owl, and the cormorant, and the great owl, ^18and the horned owl, and the pelican, and the vulture, ^19and the stork, the heron after its kind, and the hoopoe, and the bat.

^20All winged creeping things that go upon all fours are an abomination unto you. ^21Yet these may ye eat of all winged creeping things that go upon all fours, which have legs above their feet, wherewith to leap upon the earth. ^22Even these of them ye may eat: the locust after its kind, and the bald locust after its kind, and the cricket after its kind, and the grasshopper after its kind. ^23But all winged creeping things, which have four feet, are an abomination unto you.

^24And by these ye shall become unclean: whosoever toucheth the carcass of them shall be unclean until the even; ^25And whosoever beareth aught of the carcass of them shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even. ^26Every beast which parteth the hoof, and is not clovenfooted, nor cheweth the cud, is unclean unto you: every one that toucheth them shall be unclean. ^27And whatsoever goeth upon its paws, among all beasts that go on all fours, they are unclean unto you: whoso toucheth their carcass shall be unclean until the even. ^28And he that beareth the carcass of them shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: they are unclean unto you.

^29And these are they which are unclean unto you among the creeping things that creep upon the earth: the weasel, and the mouse, and the great lizard after its kind, ^30and the gecko, and the land-crocodile, and the lizard, and the sand-lizard, and the chameleon. ^31These are they which are unclean to you among all that creep: whosoever doth touch them, when they are dead, shall be unclean until the even. ^32And upon whatsoever any of them, when they are dead, doth fall, it shall be unclean; whether it be any vessel of wood, or raiment, or skin, or sack, whatsoever vessel it be, wherewith any work is done, it must be put into water, and it shall be unclean until the even; then shall it be clean. ^33And every earthen vessel, whereinto any of them falleth, whatsoever is in it shall be unclean, and it ye shall break. ^34All food therein which may be eaten, that on which water cometh, shall be unclean; and all drink that may be drunk in every such vessel shall be unclean. ^35And every thing whereupon any part of their carcass falleth shall be unclean; whether oven, or range for pots, it shall be broken in pieces: they are unclean, and shall be unclean unto you. ^36Nevertheless a fountain or a pit wherein is a gathering of water shall be clean: but that which toucheth their carcass shall be unclean. ^37And if aught of their carcass fall upon any sowing seed which is to be sown, it is clean. ^38But if water be put upon the seed, and aught of their carcass fall thereon, it is unclean unto you.

^39And if any beast, of which ye may eat, die; he that toucheth the carcass thereof shall be unclean until the even. ^40And he that eateth of the carcass of it shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: he also that beareth the carcass of it shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even.

^41And every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth is an abomination; it shall not be eaten. ^42Whatsoever goeth upon the belly, and whatsoever goeth upon all fours, or whatsoever hath many feet, even all creeping things that creep upon the earth, them ye shall not eat; for they are an abomination. ^43Ye shall not make yourselves abominable with any creeping thing that creepeth, neither shall ye make yourselves unclean with them, that ye should be defiled thereby. ^44For I am Jehovah your God: sanctify yourselves therefore, and be ye holy; for I am holy: neither shall ye defile yourselves with any manner of creeping thing that moveth upon the earth. ^45For I am Jehovah that brought you up out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: ye shall therefore be holy, for I am holy.

^46This is the law of the beast, and of the bird, and of every living creature that moveth in the waters, and of every creature that creepeth upon the earth; ^47to make a distinction between the unclean and the clean, and between the living thing that may be eaten and the living thing that may not be eaten.

Leviticus 13

13

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^2When a man shall have in the skin of his flesh a rising, or a scab, or a bright spot, and it become in the skin of his flesh the plague of leprosy, then he shall be brought unto Aaron the priest, or unto one of his sons the priests: ^3and the priest shall look on the plague in the skin of the flesh: and if the hair in the plague be turned white, and the appearance of the plague be deeper than the skin of his flesh, it is the plague of leprosy; and the priest shall look on him, and pronounce him unclean. ^4And if the bright spot be white in the skin of his flesh, and the appearance thereof be not deeper than the skin, and the hair thereof be not turned white, then the priest shall shut up him that hath the plague seven days: ^5and the priest shall look on him the seventh day: and, behold, if in his eyes the plague be at a stay, and the plague be not spread in the skin, then the priest shall shut him up seven days more: ^6and the priest shall look on him again the seventh day; and, behold, if the plague be dim, and the plague be not spread in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean: it is a scab: and he shall wash his clothes, and be clean. ^7But if the scab spread abroad in the skin, after that he hath showed himself to the priest for his cleansing, he shall show himself to the priest again: ^8and the priest shall look; and, behold, if the scab be spread in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is leprosy.

^9When the plague of leprosy is in a man, then he shall be brought unto the priest; ^10and the priest shall look; and, behold, if there be a white rising in the skin, and it have turned the hair white, and there be quick raw flesh in the rising, ^11it is an old leprosy in the skin of his flesh, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean: he shall not shut him up, for he is unclean. ^12And if the leprosy break out abroad in the skin, and the leprosy cover all the skin of him that hath the plague from his head even to his feet, as far as appeareth to the priest; ^13then the priest shall look; and, behold, if the leprosy have covered all his flesh, he shall pronounce him clean that hath the plague: it is all turned white: he is clean. ^14But whensoever raw flesh appeareth in him, he shall be unclean. ^15And the priest shall look on the raw flesh, and pronounce him unclean: the raw flesh is unclean: it is leprosy. ^16Or if the raw flesh turn again, and be changed unto white, then he shall come unto the priest; ^17and the priest shall look on him; and, behold, if the plague be turned into white, then the priest shall pronounce him clean that hath the plague: he is clean.

^18And when the flesh hath in the skin thereof a boil, and it is healed, ^19and in the place of the boil there is a white rising, or a bright spot, reddish-white, then is shall be showed to the priest; ^20and the priest shall look; and, behold, if the appearance thereof be lower than the skin, and the hair thereof be turned white, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is the plague of leprosy, it hath broken out in the boil. ^21But if the priest look on it, and, behold, there be no white hairs therein, and it be not lower than the skin, but be dim; then the priest shall shut him up seven days: ^22And if it spread abroad in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a plague. ^23But if the bright spot stay in its place, and be not spread, it is the scar of the boil; and the priest shall pronounce him clean.

^24Or when the flesh hath in the skin thereof a burning by fire, and the quick flesh of the burning become a bright spot, reddish-white, or white; ^25then the priest shall look upon it; and, behold, if the hair in the bright spot be turned white, and the appearance thereof be deeper than the skin; it is leprosy, it hath broken out in the burning: and the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is the plague of leprosy. ^26But if the priest look on it, and, behold, there be no white hair in the bright spot, and it be no lower than the skin, but be dim; then the priest shall shut him up seven days: ^27and the priest shall look upon him the seventh day: if it spread abroad in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is the plague of leprosy. ^28And if the bright spot stay in its place, and be not spread in the skin, but be dim; it is the rising of the burning, and the priest shall pronounce him clean: for it is the scar of the burning.

^29And when a man or woman hath a plague upon the head or upon the beard, ^30then the priest shall look on the plague; and, behold, if the appearance thereof be deeper than the skin, and there be in it yellow thin hair, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a scall, it is leprosy of the head or of the beard. ^31And if the priest look on the plague of the scall, and, behold, the appearance thereof be not deeper than the skin, and there be no black hair in it, then the priest shall shut up him that hath the plague of the scall seven days: ^32And in the seventh day the priest shall look on the plague; and, behold, if the scall be not spread, and there be in it no yellow hair, and the appearance of the scall be not deeper than the skin, ^33then he shall be shaven, but the scall shall he not shave; and the priest shall shut up him that hath the scall seven days more: ^34and in the seventh day the priest shall look on the scall; and, behold, if the scall be not spread in the skin, and the appearance thereof be not deeper than the skin; then the priest shall pronounce him clean: and he shall wash his clothes, and be clean. ^35But if the scall spread abroad in the skin after his cleansing, ^36then the priest shall look on him; and, behold, if the scall be spread in the skin, the priest shall not seek for the yellow hair; he is unclean. ^37But if in his eyes the scall be at a stay, and black hair be grown up therein; the scall is healed, he is clean: and the priest shall pronounce him clean.

^38And when a man or a woman hath in the skin of the flesh bright spots, even white bright spots; ^39then the priest shall look; and, behold, if the bright spots in the skin of their flesh be of a dull white, it is a tetter, it hath broken out in the skin; he is clean.

^40And if a man's hair be fallen off his head, he is bald; yet is he clean. ^41And if his hair be fallen off from the front part of his head, he is forehead bald; yet is he clean. ^42But if there be in the bald head, or the bald forehead, a reddish-white plague; it is leprosy breaking out in his bald head, or his bald forehead. ^43Then the priest shall look upon him; and, behold, if the rising of the plague be reddish-white in his bald head, or in his bald forehead, as the appearance of leprosy in the skin of the flesh; ^44he is a leprous man, he is unclean: the priest shall surely pronounce him unclean; his plague is in his head.

^45And the leper in whom the plague is, his clothes shall be rent, and the hair of his head shall go loose, and he shall cover his upper lip, and shall cry, Unclean, unclean. ^46All the days wherein the plague is in him he shall be unclean; he is unclean: he shall dwell alone; without the camp shall his dwelling be.

^47The garment also that the plague of leprosy is in, whether it be a woollen garment, or a linen garment; ^48whether it be in warp, or woof; of linen, or of woollen; whether in a skin, or in anything made of skin; ^49if the plague be greenish or reddish in the garment, or in the skin, or in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything of skin; it is the plague of leprosy, and shall be showed unto the priest. ^50And the priest shall look upon the plague, and shut up that which hath the plague seven days: ^51and he shall look on the plague on the seventh day: if the plague be spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in the skin, whatever service skin is used for; the plague is a fretting leprosy; it is unclean. ^52And he shall burn the garment, whether the warp or the woof, in woollen or in linen, or anything of skin, wherein the plague is: for it is a fretting leprosy; it shall be burnt in the fire.

^53And if the priest shall look, and, behold, the plague be not spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything of skin; ^54then the priest shall command that they wash the thing wherein the plague is, and he shall shut it up seven days more: ^55and the priest shall look, after that the plague is washed; and, behold, if the plague have not changed its color, and the plague be not spread, it is unclean; thou shalt burn it in the fire: it is a fret, whether the bareness be within or without.

^56And if the priest look, and, behold, the plague be dim after the washing thereof, then he shall rend it out of the garment, or out of the skin, or out of the warp, or out of the woof: ^57and if it appear still in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything of skin, it is breaking out: thou shalt burn that wherein the plague is with fire. ^58And the garment, either the warp, or the woof, or whatsoever thing of skin it be, which thou shalt wash, if the plague be departed from them, then it shall be washed the second time, and shall be clean.

^59This is the law of the plague of leprosy in a garment of woollen or linen, either in the warp, or the woof, or anything of skin, to pronounce it clean, or to pronounce it unclean.

Leviticus 15

15

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses and to Aaron, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When any man hath an issue out of his flesh, because of his issue he is unclean. ^3And this shall be his uncleanness in his issue: whether his flesh run with his issue, or his flesh be stopped from his issue, it is his uncleanness. ^4Every bed whereon he that hath the issue lieth shall be unclean; and everything whereon he sitteth shall be unclean. ^5And whosoever toucheth his bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^6And he that sitteth on anything whereon he that hath the issue sat shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^7And he that toucheth the flesh of him that hath the issue shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^8And if he that hath the issue spit upon him that is clean, then he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^9And what saddle soever he that hath the issue rideth upon shall be unclean. ^10And whosoever toucheth anything that was under him shall be unclean until the even: and he that beareth those things shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^11And whomsoever he that hath the issue toucheth, without having rinsed his hands in water, he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^12And the earthen vessel, which he that hath the issue toucheth, shall be broken; and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water.

^13And when he that hath an issue is cleansed of his issue, then he shall number to himself seven days for his cleansing, and wash his clothes; and he shall bathe his flesh in running water, and shall be clean. ^14And on the eighth day he shall take to him two turtle-doves, or two young pigeons, and come before Jehovah unto the door of the tent of meeting, and give them unto the priest: ^15and the priest shall offer them, the one for a sin-offering, and the other for a burnt-offering; and the priest shall make atonement for him before Jehovah for his issue.

^16And if any man's seed of copulation go out from him, then he shall bathe all his flesh in water, and be unclean until the even. ^17And every garment, and every skin, whereon is the seed of copulation, shall be washed with water, and be unclean until the even. ^18The woman also with whom a man shall lie with seed of copulation, they shall both bathe themselves in water, and be unclean until the even.

^19And if a woman have an issue, and her issue in her flesh be blood, she shall be in her impurity seven days: and whosoever toucheth her shall be unclean until the even. ^20And everything that she lieth upon in her impurity shall be unclean: everything also that she sitteth upon shall be unclean. ^21And whosoever toucheth her bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^22And whosoever toucheth anything that she sitteth upon shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^23And if it be on the bed, or on anything whereon she sitteth, when he toucheth it, he shall be unclean until the even. ^24And if any man lie with her, and her impurity be upon him, he shall be unclean seven days; and every bed whereon he lieth shall be unclean.

^25And if a woman have an issue of her blood many days not in the time of her impurity, or if she have an issue beyond the time of her impurity; all the days of the issue of her uncleanness she shall be as in the days of her impurity: she is unclean. ^26Every bed whereon she lieth all the days of her issue shall be unto her as the bed of her impurity: and everything whereon she sitteth shall be unclean, as the uncleanness of her impurity. ^27And whosoever toucheth those things shall be unclean, and shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^28But if she be cleansed of her issue, then she shall number to herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean. ^29And on the eighth day she shall take unto her two turtle-doves, or two young pigeons, and bring them unto the priest, to the door of the tent of meeting. ^30And the priest shall offer the one for a sin-offering, and the other for a burnt-offering; and the priest shall make atonement for her before Jehovah for the issue of her uncleanness.

^31Thus shall ye separate the children of Israel from their uncleanness, that they die not in their uncleanness, when they defile my tabernacle that is in the midst of them.

^32This is the law of him that hath an issue, and of him whose seed of copulation goeth from him, so that he is unclean thereby; ^33and of her that is sick with her impurity, and of him that hath an issue, of the man, and of the woman, and of him that lieth with her that is unclean.

Leviticus 16

16

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, after the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they drew near before Jehovah, and died; ^2and Jehovah said unto Moses, Speak unto Aaron thy brother, that he come not at all times into the holy place within the veil, before the mercy-seat which is upon the ark; that he die not: for I will appear in the cloud upon the mercy-seat. ^3Herewith shall Aaron come into the holy place: with a young bullock for a sin-offering, and a ram for a burnt-offering. ^4He shall put on the holy linen coat, and he shall have the linen breeches upon his flesh, and shall be girded with the linen girdle, and with the linen mitre shall he be attired: they are the holy garments; and he shall bathe his flesh in water, and put them on. ^5And he shall take of the congregation of the children of Israel two he-goats for a sin-offering, and one ram for a burnt-offering.

^6And Aaron shall present the bullock of the sin-offering, which is for himself, and make atonement for himself, and for his house. ^7And he shall take the two goats, and set them before Jehovah at the door of the tent of meeting. ^8And Aaron shall cast lots upon the two goats; one lot for Jehovah, and the other lot for Azazel. ^9And Aaron shall present the goat upon which the lot fell for Jehovah, and offer him for a sin-offering. ^10But the goat, on which the lot fell for Azazel, shall be set alive before Jehovah, to make atonement for him, to send him away for Azazel into the wilderness.

^11And Aaron shall present the bullock of the sin-offering, which is for himself, and shall make atonement for himself, and for his house, and shall kill the bullock of the sin-offering which is for himself: ^12and he shall take a censer full of coals of fire from off the altar before Jehovah, and his hands full of sweet incense beaten small, and bring it within the veil: ^13and he shall put the incense upon the fire before Jehovah, that the cloud of the incense may cover the mercy-seat that is upon the testimony, that he die not: ^14and he shall take of the blood of the bullock, and sprinkle it with his finger upon the mercy-seat on the east; and before the mercy-seat shall he sprinkle of the blood with his finger seven times.

^15Then shall he kill the goat of the sin-offering, that is for the people, and bring his blood within the veil, and do with his blood as he did with the blood of the bullock, and sprinkle it upon the mercy-seat, and before the mercy-seat: ^16and he shall make atonement for the holy place, because of the uncleannesses of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions, even all their sins: and so shall he do for the tent of meeting, that dwelleth with them in the midst of their uncleannesses. ^17And there shall be no man in the tent of meeting when he goeth in to make atonement in the holy place, until he come out, and have made atonement for himself, and for his household, and for all the assembly of Israel. ^18And he shall go out unto the altar that is before Jehovah, and make atonement for it, and shall take of the blood of the bullock, and of the blood of the goat, and put it upon the horns of the altar round about. ^19And he shall sprinkle of the blood upon it with his finger seven times, and cleanse it, and hallow it from the uncleannesses of the children of Israel.

^20And when he hath made an end of atoning for the holy place, and the tent of meeting, and the altar, he shall present the live goat: ^21and Aaron shall lay both his hands upon the head of the live goat, and confess over him all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and all their transgressions, even all their sins; and he shall put them upon the head of the goat, and shall send him away by the hand of a man that is in readiness into the wilderness: ^22and the goat shall bear upon him all their iniquities unto a solitary land: and he shall let go the goat in the wilderness.

^23And Aaron shall come into the tent of meeting, and shall put off the linen garments, which he put on when he went into the holy place, and shall leave them there: ^24and he shall bathe his flesh in water in a holy place, and put on his garments, and come forth, and offer his burnt-offering and the burnt-offering of the people, and make atonement for himself and for the people. ^25And the fat of the sin-offering shall he burn upon the altar. ^26And he that letteth go the goat for Azazel shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp. ^27And the bullock of the sin-offering, and the goat of the sin-offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the holy place, shall be carried forth without the camp; and they shall burn in the fire their skins, and their flesh, and their dung. ^28And he that burneth them shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp.

^29And it shall be a statute for ever unto you: in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, ye shall afflict your souls, and shall do no manner of work, the home-born, or the stranger that sojourneth among you: ^30for on this day shall atonement be made for you, to cleanse you; from all your sins shall ye be clean before Jehovah. ^31It is a sabbath of solemn rest unto you, and ye shall afflict your souls; it is a statute for ever. ^32And the priest, who shall be anointed and who shall be consecrated to be priest in his father's stead, shall make the atonement, and shall put on the linen garments, even the holy garments: ^33and he shall make atonement for the holy sanctuary; and he shall make atonement for the tent of meeting and for the altar; and he shall make atonement for the priests and for all the people of the assembly. ^34And this shall be an everlasting statute unto you, to make atonement for the children of Israel because of all their sins once in the year. And he did as Jehovah commanded Moses.

Leviticus 17

17

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto Aaron, and unto his sons, and unto all the children of Israel, and say unto them: This is the thing which Jehovah hath commanded, saying, ^3What man soever there be of the house of Israel, that killeth an ox, or lamb, or goat, in the camp, or that killeth it without the camp, ^4and hath not brought it unto the door of the tent of meeting, to offer it as an oblation unto Jehovah before the tabernacle of Jehovah: blood shall be imputed unto that man; he hath shed blood; and that man shall be cut off from among his people: ^5To the end that the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices, which they sacrifice in the open field, even that they may bring them unto Jehovah, unto the door of the tent of meeting, unto the priest, and sacrifice them for sacrifices of peace-offerings unto Jehovah. ^6And the priest shall sprinkle the blood upon the altar of Jehovah at the door of the tent of meeting, and burn the fat for a sweet savor unto Jehovah. ^7And they shall no more sacrifice their sacrifices unto the he-goats, after which they play the harlot. This shall be a statute forever unto them throughout their generations.

^8And thou shalt say unto them, Whatsoever man there be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among them, that offereth a burnt-offering or sacrifice, ^9and bringeth it not unto the door of the tent of meeting, to sacrifice it unto Jehovah; that man shall be cut off from his people.

^10And whatsoever man there be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among them, that eateth any manner of blood, I will set my face against that soul that eateth blood, and will cut him off from among his people. ^11For the life of the flesh is in the blood; and I have given it to you upon the altar to make atonement for your souls: for it is the blood that maketh atonement by reason of the life. ^12Therefore I said unto the children of Israel, No soul of you shall eat blood, neither shall any stranger that sojourneth among you eat blood. ^13And whatsoever man there be of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among them, who taketh in hunting any beast or bird that may be eaten; he shall pour out the blood thereof, and cover it with dust.

^14For as to the life of all flesh, the blood thereof is all one with the life thereof: therefore I said unto the children of Israel, Ye shall eat the blood of no manner of flesh; for the life of all flesh is the blood thereof: whosoever eateth it shall be cut off. ^15And every soul that eateth that which dieth of itself, or that which is torn of beasts, whether he be home-born or a sojourner, he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even: then shall he be clean. ^16But if he wash them not, nor bathe his flesh, then he shall bear his iniquity.

Leviticus 18

18

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, I am Jehovah your God. ^3After the doings of the land of Egypt, wherein ye dwelt, shall ye not do: and after the doings of the land of Canaan, whither I bring you, shall ye not do; neither shall ye walk in their statutes. ^4Mine ordinances shall ye do, and my statutes shall ye keep, to walk therein: I am Jehovah your God. ^5Ye shall therefore keep my statutes, and mine ordinances; which if a man do, he shall live in them: I am Jehovah.

^6None of you shall approach to any that are near of kin to him, to uncover their nakedness: I am Jehovah. ^7The nakedness of thy father, even the nakedness of thy mother, shalt thou not uncover: she is thy mother; thou shalt not uncover her nakedness. ^8The nakedness of thy father's wife shalt thou not uncover: it is thy father's nakedness. ^9The nakedness of thy sister, the daughter of thy father, or the daughter of thy mother, whether born at home, or born abroad, even their nakedness thou shalt not uncover. ^10The nakedness of thy son's daughter, or of thy daughter's daughter, even their nakedness thou shalt not uncover: for theirs is thine own nakedness. ^11The nakedness of thy father's wife's daughter, begotten of thy father, she is thy sister, thou shalt not uncover her nakedness. ^12Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy father's sister: she is thy father's near kinswoman. ^13Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy mother's sister: for she is thy mother's near kinswoman. ^14Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy father's brother, thou shalt not approach to his wife: she is thine aunt. ^15Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy daughter-in-law: she is thy son's wife; thou shalt not uncover her nakedness. ^16Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy brother's wife: it is thy brother's nakedness. ^17Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of a woman and her daughter; thou shalt not take her son's daughter, or her daughter's daughter, to uncover her nakedness; they are near kinswomen: it is wickedness. ^18And thou shalt not take a wife to her sister, to be a rival to her, to uncover her nakedness, besides the other in her life-time.

^19And thou shalt not approach unto a woman to uncover her nakedness, as long as she is impure by her uncleanness. ^20And thou shalt not lie carnally with thy neighbor's wife, to defile thyself with her. ^21And thou shalt not give any of thy seed to make them pass through the fire to Molech; neither shalt thou profane the name of thy God: I am Jehovah. ^22Thou shalt not lie with mankind, as with womankind: it is abomination. ^23And thou shalt not lie with any beast to defile thyself therewith; neither shall any woman stand before a beast, to lie down thereto: it is confusion.

^24Defile not ye yourselves in any of these things: for in all these the nations are defiled which I cast out from before you; ^25And the land is defiled: therefore I do visit the iniquity thereof upon it, and the land vomiteth out her inhabitants. ^26Ye therefore shall keep my statutes and mine ordinances, and shall not do any of these abominations; neither the home-born, nor the stranger that sojourneth among you; ^27(for all these abominations have the men of the land done, that were before you, and the land is defiled); ^28that the land vomit not you out also, when ye defile it, as it vomited out the nation that was before you. ^29For whosoever shall do any of these abominations, even the souls that do them shall be cut off from among their people. ^30Therefore shall ye keep my charge, that ye practise not any of these abominable customs, which were practised before you, and that ye defile not yourselves therein: I am Jehovah your God.

Leviticus 19

19

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, and say unto them, Ye shall be holy; for I Jehovah your God am holy. ^3Ye shall fear every man his mother, and his father; and ye shall keep my sabbaths: I am Jehovah your God. ^4Turn ye not unto idols, nor make to yourselves molten gods: I am Jehovah your God.

^5And when ye offer a sacrifice of peace-offerings unto Jehovah, ye shall offer it that ye may be accepted. ^6It shall be eaten the same day ye offer it, and on the morrow: and if aught remain until the third day, it shall be burnt with fire. ^7And if it be eaten at all on the third day, it is an abomination; it shall not be accepted: ^8but every one that eateth it shall bear his iniquity, because he hath profaned the holy thing of Jehovah: and that soul shall be cut off from his people.

^9And when ye reap the harvest of your land, thou shalt not wholly reap the corners of thy field, neither shalt thou gather the gleaning of thy harvest. ^10And thou shalt not glean thy vineyard, neither shalt thou gather the fallen fruit of thy vineyard; thou shalt leave them for the poor and for the sojourner: I am Jehovah your God.

^11Ye shall not steal; neither shall ye deal falsely, nor lie one to another. ^12And ye shall not swear by my name falsely, and profane the name of thy God: I am Jehovah.

^13Thou shalt not oppress thy neighbor, nor rob him: the wages of a hired servant shall not abide with thee all night until the morning. ^14Thou shalt not curse the deaf, nor put a stumblingblock before the blind; but thou shalt fear thy God: I am Jehovah.

^15Ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment: thou shalt not respect the person of the poor, nor honor the person of the mighty; but in righteousness shalt thou judge thy neighbor. ^16Thou shalt not go up and down as a talebearer among thy people: neither shalt thou stand against the blood of thy neighbor: I am Jehovah.

^17Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thy heart: thou shalt surely rebuke thy neighbor, and not bear sin because of him. ^18Thou shalt not take vengeance, nor bear any grudge against the children of thy people; but thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself: I am Jehovah.

^19Ye shall keep my statutes. Thou shalt not let thy cattle gender with a diverse kind: thou shalt not sow thy field with two kinds of seed: neither shall there come upon thee a garment of two kinds of stuff mingled together. ^20And whosoever lieth carnally with a woman, that is a bondmaid, betrothed to a husband, and not at all redeemed, nor freedom given her; they shall be punished; they shall not be put to death, because she was not free. ^21And he shall bring his trespass-offering unto Jehovah, unto the door of the tent of meeting, even a ram for a trespass-offering. ^22And the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass-offering before Jehovah for his sin which he hath sinned: and the sin which he hath sinned shall be forgiven him. ^23And when ye shall come into the land, and shall have planted all manner of trees for food, then ye shall count the fruit thereof as their uncircumcision: three years shall they be as uncircumcised unto you; it shall not be eaten. ^24But in the fourth year all the fruit thereof shall be holy, for giving praise unto Jehovah. ^25And in the fifth year shall ye eat of the fruit thereof, that it may yield unto you the increase thereof: I am Jehovah your God.

^26Ye shall not eat anything with the blood: neither shall ye use enchantments, nor practise augury. ^27Ye shall not round the corners of your heads, neither shalt thou mar the corners of thy beard. ^28Ye shall not make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor print any marks upon you: I am Jehovah.

^29Profane not thy daughter, to make her a harlot; lest the land fall to whoredom, and the land become full of wickedness. ^30Ye shall keep my sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary; I am Jehovah.

^31Turn ye not unto them that have familiar spirits, nor unto the wizards; seek them not out, to be defiled by them: I am Jehovah your God.

^32Thou shalt rise up before the hoary head, and honor the face of the old man, and thou shalt fear thy God: I am Jehovah.

^33And if a stranger sojourn with thee in your land, ye shall not do him wrong. ^34The stranger that sojourneth with you shall be unto you as the home-born among you, and thou shalt love him as thyself; for ye were sojourners in the land of Egypt: I am Jehovah your God.

^35Ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment, in measures of length, of weight, or of quantity. ^36Just balances, just weights, a just ephah, and a just hin, shall ye have: I am Jehovah your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt. ^37And ye shall observe all my statutes, and all mine ordinances, and do them: I am Jehovah.

Leviticus 20

20

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Moreover, thou shalt say to the children of Israel, Whosoever he be of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn in Israel, that giveth of his seed unto Molech; he shall surely be put to death: the people of the land shall stone him with stones. ^3I also will set my face against that man, and will cut him off from among his people; because he hath given of his seed unto Molech, to defile my sanctuary, and to profane my holy name. ^4And if the people at the land do at all hide their eyes from that man, when he giveth of his seed unto Molech, and put him not to death; ^5then I will set my face against that man, and against his family, and will cut him off, and all that play the harlot after him, to play the harlot with Molech, from among their people.

^6And the soul that turneth unto them that have familiar spirits, and unto the wizards, to play the harlot after them, I will even set my face against that soul, and will cut him off from among his people. ^7Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be ye holy; for I am Jehovah your God. ^8And ye shall keep my statutes, and do them: I am Jehovah who sanctifieth you. ^9For every one that curseth his father or his mother shall surely be put to death: he hath cursed his father or his mother; his blood shall be upon him.

^10And the man that committeth adultery with another man's wife, even he that committeth adultery with his neighbor's wife, the adulterer and the adulteress shall surely be put to death. ^11And the man that lieth with his father's wife hath uncovered his father's nakedness: both of them shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them. ^12And if a man lie with his daughter-in-law, both of them shall surely be put to death: they have wrought confusion; their blood shall be upon them. ^13And if a man lie with mankind, as with womankind, both of them have committed abomination: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them. ^14And if a man take a wife and her mother, it is wickedness: they shall be burnt with fire, both he and they; that there be no wickedness among you. ^15And if a man lie with a beast, he shall surely be put to death: and ye shall slay the beast. ^16And if a woman approach unto any beast, and lie down thereto, thou shalt kill the woman, and the beast: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them.

^17And if a man shall take his sister, his father's daughter, or his mother's daughter, and see her nakedness, and she see his nakedness; it is a shameful thing; and they shall be cut off in the sight of the children of their people: he hath uncovered his sister's nakedness; he shall bear his iniquity. ^18And if a man shall lie with a woman having her sickness, and shall uncover her nakedness; he hath made naked her fountain, and she hath uncovered the fountain of her blood: and both of them shall be cut off from among their people. ^19And thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy mother's sister, nor of thy father's sister; for he hath made naked his near kin: they shall bear their iniquity. ^20And if a man shall lie with his uncle's wife, he hath uncovered his uncle's nakedness: they shall bear their sin; they shall die childless. ^21And if a man shall take his brother's wife, it is impurity: he hath uncovered his brother's nakedness; they shall be childless.

^22Ye shall therefore keep all my statutes, and all mine ordinances, and do them; that the land, whither I bring you to dwell therein, vomit you not out. ^23And ye shall not walk in the customs of the nation, which I cast out before you: for they did all these things, and therefore I abhorred them. ^24But I have said unto you, Ye shall inherit their land, and I will give it unto you to possess it, a land flowing with milk and honey: I am Jehovah your God, who hath separated you from the peoples. ^25Ye shall therefore make a distinction between the clean beast and the unclean, and between the unclean fowl and the clean: and ye shall not make your souls abominable by beast, or by bird, or by anything wherewith the ground teemeth, which I have separated from you as unclean. ^26And ye shall be holy unto me: for I, Jehovah, am holy, and have set you apart from the peoples, that ye should be mine.

^27A man also or a woman that hath a familiar spirit, or that is a wizard, shall surely be put to death: they shall stone them with stones; their blood shall be upon them.

Leviticus 21

21

^1And Jehovah said unto Moses, Speak unto the priests, the sons of Aaron, and say unto them, There shall none defile himself for the dead among his people; ^2except for his kin, that is near unto him, for his mother, and for his father, and for his son, and for his daughter, and for his brother, ^3and for his sister a virgin, that is near unto him, that hath had no husband; for her may he defile himself. ^4He shall not defile himself, being a chief man among his people, to profane himself. ^5They shall not make baldness upon their head, neither shall they shave off the corner of their beard, nor make any cuttings in their flesh. ^6They shall be holy unto their God, and not profane the name of their God; for the offerings of Jehovah made by fire, the bread of their God, they do offer: therefore they shall be holy. ^7They shall not take a woman that is a harlot, or profane; neither shall they take a woman put away from her husband: for he is holy unto his God. ^8Thou shalt sanctify him therefore; for he offereth the bread of thy God: he shall be holy unto thee: for I Jehovah, who sanctify you, am holy. ^9And the daughter of any priest, if she profane herself by playing the harlot, she profaneth her father: she shall be burnt with fire.

^10And he that is the high priest among his brethren, upon whose head the anointing oil is poured, and that is consecrated to put on the garments, shall not let the hair of his head go loose, nor rend his clothes; ^11neither shall he go in to any dead body, nor defile himself for his father, or for his mother; ^12neither shall he go out of the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his God; for the crown of the anointing oil of his God is upon him: I am Jehovah. ^13And he shall take a wife in her virginity. ^14A widow, or one divorced, or a profane woman, a harlot, these shall he not take: but a virgin of his own people shall he take to wife. ^15And he shall not profane his seed among his people: for I am Jehovah who sanctifieth him.

^16And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^17Speak unto Aaron, saying, Whosoever he be of thy seed throughout their generations that hath a blemish, let him not approach to offer the bread of his God. ^18For whatsoever man he be that hath a blemish, he shall not approach: a blind man, or a lame, or he that hath a flat nose, or anything superfluous, ^19or a man that is broken-footed, or broken-handed, ^20or crook-backed, or a dwarf, or that hath a blemish in his eye, or is scurvy, or scabbed, or hath his stones broken; ^21no man of the seed of Aaron the priest, that hath a blemish, shall come nigh to offer the offerings of Jehovah made by fire: he hath a blemish; he shall not come nigh to offer the bread of his God. ^22He shall eat the bread of his God, both of the most holy, and of the holy: ^23only he shall not go in unto the veil, nor come nigh unto the altar, because he hath a blemish; that he profane not my sanctuaries: for I am Jehovah who sanctifieth them. ^24So Moses spake unto Aaron, and to his sons, and unto all the children of Israel.

Leviticus 22

22

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto Aaron and to his sons, that they separate themselves from the holy things of the children of Israel, which they hallow unto me, and that they profane not my holy name: I am Jehovah. ^3Say unto them, Whosoever he be of all your seed throughout your generations, that approacheth unto the holy things, which the children of Israel hallow unto Jehovah, having his uncleanness upon him, that soul shall be cut off from before me: I am Jehovah. ^4What man soever of the seed of Aaron is a leper, or hath an issue; he shall not eat of the holy things, until he be clean. And whoso toucheth anything that is unclean by the dead, or a man whose seed goeth from him; ^5or whosoever toucheth any creeping thing, whereby he may be made unclean, or a man of whom he may take uncleanness, whatsoever uncleanness he hath; ^6the soul that toucheth any such shall be unclean until the even, and shall not eat of the holy things, unless he bathe his flesh in water. ^7And when the sun is down, he shall be clean; and afterward he shall eat of the holy things, because it is his bread. ^8That which dieth of itself, or is torn of beasts, he shall not eat, to defile himself therewith: I am Jehovah. ^9They shall therefore keep my charge, lest they bear sin for it, and die therein, if they profane it: I am Jehovah who sanctifieth them.

^10There shall no stranger eat of the holy thing: a sojourner of the priest's, or a hired servant, shall not eat of the holy thing. ^11But if a priest buy any soul, the purchase of his money, he shall eat of it; and such as are born in his house, they shall eat of his bread. ^12And if a priest's daughter be married unto a stranger, she shall not eat of the heave-offering of the holy things. ^13But if a priest's daughter be a widow, or divorced, and have no child, and be returned unto her father's house, as in her youth, she shall eat of her father's bread: but there shall no stranger eat thereof. ^14And if a man eat of the holy thing unwittingly, then he shall put the fifth part thereof unto it, and shall give unto the priest the holy thing. ^15And they shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, which they offer unto Jehovah, ^16and so cause them to bear the iniquity that bringeth guilt, when they eat their holy things: for I am Jehovah who sanctifieth them.

^17And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^18Speak unto Aaron, and to his sons, and unto all the children of Israel, and say unto them, Whosoever he be of the house of Israel, or of the sojourners in Israel, that offereth his oblation, whether it be any of their vows, or any of their freewill-offerings, which they offer unto Jehovah for a burnt-offering; ^19that ye may be accepted, ye shall offer a male without blemish, of the bullocks, of the sheep, or of the goats. ^20But whatsoever hath a blemish, that shall ye not offer: for it shall not be acceptable for you. ^21And whosoever offereth a sacrifice of peace-offerings unto Jehovah to accomplish a vow, or for a freewill-offering, of the herd or of the flock, it shall be perfect to be accepted; there shall be no blemish therein. ^22Blind, or broken, or maimed, or having a wen, or scurvy, or scabbed, ye shall not offer these unto Jehovah, nor make an offering by fire of them upon the altar unto Jehovah. ^23Either a bullock or a lamb that hath anything superfluous or lacking in his parts, that mayest thou offer for a freewill-offering; but for a vow it shall not be accepted. ^24That which hath its stones bruised, or crushed, or broken, or cut, ye shall not offer unto Jehovah; neither shall ye do thus in your land. ^25Neither from the hand of a foreigner shall ye offer the bread of your God of any of these; because their corruption is in them, there is a blemish in them: they shall not be accepted for you.

^26And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^27When a bullock, or a sheep, or a goat, is brought forth, then it shall be seven days under the dam; and from the eighth day and thenceforth it shall be accepted for the oblation of an offering made by fire unto Jehovah. ^28And whether it be cow or ewe, ye shall not kill it and its young both in one day. ^29And when ye sacrifice a sacrifice of thanksgiving unto Jehovah, ye shall sacrifice it that ye may be accepted. ^30On the same day it shall be eaten; ye shall leave none of it until the morning: I am Jehovah. ^31Therefore shall ye keep my commandments, and do them: I am Jehovah. ^32And ye shall not profane my holy name; but I will be hallowed among the children of Israel: I am Jehovah who halloweth you, ^33who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am Jehovah.

Leviticus 23

23

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, The set feasts of Jehovah, which ye shall proclaim to be holy convocations, even these are my set feasts. ^3Six days shall work be done: but on the seventh day is a sabbath of solemn rest, a holy convocation; ye shall do no manner of work: it is a sabbath unto Jehovah in all your dwellings.

^4These are the set feasts of Jehovah, even holy convocations, which ye shall proclaim in their appointed season. ^5In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at even, is Jehovah's passover. ^6And on the fifteenth day of the same month is the feast of unleavened bread unto Jehovah: seven days ye shall eat unleavened bread. ^7In the first day ye shall have a holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work. ^8But ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto Jehovah seven days: in the seventh day is a holy convocation; ye shall do no servile work.

^9And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^10Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye are come into the land which I give unto you, and shall reap the harvest thereof, then ye shall bring the sheaf of the first-fruits of your harvest unto the priest: ^11and he shall wave the sheaf before Jehovah, to be accepted for you: on the morrow after the sabbath the priest shall wave it. ^12And in the day when ye wave the sheaf, ye shall offer a he-lamb without blemish a year old for a burnt-offering unto Jehovah. ^13And the meal-offering thereof shall be two tenth parts of an ephah of fine flour mingled with oil, an offering made by fire unto Jehovah for a sweet savor; and the drink-offering thereof shall be of wine, the fourth part of a hin. ^14And ye shall eat neither bread, nor parched grain, nor fresh ears, until this selfsame day, until ye have brought the oblation of your God: it is a statute for ever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.

^15And ye shall count unto you from the morrow after the sabbath, from the day that ye brought the sheaf of the wave-offering; seven sabbaths shall there be complete: ^16even unto the morrow after the seventh sabbath shall ye number fifty days; and ye shall offer a new meal-offering unto Jehovah. ^17Ye shall bring out of your habitations two wave-loaves of two tenth parts of an ephah: they shall be of fine flour, they shall be baken with leaven, for first-fruits unto Jehovah. ^18And ye shall present with the bread seven lambs without blemish a year old, and one young bullock, and two rams: they shall be a burnt-offering unto Jehovah, with their meal-offering, and their drink-offerings, even an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah. ^19And ye shall offer one he-goat for a sin-offering, and two he-lambs a year old for a sacrifice of peace-offerings. ^20And the priest shall wave them with the bread of the first-fruits for a wave-offering before Jehovah, with the two lambs: they shall be holy to Jehovah for the priest. ^21And ye shall make proclamation on the selfsame day; there shall be a holy convocation unto you; ye shall do no servile work: it is a statute for ever in all your dwellings throughout your generations.

^22And when ye reap the harvest of your land, thou shalt not wholly reap the corners of thy field, neither shalt thou gather the gleaning of thy harvest: thou shalt leave them for the poor, and for the sojourner: I am Jehovah your God.

^23And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^24Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, In the seventh month, on the first day of the month, shall be a solemn rest unto you, a memorial of blowing of trumpets, a holy convocation. ^25Ye shall do no servile work; and ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto Jehovah.

^26And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^27Howbeit on the tenth day of this seventh month is the day of atonement: it shall be a holy convocation unto you, and ye shall afflict your souls; and ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto Jehovah. ^28And ye shall do no manner of work in that same day; for it is a day of atonement, to make atonement for you before Jehovah your God. ^29For whatsoever soul it be that shall not be afflicted in that same day; he shall be cut off from his people. ^30And whatsoever soul it be that doeth any manner of work in that same day, that soul will I destroy from among his people. ^31Ye shall do no manner of work: it is a statute for ever throughout your generations in all your dwellings. ^32It shall be unto you a sabbath of solemn rest, and ye shall afflict your souls: in the ninth day of the month at even, from even unto even, shall ye keep your sabbath.

^33And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^34Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, On the fifteenth day of this seventh month is the feast of tabernacles for seven days unto Jehovah. ^35On the first day shall be a holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work. ^36Seven days ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto Jehovah: on the eighth day shall be a holy convocation unto you; and ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto Jehovah: it is a solemn assembly; ye shall do no servile work.

^37These are the set feasts of Jehovah, which ye shall proclaim to be holy convocations, to offer an offering made by fire unto Jehovah, a burnt-offering, and a meal-offering, a sacrifice, and drink-offerings, each on its own day; ^38besides the sabbaths of Jehovah, and besides your gifts, and besides all your vows, and besides all your freewill-offerings, which ye give unto Jehovah.

^39Howbeit on the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when ye have gathered in the fruits of the land, ye shall keep the feast of Jehovah seven days: on the first day shall be a solemn rest, and on the eighth day shall be a solemn rest. ^40And ye shall take you on the first day the fruit of goodly trees, branches of palm-trees, and boughs of thick trees, and willows of the brook; and ye shall rejoice before Jehovah your God seven days. ^41And ye shall keep it a feast unto Jehovah seven days in the year: it is a statute for ever throughout your generations; ye shall keep it in the seventh month. ^42Ye shall dwell in booths seven days; all that are home-born in Israel shall dwell in booths; ^43that your generations may know that I made the children of Israel to dwell in booths, when I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I am Jehovah your God. ^44And Moses declared unto the children of Israel the set feasts of Jehovah.

Leviticus 24

24

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Command the children of Israel, that they bring unto thee pure olive oil beaten for the light, to cause a lamp to burn continually. ^3Without the veil of the testimony, in the tent of meeting, shall Aaron keep it in order from evening to morning before Jehovah continually: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations. ^4He shall keep in order the lamps upon the pure candlestick before Jehovah continually.

^5And thou shalt take fine flour, and bake twelve cakes thereof: two tenth parts of an ephah shall be in one cake. ^6And thou shalt set them in two rows, six on a row, upon the pure table before Jehovah. ^7And thou shalt put pure frankincense upon each row, that it may be to the bread for a memorial, even an offering made by fire unto Jehovah. ^8Every sabbath day he shall set it in order before Jehovah continually; it is on the behalf of the children of Israel, an everlasting covenant. ^9And it shall be for Aaron and his sons; and they shall eat it in a holy place: for it is most holy unto him of the offerings of Jehovah made by fire by a perpetual statute.

^10And the son of an Israelitish woman, whose father was an Egyptian, went out among the children of Israel; and the son of the Israelitish woman and a man of Israel strove together in the camp: ^11and the son of the Israelitish woman blasphemed the Name, and cursed; and they brought him unto Moses. And his mother's name was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan. ^12And they put him in ward, that it might be declared unto them at the mouth of Jehovah.

^13And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^14Bring forth him that hath cursed without the camp; and let all that heard him lay their hands upon his head, and let all the congregation stone him. ^15And thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel, saying, Whosoever curseth his God shall bear his sin. ^16And he that blasphemeth the name of Jehovah, he shall surely be put to death; all the congregation shall certainly stone him: as well the sojourner, as the home-born, when he blasphemeth the name of Jehovah, shall be put to death. ^17And he that smiteth any man mortally shall surely be put to death. ^18And he that smiteth a beast mortally shall make it good, life for life. ^19And if a man cause a blemish in his neighbor; as he hath done, so shall it be done to him: ^20breach for breach, eye for eye, tooth for tooth; as he hath caused a blemish in a man, so shall it be rendered unto him. ^21And he that killeth a beast shall make it good: and he that killeth a man shall be put to death. ^22Ye shall have one manner of law, as well for the sojourner, as for the home-born: for I am Jehovah your God. ^23And Moses spake to the children of Israel; and they brought forth him that had cursed out of the camp, and stoned him with stones. And the children of Israel did as Jehovah commanded Moses.

Leviticus 25

25

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses in mount Sinai, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye come into the land which I give you, then shall the land keep a sabbath unto Jehovah. ^3Six years thou shalt sow thy field, and six years thou shalt prune thy vineyard, and gather in the fruits thereof; ^4but in the seventh year shall be a sabbath of solemn rest for the land, a sabbath unto Jehovah: thou shalt neither sow thy field, nor prune thy vineyard. ^5That which groweth of itself of thy harvest thou shalt not reap, and the grapes of thy undressed vine thou shalt not gather: it shall be a year of solemn rest for the land. ^6And the sabbath of the land shall be for food for you; for thee, and for thy servant and for thy maid, and for thy hired servant and for thy stranger, who sojourn with thee. ^7And for thy cattle, and for the beasts that are in thy land, shall all the increase thereof be for food.

^8And thou shalt number seven sabbaths of years unto thee, seven times seven years; and there shall be unto thee the days of seven sabbaths of years, even forty and nine years. ^9Then shalt thou send abroad the loud trumpet on the tenth day of the seventh month; in the day of atonement shall ye send abroad the trumpet throughout all your land. ^10And ye shall hallow the fiftieth year, and proclaim liberty throughout the land unto all the inhabitants thereof: it shall be a jubilee unto you; and ye shall return every man unto his possession, and ye shall return every man unto his family. ^11A jubilee shall that fiftieth year be unto you: ye shall not sow, neither reap that which groweth of itself in it, nor gather the grapes in it of the undressed vines. ^12For it is a jubilee; it shall be holy unto you: ye shall eat the increase thereof out of the field.

^13In this year of jubilee ye shall return every man unto his possession. ^14And if thou sell aught unto thy neighbor, or buy of thy neighbor's hand, ye shall not wrong one another. ^15According to the number of years after the jubilee thou shalt buy of thy neighbor, and according unto the number of years of the crops he shall sell unto thee. ^16According to the multitude of the years thou shalt increase the price thereof, and according to the fewness of the years thou shalt diminish the price of it; for the number of the crops doth he sell unto thee. ^17And ye shall not wrong one another; but thou shalt fear thy God: for I am Jehovah your God.

^18Wherefore ye shall do my statutes, and keep mine ordinances and do them; and ye shall dwell in the land in safety. ^19And the land shall yield its fruit, and ye shall eat your fill, and dwell therein in safety. ^20And if ye shall say, What shall we eat the seventh year? Behold, we shall not sow, nor gather in our increase; ^21then I will command my blessing upon you in the sixth year, and it shall bring forth fruit for the three years. ^22And ye shall sow the eighth year, and eat of the fruits, the old store; until the ninth year, until its fruits come in, ye shall eat the old store.

^23And the land shall not be sold in perpetuity; for the land is mine: for ye are strangers and sojourners with me. ^24And in all the land of your possession ye shall grant a redemption for the land. ^25If thy brother be waxed poor, and sell some of his possession, then shall his kinsman that is next unto him come, and shall redeem that which his brother hath sold. ^26And if a man have no one to redeem it, and he be waxed rich and find sufficient to redeem it; ^27then let him reckon the years of the sale thereof, and restore the overplus unto the man to whom he sold it; and he shall return unto his possession. ^28But if he be not able to get it back for himself, then that which he hath sold shall remain in the hand of him that hath bought it until the year of jubilee: and in the jubilee it shall go out, and he shall return unto his possession.

^29And if a man sell a dwelling-house in a walled city, then he may redeem it within a whole year after it is sold; for a full year shall he have the right of redemption. ^30And if it be not redeemed within the space of a full year, then the house that is in the walled city shall be made sure in perpetuity to him that bought it, throughout his generations: it shall not go out in the jubilee. ^31But the houses of the villages which have no wall round about them shall be reckoned with the fields of the country: they may be redeemed, and they shall go out in the jubilee. ^32Nevertheless the cities of the Levites, the houses of the cities of their possession, may the Levites redeem at any time. ^33And if one of the Levites redeem, then the house that was sold, and the city of his possession, shall go out in the jubilee; for the houses of the cities of the Levites are their possession among the children of Israel. ^34But the field of the suburbs of their cities may not be sold; for it is their perpetual possession.

^35And if thy brother be waxed poor, and his hand fail with thee; then thou shalt uphold him: as a stranger and a sojourner shall he live with thee. ^36Take thou no interest of him or increase, but fear thy God; that thy brother may live with thee. ^37Thou shalt not give him thy money upon interest, nor give him thy victuals for increase. ^38I am Jehovah your God, who brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, to give you the land of Canaan, and to be your God.

^39And if thy brother be waxed poor with thee, and sell himself unto thee; thou shalt not make him to serve as a bond-servant. ^40As a hired servant, and as a sojourner, he shall be with thee; he shall serve with thee unto the year of jubilee: ^41then shall he go out from thee, he and his children with him, and shall return unto his own family, and unto the possession of his fathers shall he return. ^42For they are my servants, whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: they shall not be sold as bondmen. ^43Thou shalt not rule over him with rigor, but shalt fear thy God. ^44And as for thy bondmen, and thy bondmaids, whom thou shalt have; of the nations that are round about you, of them shall ye buy bondmen and bondmaids. ^45Moreover of the children of the strangers that sojourn among you, of them shall ye buy, and of their families that are with you, which they have begotten in your land: and they shall be your possession. ^46And ye shall make them an inheritance for your children after you, to hold for a possession; of them shall ye take your bondmen for ever: but over your brethren the children of Israel ye shall not rule, one over another, with rigor.

^47And if a stranger or sojourner with thee be waxed rich, and thy brother be waxed poor beside him, and sell himself unto the stranger or sojourner with thee, or to the stock of the stranger's family; ^48after that he is sold he may be redeemed: one of his brethren may redeem him; ^49or his uncle, or his uncle's son, may redeem him, or any that is nigh of kin unto him of his family may redeem him; or if he be waxed rich, he may redeem himself. ^50And he shall reckon with him that bought him from the year that he sold himself to him unto the year of jubilee: and the price of his sale shall be according unto the number of years; according to the time of a hired servant shall he be with him. ^51If there be yet many years, according unto them he shall give back the price of his redemption out of the money that he was bought for. ^52And if there remain but few years unto the year of jubilee, then he shall reckon with him; according unto his years shall he give back the price of his redemption. ^53As a servant hired year by year shall he be with him: he shall not rule with rigor over him in thy sight. ^54And if he be not redeemed by these means, then he shall go out in the year of jubilee, he, and his children with him. ^55For unto me the children of Israel are servants; they are my servants whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: I am Jehovah your God.

Leviticus 26

26

^1Ye shall make you no idols, neither shall ye rear you up a graven image, or a pillar, neither shall ye place any figured stone in your land, to bow down unto it: for I am Jehovah your God. ^2Ye shall keep my sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary: I am Jehovah.

^3If ye walk in my statutes, and keep my commandments, and do them; ^4then I will give your rains in their season, and the land shall yield its increase, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit. ^5And your threshing shall reach unto the vintage, and the vintage shall reach unto the sowing time; and ye shall eat your bread to the full, and dwell in your land safely. ^6And I will give peace in the land, and ye shall lie down, and none shall make you afraid: and I will cause evil beasts to cease out of the land, neither shall the sword go through your land. ^7And ye shall chase your enemies, and they shall fall before you by the sword. ^8And five of you shall chase a hundred, and a hundred of you shall chase ten thousand; and your enemies shall fall before you by the sword. ^9And I will have respect unto you, and make you fruitful, and multiply you, and will establish my covenant with you. ^10And ye shall eat old store long kept, and ye shall bring forth the old because of the new. ^11And I will set my tabernacle among you: and my soul shall not abhor you. ^12And I will walk among you, and will be your God, and ye shall be my people. ^13I am Jehovah your God, who brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, that ye should not be their bondmen; and I have broken the bars of your yoke, and made you go upright.

^14But if ye will not hearken unto me, and will not do all these commandments; ^15and if ye shall reject my statutes, and if your soul abhor mine ordinances, so that ye will not do all my commandments, but break my covenant; ^16I also will do this unto you: I will appoint terror over you, even consumption and fever, that shall consume the eyes, and make the soul to pine away; and ye shall sow your seed in vain, for your enemies shall eat it. ^17And I will set my face against you, and ye shall be smitten before your enemies: they that hate you shall rule over you; and ye shall flee when none pursueth you. ^18And if ye will not yet for these things hearken unto me, then I will chastise you seven times more for your sins. ^19And I will break the pride of your power: and I will make your heaven as iron, and your earth as brass; ^20and your strength shall be spent in vain; for your land shall not yield its increase, neither shall the trees of the land yield their fruit.

^21And if ye walk contrary unto me, and will not hearken unto me, I will bring seven times more plagues upon you according to your sins. ^22And I will send the beast of the field among you, which shall rob you of your children, and destroy your cattle, and make you few in number; and your ways shall become desolate. ^23And if by these things ye will not be reformed unto me, but will walk contrary unto me; ^24then will I also walk contrary unto you; and I will smite you, even I, seven times for your sins. ^25And I will bring a sword upon you, that shall execute the vengeance of the covenant; and ye shall be gathered together within your cities: and I will send the pestilence among you; and ye shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy. ^26When I break your staff of bread, ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall deliver your bread again by weight: and ye shall eat, and not be satisfied.

^27And if ye will not for all this hearken unto me, but walk contrary unto me; ^28then I will walk contrary unto you in wrath; and I also will chastise you seven times for your sins. ^29And ye shall eat the flesh of your sons, and the flesh of your daughters shall ye eat. ^30And I will destroy your high places, and cut down your sun-images, and cast your dead bodies upon the bodies of your idols; and my soul shall abhor you. ^31And I will make your cities a waste, and will bring your sanctuaries unto desolation, and I will not smell the savor of your sweet odors. ^32And I will bring the land into desolation; and your enemies that dwell therein shall be astonished at it. ^33And you will I scatter among the nations, and I will draw out the sword after you: and your land shall be a desolation, and your cities shall be a waste.

^34Then shall the land enjoy its sabbaths, as long as it lieth desolate, and ye are in your enemies' land; even then shall the land rest, and enjoy its sabbaths. ^35As long as it lieth desolate it shall have rest, even the rest which it had not in your sabbaths, when ye dwelt upon it. ^36And as for them that are left of you, I will send a faintness into their heart in the lands of their enemies: and the sound of a driven leaf shall chase them; and they shall flee, as one fleeth from the sword; and they shall fall when none pursueth. ^37And they shall stumble one upon another, as it were before the sword, when none pursueth: and ye shall have no power to stand before your enemies. ^38And ye shall perish among the nations, and the land of your enemies shall eat you up. ^39And they that are left of you shall pine away in their iniquity in your enemies' lands; and also in the iniquities of their fathers shall they pine away with them.

^40And they shall confess their iniquity, and the iniquity of their fathers, in their trespass which they trespassed against me, and also that, because they walked contrary unto me, ^41I also walked contrary unto them, and brought them into the land of their enemies: if then their uncircumcised heart be humbled, and they then accept of the punishment of their iniquity; ^42then will I remember my covenant with Jacob; and also my covenant with Isaac, and also my covenant with Abraham will I remember; and I will remember the land. ^43The land also shall be left by them, and shall enjoy its sabbaths, while it lieth desolate without them: and they shall accept of the punishment of their iniquity; because, even because they rejected mine ordinances, and their soul abhorred my statutes. ^44And yet for all that, when they are in the land of their enemies, I will not reject them, neither will I abhor them, to destroy them utterly, and to break my covenant with them; for I am Jehovah their God; ^45but I will for their sakes remember the covenant of their ancestors, whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt in the sight of the nations, that I might be their God: I am Jehovah.

^46These are the statutes and ordinances and laws, which Jehovah made between him and the children of Israel in mount Sinai by Moses.

Leviticus 27

27

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When a man shall accomplish a vow, the persons shall be for Jehovah by thy estimation. ^3And thy estimation shall be of the male from twenty years old even unto sixty years old, even thy estimation shall be fifty shekels of silver, after the shekel of the sanctuary. ^4And if it be a female, then thy estimation shall be thirty shekels. ^5And if it be from five years old even unto twenty years old, then thy estimation shall be of the male twenty shekels, and for the female ten shekels. ^6And if it be from a month old even unto five years old, then thy estimation shall be of the male five shekels of silver, and for the female thy estimation shall be three shekels of silver. ^7And if it be from sixty years old and upward; if it be a male, then thy estimation shall be fifteen shekels, and for the female ten shekels. ^8But if he be poorer than thy estimation, then he shall be set before the priest, and the priest shall value him; according to the ability of him that vowed shall the priest value him.

^9And if it be a beast, whereof men offer an oblation unto Jehovah, all that any man giveth of such unto Jehovah shall be holy. ^10He shall not alter it, nor change it, a good for a bad, or a bad for a good: and if he shall at all change beast for beast, then both it and that for which it is changed shall be holy. ^11And if it be any unclean beast, of which they do not offer an oblation unto Jehovah, then he shall set the beast before the priest; ^12and the priest shall value it, whether it be good or bad: as thou the priest valuest it, so shall it be. ^13But if he will indeed redeem it, then he shall add the fifth part thereof unto thy estimation.

^14And when a man shall sanctify his house to be holy unto Jehovah, then the priest shall estimate it, whether it be good or bad: as the priest shall estimate it, so shall it stand. ^15And if he that sanctified it will redeem his house, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of thy estimation unto it, and it shall be his.

^16And if a man shall sanctify unto Jehovah part of the field of his possession, then thy estimation shall be according to the sowing thereof: the sowing of a homer of barley shall be valued at fifty shekels of silver. ^17If he sanctify his field from the year of jubilee, according to thy estimation it shall stand. ^18But if he sanctify his field after the jubilee, then the priest shall reckon unto him the money according to the years that remain unto the year of jubilee; and an abatement shall be made from thy estimation. ^19And if he that sanctified the field will indeed redeem it, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of thy estimation unto it, and it shall be assured to him. ^20And if he will not redeem the field, or if he have sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed any more: ^21but the field, when it goeth out in the jubilee, shall be holy unto Jehovah, as a field devoted; the possession thereof shall be the priest's. ^22And if he sanctify unto Jehovah a field which he hath bought, which is not of the field of his possession; ^23then the priest shall reckon unto him the worth of thy estimation unto the year of jubilee: and he shall give thine estimation in that day, as a holy thing unto Jehovah. ^24In the year of jubilee the field shall return unto him of whom it was bought, even to him to whom the possession of the land belongeth. ^25And all thy estimations shall be according to the shekel of the sanctuary: twenty gerahs shall be the shekel.

^26Only the firstling among beasts, which is made a firstling to Jehovah, no man shall sanctify it; whether it be ox or sheep, it is Jehovah's. ^27And if it be of an unclean beast, then he shall ransom it according to thine estimation, and shall add unto it the fifth part thereof: or if it be not redeemed, then it shall be sold according to thy estimation.

^28Notwithstanding, no devoted thing, that a man shall devote unto Jehovah of all that he hath, whether of man or beast, or of the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed: every devoted thing is most holy unto Jehovah. ^29No one devoted, that shall be devoted from among men, shall be ransomed; he shall surely be put to death.

^30And all the tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land, or of the fruit of the tree, is Jehovah's: it is holy unto Jehovah. ^31And if a man will redeem aught of his tithe, he shall add unto it the fifth part thereof. ^32And all the tithe of the herd or the flock, whatsoever passeth under the rod, the tenth shall be holy unto Jehovah. ^33He shall not search whether it be good or bad, neither shall he change it: and if he change it at all, then both it and that for which it is changed shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed.

^34These are the commandments, which Jehovah commanded Moses for the children of Israel in mount Sinai.

Luke 2

2

^1Now it came to pass in those days, there went out a decree from Caesar Augustus, that all the world should be enrolled. ^2This was the first enrolment made when Quirinius was governor of Syria. ^3And all went to enrol themselves, every one to his own city. ^4And Joseph also went up from Galilee, out of the city of Nazareth, into Judaea, to the city of David, which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and family of David; ^5to enrol himself with Mary, who was betrothed to him, being great with child. ^6And it came to pass, while they were there, the days were fulfilled that she should be delivered. ^7And she brought forth her firstborn son; and she wrapped him in swaddling clothes, and laid him in a manger, because there was no room for them in the inn. ^8And there were shepherds in the same country abiding in the field, and keeping watch by night over their flock. ^9And an angel of the Lord stood by them, and the glory of the Lord shone round about them: and they were sore afraid. ^10And the angel said unto them, Be not afraid; for behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy which shall be to all the people: ^11for there is born to you this day in the city of David a Saviour, who is Christ the Lord. ^12And this is the sign unto you: Ye shall find a babe wrapped in swaddling clothes, and lying in a manger. ^13And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host praising God, and saying,

^14Glory to God in the highest,

And on earth peace among men in whom he is well pleased.

^15And it came to pass, when the angels went away from them into heaven, the shepherds said one to another, Let us now go even unto Bethlehem, and see this thing that is come to pass, which the Lord hath made known unto us. ^16And they came with haste, and found both Mary and Joseph, and the babe lying in the manger. ^17And when they saw it, they made known concerning the saying which was spoken to them about this child. ^18And all that heard it wondered at the things which were spoken unto them by the shepherds. ^19But Mary kept all these sayings, pondering them in her heart. ^20And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all the things that they had heard and seen, even as it was spoken unto them. ^21And when eight days were fulfilled for circumcising him, his name was called JESUS, which was so called by the angel before he was conceived in the womb. ^22And when the days of their purification according to the law of Moses were fulfilled, they brought him up to Jerusalem, to present him to the Lord ^23(as it is written in the law of the Lord, Every male that openeth the womb shall be called holy to the Lord), ^24and to offer a sacrifice according to that which is said in the law of the Lord, A pair of turtledoves, or two young pigeons. ^25And behold, there was a man in Jerusalem whose name was Simeon; and this man was righteous and devout, looking for the consolation of Israel: and the Holy Spirit was upon him. ^26And it had been revealed unto him by the Holy Spirit, that he should not see death, before he had seen the Lord's Christ. ^27And he came in the Spirit into the temple: and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, that they might do concerning him after the custom of the law, ^28then he received him into his arms, and blessed God, and said,

^29Now lettest thou thy servant depart, Lord,

According to thy word, in peace;

^30For mine eyes have seen thy salvation,

^31Which thou hast prepared before the face of all peoples;

^32A light for revelation to the Gentiles,

And the glory of thy people Israel.

^33And his father and his mother were marvelling at the things which were spoken concerning him; ^34and Simeon blessed them, and said unto Mary his mother, Behold, this child is set for the falling and the rising of many in Israel; and for a sign which is spoken against; ^35yea and a sword shall pierce through thine own soul; that thoughts out of many hearts may be revealed. ^36And there was one Anna, a prophetess, the daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Asher (she was of a great age, having lived with a husband seven years from her virginity, ^37and she had been a widow even unto fourscore and four years), who departed not from the temple, worshipping with fastings and supplications night and day. ^38And coming up at that very hour she gave thanks unto God, and spake of him to all them that were looking for the redemption of Jerusalem. ^39And when they had accomplished all things that were according to the law of the Lord, they returned into Galilee, to their own city Nazareth. ^40And the child grew, and waxed strong, filled with wisdom: and the grace of God was upon him. ^41And his parents went every year to Jerusalem at the feast of the passover. ^42And when he was twelve years old, they went up after the custom of the feast; ^43and when they had fulfilled the days, as they were returning, the boy Jesus tarried behind in Jerusalem; and his parents knew it not; ^44but supposing him to be in the company, they went a day's journey; and they sought for him among their kinsfolk and acquaintance: ^45and when they found him not, they returned to Jerusalem, seeking for him. ^46And it came to pass, after three days they found him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the teachers, both hearing them, and asking them questions: ^47and all that heard him were amazed at his understanding and his answers. ^48And when they saw him, they were astonished; and his mother said unto him, Son, why hast thou thus dealt with us? behold, thy father and I sought thee sorrowing. ^49And he said unto them, How is it that ye sought me? knew ye not that I must be in my Father's house? ^50And they understood not the saying which he spake unto them. ^51And he went down with them, and came to Nazareth; and he was subject unto them: and his mother kept all these sayings in her heart. ^52And Jesus advanced in wisdom and stature, and in favor with God and men.

Luke 3

3

^1Now in the fifteenth year of the reign of Tiberius Caesar, Pontius Pilate being governor of Judaea, and Herod being tetrarch of Galilee, and his brother Philip tetrarch of the region of Ituraea and Trachonitis, and Lysanias tetrarch of Abilene, ^2in the highpriesthood of Annas and Caiaphas, the word of God came unto John the son of Zacharias in the wilderness. ^3And he came into all the region round about the Jordan, preaching the baptism of repentance unto remission of sins; ^4as it is written in the book of the words of Isaiah the prophet, The voice of one crying in the wilderness, Make ye ready the way of the Lord, Make his paths straight. ^5Every valley shall be filled, And every mountain and hill shall be brought low; And the crooked shall become straight, And the rough ways smooth; ^6And all flesh shall see the salvation of God. ^7He said therefore to the multitudes that went out to be baptized of him, Ye offspring of vipers, who warned you to flee from the wrath to come? ^8Bring forth therefore fruits worthy of repentance, and begin not to say within yourselves, We have Abraham to our father: for I say unto you, that God is able of these stones to raise up children unto Abraham. ^9And even now the axe also lieth at the root of the trees: every tree therefore that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire. ^10And the multitudes asked him, saying, What then must we do? ^11And he answered and said unto them, He that hath two coats, let him impart to him that hath none; and he that hath food, let him do likewise. ^12And there came also publicans to be baptized, and they said unto him, Teacher, what must we do? ^13And he said unto them, Extort no more than that which is appointed you. ^14And soldiers also asked him, saying, And we, what must we do? And he said unto them, Extort from no man by violence, neither accuse any one wrongfully; and be content with your wages. ^15And as the people were in expectation, and all men reasoned in their hearts concerning John, whether haply he were the Christ; ^16John answered, saying unto them all, I indeed baptize you with water; but there cometh he that is mightier than I, the latchet of whose shoes I am not worthy to unloose: he shall baptize you in the Holy Spirit and in fire: ^17whose fan is in his hand, thoroughly to cleanse his threshing-floor, and to gather the wheat into his garner; but the chaff he will burn up with unquenchable fire. ^18With many other exhortations therefore preached he good tidings unto the people; ^19but Herod the tetrarch, being reproved by him for Herodias his brother's wife, and for all the evil things which Herod had done, ^20added this also to them all, that he shut up John in prison. ^21Now it came to pass, when all the people were baptized, that, Jesus also having been baptized, and praying, the heaven was opened, ^22and the Holy Spirit descended in a bodily form, as a dove, upon him, and a voice came out of heaven, Thou art my beloved Son; in thee I am well pleased. ^23And Jesus himself, when he began to teach, was about thirty years of age, being the son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli, ^24the son of Matthat, the son of Levi, the son of Melchi, the son of Jannai, the son of Joseph, ^25the son of Mattathias, the son of Amos, the son of Nahum, the son of Esli, the son of Naggai, ^26the son of Maath, the son of Mattathias, the son of Semein, the son of Josech, the son of Joda, ^27the son of Joanan, the son of Rhesa, the son of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, the son of Neri, ^28the son of Melchi, the son of Addi, the son of Cosam, the son of Elmadam, the son of Er, ^29the son of Jesus, the son of Eliezer, the son of Jorim, the son of Matthat, the son of Levi, ^30the son of Symeon, the son of Judas, the son of Joseph, the son of Jonam, the son of Eliakim, ^31the son of Melea, the son of Menna, the son of Mattatha, the son of Nathan, the son of David, ^32the son of Jesse, the son of Obed, the son of Boaz, the son of Salmon, the son of Nahshon, ^33the son of Amminadab, the son of Arni, the son of Hezron, the son of Perez, the son of Judah, ^34the son of Jacob, the son of Isaac, the son of Abraham, the son of Terah, the son of Nahor, ^35the son of Serug, the son of Reu, the son of Peleg, the son of Eber, the son of Shelah ^36the son of Cainan, the son of Arphaxad, the son of Shem, the son of Noah, the son of Lamech, ^37the son of Methuselah, the son of Enoch, the son of Jared, the son of Mahalaleel, the son of Cainan, ^38the son of Enos, the son of Seth, the son of Adam, the son of God.

Luke 4

4

^1And Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, returned from the Jordan, and was led in the Spirit in the wilderness ^2during forty days, being tempted of the devil. And he did eat nothing in those days: and when they were completed, he hungered. ^3And the devil said unto him, if thou art the Son of God, command this stone that it become bread. ^4And Jesus answered unto him, It is written, Man shall not live by bread alone. ^5And he led him up, and showed him all the kingdoms of the world in a moment of time. ^6And the devil said unto him, To thee will I give all this authority, and the glory of them: for it hath been delivered unto me; and to whomsoever I will I give it. ^7If thou therefore wilt worship before me, it shall all be thine. ^8And Jesus answered and said unto him, It is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve. ^9And he led him to Jerusalem, and set him on the pinnacle of the temple, and said unto him, If thou art the Son of God, cast thyself down from hence: ^10for it is written,

He shall give his angels charge concerning thee, to guard thee:

^11and,

On their hands they shall bear thee up,

Lest haply thou dash thy foot against a stone.

^12And Jesus answering said unto him, It is said, Thou shalt not make trial of the Lord thy God.

^13And when the devil had completed every temptation, he departed from him for a season.

^14And Jesus returned in the power of the Spirit into Galilee: and a fame went out concerning him through all the region round about. ^15And he taught in their synagogues, being glorified of all.

^16And he came to Nazareth, where he had been brought up: and he entered, as his custom was, into the synagogue on the sabbath day, and stood up to read. ^17And there was delivered unto him the book of the prophet Isaiah. And he opened the book, and found the place where it was written,

^18The Spirit of the Lord is upon me,

Because he anointed me to preach good tidings to the poor:

He hath sent me to proclaim release to the captives,

And recovering of sight to the blind,

To set at liberty them that are bruised,

^19To proclaim the acceptable year of the Lord.

^20And he closed the book, and gave it back to the attendant, and sat down: and the eyes of all in the synagogue were fastened on him. ^21And he began to say unto them, To-day hath this span been fulfilled in your ears. ^22And all bare him witness, and wondered at the words of grace which proceeded out of his mouth: and they said, Is not this Joseph's son? ^23And he said unto them, Doubtless ye will say unto me this parable, Physician, heal thyself: whatsoever we have heard done at Capernaum, do also here in thine own country. ^24And he said, Verily I say unto you, No prophet is acceptable in his own country. ^25But of a truth I say unto you, There were many widows in Israel in the days of Elijah, when the heaven was shut up three years and six months, when there came a great famine over all the land; ^26and unto none of them was Elijah sent, but only to Zarephath, in the land of Sidon, unto a woman that was a widow. ^27And there were many lepers in Israel in the time of Elisha the prophet; and none of them was cleansed, but only Naaman the Syrian. ^28And they were all filled with wrath in the synagogue, as they heard these things; ^29and they rose up, and cast him forth out of the city, and led him unto the brow of the hill whereon their city was built, that they might throw him down headlong. ^30But he passing through the midst of them went his way. ^31And he came down to Capernaum, a city of Galilee. And he was teaching them on the sabbath day: ^32and they were astonished at his teaching; for his word was with authority. ^33And in the synagogue there was a man, that had a spirit of an unclean demon; and he cried out with a loud voice, ^34Ah! what have we to do with thee, Jesus thou Nazarene? art thou come to destroy us? I know thee who thou art, the Holy One of God. ^35And Jesus rebuked him, saying, Hold thy peace, and come out of him. And when the demon had thrown him down in the midst, he came out of him, having done him no hurt. ^36And amazement came upon all, and they spake together, one with another, saying, What is this word? for with authority and power he commandeth the unclean spirits, and they come out. ^37And there went forth a rumor concerning him into every place of the region round about. ^38And he rose up from the synagogue, and entered into the house of Simon. And Simon's wife's mother was holden with a great fever; and they besought him for her. ^39And he stood over her, and rebuked the fever; and it left her: and immediately she rose up and ministered unto them. ^40And when the sun was setting, all they that had any sick with divers diseases brought them unto him; and he laid his hands on every one of them, and healed them. ^41And demons also came out from many, crying out, and saying, Thou art the Son of God. And rebuking them, he suffered them not to speak, because they knew that he was the Christ. ^42And when it was day, he came out and went into a desert place: and the multitudes sought after him, and came unto him, and would have stayed him, that he should not go from them. ^43But he said unto them, I must preach the good tidings of the kingdom of God to the other cities also: for therefore was I sent. ^44And he was preaching in the synagogues of Galilee.

Luke 5

5

^1Now it came to pass, while the multitude pressed upon him and heard the word of God, that he was standing by the lake of Gennesaret; ^2and he saw two boats standing by the lake: but the fishermen had gone out of them, and were washing their nets. ^3And he entered into one of the boats, which was Simon's, and asked him to put out a little from the land. And he sat down and taught the multitudes out of the boat. ^4And when he had left speaking, he said unto Simon, Put out into the deep, and let down your nets for a draught. ^5And Simon answered and said, Master, we toiled all night, and took nothing: but at thy word I will let down the nets. ^6And when they had done this, they inclosed a great multitude of fishes; and their nets were breaking; ^7and they beckoned unto their partners in the other boat, that they should come and help them. And they came, and filled both the boats, so that they began to sink. ^8But Simon Peter, when he saw it, fell down at Jesus' knees, saying, Depart from me; for I am a sinful man, O Lord. ^9For he was amazed, and all that were with him, at the draught of the fishes which they had taken; ^10and so were also James and John, sons of Zebedee, who were partners with Simon. And Jesus said unto Simon, Fear not; from henceforth thou shalt catch men. ^11And when they had brought their boats to land, they left all, and followed him. ^12And it came to pass, while he was in one of the cities, behold, a man full of leprosy: and when he saw Jesus, he fell on his face, and besought him, saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean. ^13And he stretched forth his hand, and touched him, saying, I will; be thou made clean. And straightway the leprosy departed from him. ^14And he charged him to tell no man: but go thy way, and show thyself to the priest, and offer for thy cleansing, according as Moses commanded, for a testimony unto them. ^15But so much the more went abroad the report concerning him: and great multitudes came together to hear, and to be healed of their infirmities. ^16But he withdrew himself in the deserts, and prayed. ^17And it came to pass on one of those days, that he was teaching; and there were Pharisees and doctors of the law sitting by, who were come out of every village of Galilee and Judaea and Jerusalem: and the power of the Lord was with him to heal. ^18And behold, men bring on a bed a man that was palsied: and they sought to bring him in, and to lay him before him. ^19And not finding by what way they might bring him in because of the multitude, they went up to the housetop, and let him down through the tiles with his couch into the midst before Jesus. ^20And seeing their faith, he said, Man, thy sins are forgiven thee. ^21And the scribes and the Pharisees began to reason, saying, Who is this that speaketh blasphemies? Who can forgive sins, but God alone? ^22But Jesus perceiving their reasonings, answered and said unto them, Why reason ye in your hearts? ^23Which is easier, to say, Thy sins are forgiven thee; or to say, Arise and walk? ^24But that ye may know that the Son of man hath authority on earth to forgive sins (he said unto him that was palsied), I say unto thee, Arise, and take up thy couch, and go unto thy house. ^25And immediately he rose up before them, and took up that whereon he lay, and departed to his house, glorifying God. ^26And amazement took hold on all, and they glorified God; and they were filled with fear, saying, We have seen strange things to-day. ^27And after these things he went forth, and beheld a publican, named Levi, sitting at the place of toll, and said unto him, Follow me. ^28And he forsook all, and rose up and followed him. ^29And Levi made him a great feast in his house: and there was a great multitude of publicans and of others that were sitting at meat with them. ^30And the Pharisees and their scribes murmured against his disciples, saying, Why do ye eat and drink with the publicans and sinners? ^31And Jesus answering said unto them, They that are in health have no need of a physician; but they that are sick. ^32I am not come to call the righteous but sinners to repentance. ^33And they said unto him, The disciples of John fast often, and make supplications; likewise also the disciples of the Pharisees; but thine eat and drink. ^34And Jesus said unto them, Can ye make the sons of the bride-chamber fast, while the bridegroom is with them? ^35But the days will come; and when the bridegroom shall be taken away from them, then will they fast in those days. ^36And he spake also a parable unto them: No man rendeth a piece from a new garment and putteth it upon an old garment; else he will rend the new, and also the piece from the new will not agree with the old. ^37And no man putteth new wine into old wine-skins; else the new wine will burst the skins, and itself will be spilled, and the skins will perish. ^38But new wine must be put into fresh wine-skins. ^39And no man having drunk old wine desireth new; for he saith, The old is good.

Luke 6

6

^1Now it came to pass on a sabbath, that he was going through the grainfields; and his disciples plucked the ears, and did eat, rubbing them in their hands. ^2But certain of the Pharisees said, Why do ye that which it is not lawful to do on the sabbath day? ^3And Jesus answering them said, Have ye not read even this, what David did, when he was hungry, he, and they that were with him; ^4how he entered into the house of God, and took and ate the showbread, and gave also to them that were with him; which it is not lawful to eat save for the priests alone? ^5And he said unto them, The Son of man is lord of the sabbath. ^6And it came to pass on another sabbath, that he entered into the synagogue and taught: and there was a man there, and his right hand was withered. ^7And the scribes and the Pharisees watched him, whether he would heal on the sabbath; that they might find how to accuse him. ^8But he knew their thoughts; and he said to the man that had his hand withered, Rise up, and stand forth in the midst. And he arose and stood forth. ^9And Jesus said unto them, I ask you, Is it lawful on the sabbath to do good, or to do harm? to save a life, or to destroy it? ^10And he looked round about on them all, and said unto him, Stretch forth thy hand. And he did so: and his hand was restored. ^11But they were filled with madness; and communed one with another what they might do to Jesus. ^12And it came to pass in these days, that he went out into the mountain to pray; and he continued all night in prayer to God. ^13And when it was day, he called his disciples; and he chose from them twelve, whom also he named apostles: ^14Simon, whom he also named Peter, and Andrew his brother, and James and John, and Philip and Bartholomew, ^15and Matthew and Thomas, and James the son of Alphaeus, and Simon who was called the Zealot, ^16and Judas the son of James, and Judas Iscariot, who became a traitor; ^17and he came down with them, and stood on a level place, and a great multitude of his disciples, and a great number of the people from all Judaea and Jerusalem, and the sea coast of Tyre and Sidon, who came to hear him, and to be healed of their diseases; ^18and they that were troubled with unclean spirits were healed. ^19And all the multitude sought to touch him; for power came forth from him, and healed them all. ^20And he lifted up his eyes on his disciples, and said, Blessed are ye poor: for yours is the kingdom of God. ^21Blessed are ye that hunger now: for ye shall be filled. Blessed are ye that weep now: for ye shall laugh. ^22Blessed are ye, when men shall hate you, and when they shall separate you from their company, and reproach you, and cast out your name as evil, for the Son of man's sake. ^23Rejoice in that day, and leap for joy: for behold, your reward is great in heaven; for in the same manner did their fathers unto the prophets. ^24But woe unto you that are rich! for ye have received your consolation. ^25Woe unto you, ye that are full now! for ye shall hunger. Woe unto you, ye that laugh now! for ye shall mourn and weep. ^26Woe unto you, when all men shall speak well of you! for in the same manner did their fathers to the false prophets. ^27But I say unto you that hear, Love your enemies, do good to them that hate you, ^28bless them that curse you, pray for them that despitefully use you. ^29To him that smiteth thee on the one cheek offer also the other; and from him that taketh away thy cloak withhold not thy coat also. ^30Give to every one that asketh thee; and of him that taketh away thy goods ask them not again. ^31And as ye would that men should do to you, do ye also to them likewise. ^32And if ye love them that love you, what thank have ye? for even sinners love those that love them. ^33And if ye do good to them that do good to you, what thank have ye? for even sinners do the same. ^34And if ye lend to them of whom ye hope to receive, what thank have ye? even sinners lend to sinners, to receive again as much. ^35But love your enemies, and do them good, and lend, never despairing; and your reward shall be great, and ye shall be sons of the Most High: for he is kind toward the unthankful and evil. ^36Be ye merciful, even as your Father is merciful. ^37And judge not, and ye shall not be judged: and condemn not, and ye shall not be condemned: release, and ye shall be released: ^38give, and it shall be given unto you; good measure, pressed down, shaken together, running over, shall they give into your bosom. For with what measure ye mete it shall be measured to you again. ^39And he spake also a parable unto them, Can the blind guide the blind? shall they not both fall into a pit? ^40The disciple is not above his teacher: but every one when he is perfected shall be as his teacher. ^41And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother's eye, but considerest not the beam that is in thine own eye? ^42Or how canst thou say to thy brother, Brother, let me cast out the mote that is in thine eye, when thou thyself beholdest not the beam that is in thine own eye? Thou hypocrite, cast out first the beam out of thine own eye, and then shalt thou see clearly to cast out the mote that is in thy brother's eye. ^43For there is no good tree that bringeth forth corrupt fruit; nor again a corrupt tree that bringeth forth good fruit. ^44For each tree is known by its own fruit. For of thorns men do not gather figs, nor of a bramble bush gather they grapes. ^45The good man out of the good treasure of his heart bringeth forth that which is good; and the evil man out of the evil treasure bringeth forth that which is evil: for out of the abundance of the heart his mouth speaketh. ^46And why call ye me, Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I say? ^47Every one that cometh unto me, and heareth my words, and doeth them, I will show you to whom he is like: ^48he is like a man building a house, who digged and went deep, and laid a foundation upon the rock: and when a flood arose, the stream brake against that house, and could not shake it: because it had been well builded. ^49But he that heareth, and doeth not, is like a man that built a house upon the earth without a foundation; against which the stream brake, and straightway it fell in; and the ruin of that house was great.

Luke 7

7

^1After he had ended all his sayings in the ears of the people, he entered into Capernaum. ^2And a certain centurion's servant, who was dear unto him, was sick and at the point of death. ^3And when he heard concerning Jesus, he sent unto him elders of the Jews, asking him that he would come and save his servant. ^4And they, when they came to Jesus, besought him earnestly, saying, He is worthy that thou shouldest do this for him; ^5for he loveth our nation, and himself built us our synagogue. ^6And Jesus went with them. And when he was now not far from the house, the centurion sent friends to him, saying unto him, Lord, trouble not thyself; for I am not worthy that thou shouldest come under my roof: ^7wherefore neither thought I myself worthy to come unto thee: but say the word, and my servant shall be healed. ^8For I also am a man set under authority, having under myself soldiers: and I say to this one, Go, and he goeth; and to another, Come, and he cometh; and to my servant, Do this, and he doeth it. ^9And when Jesus heard these things, he marvelled at him, and turned and said unto the multitude that followed him, I say unto you, I have not found so great faith, no, not in Israel. ^10And they that were sent, returning to the house, found the servant whole. ^11And it came to pass soon afterwards, that he went to a city called Nain; and his disciples went with him, and a great multitude. ^12Now when he drew near to the gate of the city, behold, there was carried out one that was dead, the only son of his mother, and she was a widow: and much people of the city was with her. ^13And when the Lord saw her, he had compassion on her, and said unto her, Weep not. ^14And he came nigh and touched the bier: and the bearers stood still. And he said, Young man, I say unto thee, Arise. ^15And he that was dead sat up, and began to speak. And he gave him to his mother. ^16And fear took hold on all: and they glorified God, saying, A great prophet is arisen among us: and, God hath visited his people. ^17And this report went forth concerning him in the whole of Judaea, and all the region round about. ^18And the disciples of John told him of all these things. ^19And John calling unto him two of his disciples sent them to the Lord, saying, Art thou he that cometh, or look we for another? ^20And when the men were come unto him, they said, John the Baptist hath sent us unto thee, saying, Art thou he that cometh, or look we for another? ^21In that hour he cured many of diseases and plagues and evil spirits; and on many that were blind he bestowed sight. ^22And he answered and said unto them, Go and tell John the things which ye have seen and heard; the blind receive their sight, the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, and the deaf hear, the dead are raised up, the poor have good tidings preached to them. ^23And blessed is he, whosoever shall find no occasion of stumbling in me. ^24And when the messengers of John were departed, he began to say unto the multitudes concerning John, What went ye out into the wilderness to behold? a reed shaken with the wind? ^25But what went ye out to see? a man clothed in soft raiment? Behold, they that are gorgeously apparelled, and live delicately, are in kings' courts. ^26But what went ye out to see? a prophet? Yea, I say unto you, and much more than a prophet. ^27This is he of whom it is written,

Behold, I send my messenger before thy face,

Who shall prepare thy way before thee.

^28I say unto you, Among them that are born of women there is none greater than John: yet he that is but little in the kingdom of God is greater than he. ^29And all the people when they heard, and the publicans, justified God, being baptized with the baptism of John. ^30But the Pharisees and the lawyers rejected for themselves the counsel of God, being not baptized of him. ^31Whereunto then shall I liken the men of this generation, and to what are they like? ^32They are like unto children that sit in the marketplace, and call one to another; who say, We piped unto you, and ye did not dance; we wailed, and ye did not weep. ^33For John the Baptist is come eating no bread nor drinking wine; and ye say, He hath a demon. ^34The Son of man is come eating and drinking; and ye say, Behold, a gluttonous man, and a winebibber, a friend of publicans and sinners! ^35And wisdom is justified of all her children. ^36And one of the Pharisees desired him that he would eat with him. And he entered into the Pharisee's house, and sat down to meat. ^37And behold, a woman who was in the city, a sinner; and when she knew that he was sitting at meat in the Pharisee's house, she brought an alabaster cruse of ointment, ^38and standing behind at his feet, weeping, she began to wet his feet with her tears, and wiped them with the hair of her head, and kissed his feet, and anointed them with the ointment. ^39Now when the Pharisee that had bidden him saw it, he spake within himself, saying, This man, if he were a prophet, would have perceived who and what manner of woman this is that toucheth him, that she is a sinner. ^40And Jesus answering said unto him, Simon, I have somewhat to say unto thee. And he saith, Teacher, say on. ^41A certain lender had two debtors: the one owed five hundred shillings, and the other fifty. ^42When they had not wherewith to pay, he forgave them both. Which of them therefore will love him most? ^43Simon answered and said, He, I suppose, to whom he forgave the most. And he said unto him, Thou hast rightly judged. ^44And turning to the woman, he said unto Simon, Seest thou this woman? I entered into thy house, thou gavest me no water for my feet: but she hath wetted my feet with her tears, and wiped them with her hair. ^45Thou gavest me no kiss: but she, since the time I came in, hath not ceased to kiss my feet. ^46My head with oil thou didst not anoint: but she hath anointed my feet with ointment. ^47Wherefore I say unto thee, Her sins, which are many, are forgiven; for she loved much: but to whom little is forgiven, the same loveth little. ^48And he said unto her, Thy sins are forgiven. ^49And they that sat at meat with him began to say within themselves, Who is this that even forgiveth sins? ^50And he said unto the woman, Thy faith hath saved thee; go in peace.

Luke 8

8

^1And it came to pass soon afterwards, that he went about through cities and villages, preaching and bringing the good tidings of the kingdom of God, and with him the twelve, ^2and certain women who had been healed of evil spirits and infirmities: Mary that was called Magdalene, from whom seven demons had gone out, ^3and Joanna the wife of Chuzas Herod's steward, and Susanna, and many others, who ministered unto them of their substance. ^4And when a great multitude came together, and they of every city resorted unto him, he spake by a parable: ^5The sower went forth to sow his seed: and as he sowed, some fell by the way side; and it was trodden under foot, and the birds of the heaven devoured it. ^6And other fell on the rock; and as soon as it grew, it withered away, because it had no moisture. ^7And other fell amidst the thorns; and the thorns grew with it, and choked it. ^8And other fell into the good ground, and grew, and brought forth fruit a hundredfold. As he said these things, he cried, He that hath ears to hear, let him hear. ^9And his disciples asked him what this parable might be. ^10And he said, Unto you it is given to know the mysteries of the kingdom of God: but to the rest in parables; that seeing they may not see, and hearing they may not understand. ^11Now the parable is this: The seed is the word of God. ^12And those by the way side are they that have heard; then cometh the devil, and taketh away the word from their heart, that they may not believe and be saved. ^13And those on the rock are they who, when they have heard, receive the word with joy; and these have no root, who for a while believe, and in time of temptation fall away. ^14And that which fell among the thorns, these are they that have heard, and as they go on their way they are choked with cares and riches and pleasures of this life, and bring no fruit to perfection. ^15And that in the good ground, these are such as in an honest and good heart, having heard the word, hold it fast, and bring forth fruit with patience. ^16And no man, when he hath lighted a lamp, covereth it with a vessel, or putteth it under a bed; but putteth it on a stand, that they that enter in may see the light. ^17For nothing is hid, that shall not be made manifest; nor anything secret, that shall not be known and come to light. ^18Take heed therefore how ye hear: for whosoever hath, to him shall be given; and whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that which he thinketh he hath. ^19And there came to him his mother and brethren, and they could not come at him for the crowd. ^20And it was told him, Thy mother and thy brethren stand without, desiring to see thee. ^21But he answered and said unto them, My mother and my brethren are these that hear the word of God, and do it. ^22Now it came to pass on one of those days, that he entered into a boat, himself and his disciples; and he said unto them, Let us go over unto the other side of the lake: and they launched forth. ^23But as they sailed he fell asleep: and there came down a storm of wind on the lake; and they were filling with water, and were in jeopardy. ^24And they came to him, and awoke him, saying, Master, master, we perish. And he awoke, and rebuked the wind and the raging of the water: and they ceased, and there was a calm. ^25And he said unto them, Where is your faith? And being afraid they marvelled, saying one to another, Who then is this, that he commandeth even the winds and the water, and they obey him? ^26And they arrived at the country of the Gerasenes, which is over against Galilee. ^27And when he was come forth upon the land, there met him a certain man out of the city, who had demons; and for a long time he had worn no clothes, and abode not in any house, but in the tombs. ^28And when he saw Jesus, he cried out, and fell down before him, and with a loud voice said, What have I to do with thee, Jesus, thou Son of the Most High God? I beseech thee, torment me not. ^29For he was commanding the unclean spirit to come out from the man. For oftentimes it had seized him: and he was kept under guard, and bound with chains and fetters; and breaking the bands asunder, he was driven of the demon into the deserts. ^30And Jesus asked him, What is thy name? And he said, Legion; for many demons were entered into him. ^31And they entreated him that he would not command them to depart into the abyss. ^32Now there was there a herd of many swine feeding on the mountain: and they entreated him that he would give them leave to enter into them. And he gave them leave. ^33And the demons came out from the man, and entered into the swine: and the herd rushed down the steep into the lake, and were drowned. ^34And when they that fed them saw what had come to pass, they fled, and told it in the city and in the country. ^35And they went out to see what had come to pass; and they came to Jesus, and found the man, from whom the demons were gone out, sitting, clothed and in his right mind, at the feet of Jesus: and they were afraid. ^36And they that saw it told them how he that was possessed with demons was made whole. ^37And all the people of the country of the Gerasenes round about asked him to depart from them, for they were holden with great fear: and he entered into a boat, and returned. ^38But the man from whom the demons were gone out prayed him that he might be with him: but he sent him away, saying, ^39Return to thy house, and declare how great things God hath done for thee. And he went his way, publishing throughout the whole city how great things Jesus had done for him. ^40And as Jesus returned, the multitude welcomed him; for they were all waiting for him. ^41And behold, there came a man named Jairus, and he was a ruler of the synagogue: and he fell down at Jesus' feet, and besought him to come into his house; ^42for he had an only daughter, about twelve years of age, and she was dying. But as he went the multitudes thronged him. ^43And a woman having an issue of blood twelve years, who had spent all her living upon physicians, and could not be healed of any, ^44came behind him, and touched the border of his garment: and immediately the issue of her blood stanched. ^45And Jesus said, Who is it that touched me? And when all denied, Peter said, and they that were with him, Master, the multitudes press thee and crush thee. ^46But Jesus said, Some one did touch me; for I perceived that power had gone forth from me. ^47And when the woman saw that she was not hid, she came trembling, and falling down before him declared in the presence of all the people for what cause she touched him, and how she was healed immediately. ^48And he said unto her, Daughter, thy faith hath made thee whole; go in peace. ^49While he yet spake, there cometh one from the ruler of the synagogue's house, saying, Thy daughter is dead; trouble not the Teacher. ^50But Jesus hearing it, answered him, Fear not: only believe, and she shall be made whole. ^51And when he came to the house, he suffered not any man to enter in with him, save Peter, and John, and James, and the father of the maiden and her mother. ^52And all were weeping, and bewailing her: but he said, Weep not; for she is not dead, but sleepeth. ^53And they laughed him to scorn, knowing that she was dead. ^54But he, taking her by the hand, called, saying, Maiden, arise. ^55And her spirit returned, and she rose up immediately: and he commanded that something be given her to eat. ^56And her parents were amazed: but he charged them to tell no man what had been done.

Luke 9

9

^1And he called the twelve together, and gave them power and authority over all demons, and to cure diseases. ^2And he sent them forth to preach the kingdom of God, and to heal the sick. ^3And he said unto them, Take nothing for your journey, neither staff, nor wallet, nor bread, nor money; neither have two coats. ^4And into whatsoever house ye enter, there abide, and thence depart. ^5And as many as receive you not, when ye depart from that city, shake off the dust from your feet for a testimony against them. ^6And they departed, and went throughout the villages, preaching the gospel, and healing everywhere. ^7Now Herod the tetrarch heard of all that was done: and he was much perplexed, because that it was said by some, that John was risen from the dead; ^8and by some, that Elijah had appeared; and by others, that one of the old prophets was risen again. ^9And Herod said, John I beheaded: but who is this, about whom I hear such things? And he sought to see him. ^10And the apostles, when they were returned, declared unto him what things they had done. And he took them, and withdrew apart to a city called Bethsaida. ^11But the multitudes perceiving it followed him: and he welcomed them, and spake to them of the kingdom of God, and them that had need of healing he cured. ^12And the day began to wear away; and the twelve came, and said unto him, Send the multitude away, that they may go into the villages and country round about, and lodge, and get provisions: for we are here in a desert place. ^13But he said unto them, Give ye them to eat. And they said, We have no more than five loaves and two fishes; except we should go and buy food for all this people. ^14For they were about five thousand men. And he said unto his disciples, Make them sit down in companies, about fifty each. ^15And they did so, and made them all sit down. ^16And he took the five loaves and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, he blessed them, and brake; and gave to the disciples to set before the multitude. ^17And they ate, and were all filled: and there was taken up that which remained over to them of broken pieces, twelve baskets. ^18And it came to pass, as he was praying apart, the disciples were with him: and he asked them, saying, Who do the multitudes say that I am? ^19And they answering said, John the Baptist; but others say, Elijah; and others, that one of the old prophets is risen again. ^20And he said unto them, But who say ye that I am? And Peter answering said, The Christ of God. ^21But he charged them, and commanded them to tell this to no man; ^22saying, The Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected of the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and the third day be raised up. ^23And he said unto all, If any man would come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross daily, and follow me. ^24For whosoever would save his life shall lose it; but whosoever shall lose his life for my sake, the same shall save it. ^25For what is a man profited, if he gain the whole world, and lose or forfeit his own self? ^26For whosoever shall be ashamed of me and of my words, of him shall the Son of man be ashamed, when he cometh in his own glory, and the glory of the Father, and of the holy angels. ^27But I tell you of a truth, There are some of them that stand here, who shall in no wise taste of death, till they see the kingdom of God. ^28And it came to pass about eight days after these sayings, that he took with him Peter and John and James, and went up into the mountain to pray. ^29And as he was praying, the fashion of his countenance was altered, and his raiment became white and dazzling. ^30And behold, there talked with him two men, who were Moses and Elijah; ^31who appeared in glory, and spake of his decease which he was about to accomplish at Jerusalem. ^32Now Peter and they that were with him were heavy with sleep: but when they were fully awake, they saw his glory, and the two men that stood with him. ^33And it came to pass, as they were parting from him, Peter said unto Jesus, Master, it is good for us to be here: and let us make three tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah: not knowing what he said. ^34And while he said these things, there came a cloud, and overshadowed them: and they feared as they entered into the cloud. ^35And a voice came out of the cloud, saying, This is my Son, my chosen: hear ye him. ^36And when the voice came, Jesus was found alone. And they held their peace, and told no man in those days any of the things which they had seen. ^37And it came to pass, on the next day, when they were come down from the mountain, a great multitude met him. ^38And behold, a man from the multitude cried, saying, Teacher, I beseech thee to look upon my son; for he is mine only child: ^39and behold, a spirit taketh him, and he suddenly crieth out; and it teareth him that he foameth, and it hardly departeth from him, bruising him sorely. ^40And I besought thy disciples to cast it out; and they could not. ^41And Jesus answered and said, O faithless and perverse generation, how long shall I be with you, and bear with you? bring hither thy son. ^42And as he was yet a coming, the demon dashed him down, and tare him grievously. But Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit, and healed the boy, and gave him back to his father. ^43And they were all astonished at the majesty of God. But while all were marvelling at all the things which he did, he said unto his disciples, ^44Let these words sink into your ears: for the Son of man shall be delivered up into the hands of men. ^45But they understood not this saying, and it was concealed from them, that they should not perceive it; and they were afraid to ask him about this saying. ^46And there arose a reasoning among them, which of them was the greatest. ^47But when Jesus saw the reasoning of their heart, he took a little child, and set him by his side, ^48and said unto them, Whosoever shall receive this little child in my name receiveth me: and whosoever shall receive me receiveth him that sent me: for he that is least among you all, the same is great. ^49And John answered and said, Master, we saw one casting out demons in thy name; and we forbade him, because he followeth not with us. ^50But Jesus said unto him, Forbid him not: for he that is not against you is for you. ^51And it came to pass, when the days were well-nigh come that he should be received up, he stedfastly set his face to go to Jerusalem, ^52and sent messengers before his face: and they went, and entered into a village of the Samaritans, to make ready for him. ^53And they did not receive him, because his face was as though he were going to Jerusalem. ^54And when his disciples James and John saw this, they said, Lord, wilt thou that we bid fire to come down from heaven, and consume them? ^55But he turned, and rebuked them. ^56And they went to another village. ^57And as they went on the way, a certain man said unto him, I will follow thee whithersoever thou goest. ^58And Jesus said unto him, The foxes have holes, and the birds of the heaven have nests; but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head. ^59And he said unto another, Follow me. But he said, Lord, suffer me first to go and bury my father. ^60But he said unto him, Leave the dead to bury their own dead; but go thou and publish abroad the kingdom of God. ^61And another also said, I will follow thee, Lord; but first suffer me to bid farewell to them that are at my house. ^62But Jesus said unto him, No man, having put his hand to the plow, and looking back, is fit for the kingdom of God.

Luke 10

10

^1Now after these things the Lord appointed seventy others, and sent them two and two before his face into every city and place, whither he himself was about to come. ^2And he said unto them, The harvest indeed is plenteous, but the laborers are few: pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he send forth laborers into his harvest. ^3Go your ways; behold, I send you forth as lambs in the midst of wolves. ^4Carry no purse, no wallet, no shoes; and salute no man on the way. ^5And into whatsoever house ye shall enter, first say, Peace be to this house. ^6And if a son of peace be there, your peace shall rest upon him: but if not, it shall turn to you again. ^7And in that same house remain, eating and drinking such things as they give: for the laborer is worthy of his hire. Go not from house to house. ^8And into whatsoever city ye enter, and they receive you, eat such things as are set before you: ^9and heal the sick that are therein, and say unto them, The kingdom of God is come nigh unto you. ^10But into whatsoever city ye shall enter, and they receive you not, go out into the streets thereof and say, ^11Even the dust from your city, that cleaveth to our feet, we wipe off against you: nevertheless know this, that the kingdom of God is come nigh. ^12I say unto you, it shall be more tolerable in that day for Sodom, than for that city. ^13Woe unto thee, Chorazin! woe unto thee, Bethsaida! for if the mighty works had been done in Tyre and Sidon, which were done in you, they would have repented long ago, sitting in sackcloth and ashes. ^14But it shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon in the judgment, than for you. ^15And thou, Capernaum, shalt thou be exalted unto heaven? thou shalt be brought down unto Hades. ^16He that heareth you heareth me; and he that rejecteth you rejecteth me; and he that rejecteth me rejecteth him that sent me. ^17And the seventy returned with joy, saying, Lord, even the demons are subject unto us in thy name. ^18And he said unto them, I beheld Satan fallen as lightning from heaven. ^19Behold, I have given you authority to tread upon serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy: and nothing shall in any wise hurt you. ^20Nevertheless in this rejoice not, that the spirits are subject unto you; but rejoice that your names are written in heaven. ^21In that same hour he rejoiced in the Holy Spirit, and said, I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that thou didst hide these things from the wise and understanding, and didst reveal them unto babes: yea, Father; for so it was well-pleasing in thy sight. ^22All things have been delivered unto me of my Father: and no one knoweth who the Son is, save the Father; and who the Father is, save the Son, and he to whomsoever the Son willeth to reveal him. ^23And turning to the disciples, he said privately, Blessed are the eyes which see the things that ye see: ^24for I say unto you, that many prophets and kings desired to see the things which ye see, and saw them not; and to hear the things which ye hear, and heard them not. ^25And behold, a certain lawyer stood up and made trial of him, saying, Teacher, what shall I do to inherit eternal life? ^26And he said unto him, What is written in the law? how readest thou? ^27And he answering said, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy strength, and with all thy mind; and thy neighbor as thyself. ^28And he said unto him, Thou hast answered right: this do, and thou shalt live. ^29But he, desiring to justify himself, said unto Jesus, And who is my neighbor? ^30Jesus made answer and said, A certain man was going down from Jerusalem to Jericho; and he fell among robbers, who both stripped him and beat him, and departed, leaving him half dead. ^31And by chance a certain priest was going down that way: and when he saw him, he passed by on the other side. ^32And in like manner a Levite also, when he came to the place, and saw him, passed by on the other side. ^33But a certain Samaritan, as he journeyed, came where he was: and when he saw him, he was moved with compassion, ^34and came to him, and bound up his wounds, pouring on them oil and wine; and he set him on his own beast, and brought him to an inn, and took care of him. ^35And on the morrow he took out two shillings, and gave them to the host, and said, Take care of him; and whatsoever thou spendest more, I, when I come back again, will repay thee. ^36Which of these three, thinkest thou, proved neighbor unto him that fell among the robbers? ^37And he said, He that showed mercy on him. And Jesus said unto him, Go, and do thou likewise. ^38Now as they went on their way, he entered into a certain village: and a certain woman named Martha received him into her house. ^39And she had a sister called Mary, who also sat at the Lord's feet, and heard his word. ^40But Martha was cumbered about much serving; and she came up to him, and said, Lord, dost thou not care that my sister did leave me to serve alone? bid her therefore that she help me. ^41But the Lord answered and said unto her, Martha, Martha, thou art anxious and troubled about many things: ^42but one thing is needful: for Mary hath chosen the good part, which shall not be taken away from her.

Luke 11

11

^1And it came to pass, as he was praying in a certain place, that when he ceased, one of his disciples said unto him, Lord, teach us to pray, even as John also taught his disciples. ^2And he said unto them, When ye pray, say, Father, Hallowed be thy name. Thy kingdom come. ^3Give us day by day our daily bread. ^4And forgive us our sins; for we ourselves also forgive every one that is indebted to us. And bring us not into temptation. ^5And he said unto them, Which of you shall have a friend, and shall go unto him at midnight, and say to him, Friend, lend me three loaves; ^6for a friend of mine is come to me from a journey, and I have nothing to set before him; ^7and he from within shall answer and say, Trouble me not: the door is now shut, and my children are with me in bed; I cannot rise and give thee? ^8I say unto you, Though he will not rise and give him because he is his friend, yet because of his importunity he will arise and give him as many as he needeth. ^9And I say unto you, Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you. ^10For every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth; and to him that knocketh it shall be opened. ^11And of which of you that is a father shall his son ask a loaf, and he give him a stone? or a fish, and he for a fish give him a serpent? ^12Or if he shall ask an egg, will he give him a scorpion? ^13If ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your children, how much more shall your heavenly Father give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him? ^14And he was casting out a demon that was dumb. And it came to pass, when the demon was gone out, the dumb man spake; and the multitudes marvelled. ^15But some of them said, By Beelzebub the prince of the demons casteth he out demons. ^16And others, trying him, sought of him a sign from heaven. ^17But he, knowing their thoughts, said unto them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation; and a house divided against a house falleth. ^18And if Satan also is divided against himself, how shall his kingdom stand? because ye say that I cast out demons by Beelzebub. ^19And if I by Beelzebub cast out demons, by whom do your sons cast them out? therefore shall they be your judges. ^20But if I by the finger of God cast out demons, then is the kingdom of God come upon you. ^21When the strong man fully armed guardeth his own court, his goods are in peace: ^22but when a stronger than he shall come upon him, and overcome him, he taketh from him his whole armor wherein he trusted, and divideth his spoils. ^23He that is not with me is against me; and he that gathereth not with me scattereth. ^24The unclean spirit when he is gone out of the man, passeth through waterless places, seeking rest, and finding none, he saith, I will turn back unto my house whence I came out. ^25And when he is come, he findeth it swept and garnished. ^26Then goeth he, and taketh to him seven other spirits more evil than himself; and they enter in and dwell there: and the last state of that man becometh worse than the first. ^27And it came to pass, as he said these things, a certain woman out of the multitude lifted up her voice, and said unto him, Blessed is the womb that bare thee, and the breasts which thou didst suck. ^28But he said, Yea rather, blessed are they that hear the word of God, and keep it. ^29And when the multitudes were gathering together unto him, he began to say, This generation is an evil generation: it seeketh after a sign; and there shall no sign be given to it but the sign of Jonah. ^30For even as Jonah became a sign unto the Ninevites, so shall also the Son of man be to this generation. ^31The queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with the men of this generation, and shall condemn them: for she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and behold, a greater than Solomon is here. ^32The men of Nineveh shall stand up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for they repented at the preaching of Jonah; and behold, a greater than Jonah is here. ^33No man, when he hath lighted a lamp, putteth it in a cellar, neither under the bushel, but on the stand, that they which enter in may see the light. ^34The lamp of thy body is thine eye: when thine eye is single, thy whole body also is full of light; but when it is evil, thy body also is full of darkness. ^35Look therefore whether the light that is in thee be not darkness. ^36If therefore thy whole body be full of light, having no part dark, it shall be wholly full of light, as when the lamp with its bright shining doth give thee light. ^37Now as he spake, a Pharisee asketh him to dine with him: and he went in, and sat down to meat. ^38And when the Pharisee saw it, he marvelled that he had not first bathed himself before dinner. ^39And the Lord said unto him, Now ye the Pharisees cleanse the outside of the cup and of the platter; but your inward part is full of extortion and wickedness. ^40Ye foolish ones, did not he that made the outside make the inside also? ^41But give for alms those things which are within; and behold, all things are clean unto you. ^42But woe unto you Pharisees! for ye tithe mint and rue and every herb, and pass over justice and the love of God: but these ought ye to have done, and not to leave the other undone. ^43Woe unto you Pharisees! for ye love the chief seats in the synagogues, and the salutations in the marketplaces. ^44Woe unto you! for ye are as the tombs which appear not, and the men that walk over them know it not. ^45And one of the lawyers answering saith unto him, Teacher, in saying this thou reproachest us also. ^46And he said, Woe unto you lawyers also! for ye load men with burdens grievous to be borne, and ye yourselves touch not the burdens with one of your fingers. ^47Woe unto you! for ye build the tombs of the prophets, and your fathers killed them. ^48So ye are witnesses and consent unto the works of your fathers: for they killed them, and ye build their tombs. ^49Therefore also said the wisdom of God, I will send unto them prophets and apostles; and some of them they shall kill and persecute; ^50that the blood of all the prophets, which was shed from the foundation of the world, may be required of this generation; ^51from the blood of Abel unto the blood of Zachariah, who perished between the altar and the sanctuary: yea, I say unto you, it shall be required of this generation. ^52Woe unto you lawyers! for ye took away the key of knowledge: ye entered not in yourselves, and them that were entering in ye hindered. ^53And when he was come out from thence, the scribes and the Pharisees began to press upon him vehemently, and to provoke him to speak of many things; ^54laying wait for him, to catch something out of his mouth.

Luke 12

12

^1In the mean time, when the many thousands of the multitude were gathered together, insomuch that they trod one upon another, he began to say unto his disciples first of all, Beware ye of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy. ^2But there is nothing covered up, that shall not be revealed; and hid, that shall not be known. ^3Wherefore whatsoever ye have said in the darkness shall be heard in the light; and what ye have spoken in the ear in the inner chambers shall be proclaimed upon the housetops. ^4And I say unto you my friends, Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that have no more that they can do. ^5But I will warn you whom ye shall fear: Fear him, who after he hath killed hath power to cast into hell; yea, I say unto you, Fear him. ^6Are not five sparrows sold for two pence? and not one of them is forgotten in the sight of God. ^7But the very hairs of your head are all numbered. Fear not: ye are of more value than many sparrows. ^8And I say unto you, Every one who shall confess me before men, him shall the Son of man also confess before the angels of God: ^9but he that denieth me in the presence of men shall be denied in the presence of the angels of God. ^10And every one who shall speak a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him: but unto him that blasphemeth against the Holy Spirit it shall not be forgiven. ^11And when they bring you before the synagogues, and the rulers, and the authorities, be not anxious how or what ye shall answer, or what ye shall say: ^12for the Holy Spirit shall teach you in that very hour what ye ought to say. ^13And one out of the multitude said unto him, Teacher, bid my brother divide the inheritance with me. ^14But he said unto him, Man, who made me a judge or a divider over you? ^15And he said unto them, Take heed, and keep yourselves from all covetousness: for a man's life consisteth not in the abundance of the things which he possesseth. ^16And he spake a parable unto them, saying, The ground of a certain rich man brought forth plentifully: ^17and he reasoned within himself, saying, What shall I do, because I have not where to bestow my fruits? ^18And he said, This will I do: I will pull down my barns, and build greater; and there will I bestow all my grain and my goods. ^19And I will say to my soul, Soul, thou hast much goods laid up for many years; take thine ease, eat, drink, be merry. ^20But God said unto him, Thou foolish one, this night is thy soul required of thee; and the things which thou hast prepared, whose shall they be? ^21So is he that layeth up treasure for himself, and is not rich toward God. ^22And he said unto his disciples, Therefore I say unto you, Be not anxious for your life, what ye shall eat; nor yet for your body, what ye shall put on. ^23For the life is more than the food, and the body than the raiment. ^24Consider the ravens, that they sow not, neither reap; which have no store-chamber nor barn; and God feedeth them: of how much more value are ye than the birds! ^25And which of you by being anxious can add a cubit unto the measure of his life? ^26If then ye are not able to do even that which is least, why are ye anxious concerning the rest? ^27Consider the lilies, how they grow: they toil not, neither do they spin; yet I say unto you, Even Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these. ^28But if God doth so clothe the grass in the field, which to-day is, and to-morrow is cast into the oven; how much more shall he clothe you, O ye of little faith? ^29And seek not ye what ye shall eat, and what ye shall drink, neither be ye of doubtful mind. ^30For all these things do the nations of the world seek after: but your Father knoweth that ye have need of these things. ^31Yet seek ye his kingdom, and these things shall be added unto you. ^32Fear not, little flock; for it is your Father's good pleasure to give you the kingdom. ^33Sell that which ye have, and give alms; make for yourselves purses which wax not old, a treasure in the heavens that faileth not, where no thief draweth near, neither moth destroyeth. ^34For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also. ^35Let your loins be girded about, and your lamps burning; ^36and be ye yourselves like unto men looking for their lord, when he shall return from the marriage feast; that, when he cometh and knocketh, they may straightway open unto him. ^37Blessed are those servants, whom the lord when he cometh shall find watching: verily I say unto you, that he shall gird himself, and make them sit down to meat, and shall come and serve them. ^38And if he shall come in the second watch, and if in the third, and find them so blessed are those servants. ^39But know this, that if the master of the house had known in what hour the thief was coming, he would have watched, and not have left his house to be broken through. ^40Be ye also ready: for in an hour that ye think not the Son of man cometh. ^41And Peter said, Lord, speakest thou this parable unto us, or even unto all? ^42And the Lord said, Who then is the faithful and wise steward, whom his lord shall set over his household, to give them their portion of food in due season? ^43Blessed is that servant, whom his lord when he cometh shall find so doing. ^44Of a truth I say unto you, that he will set him over all that he hath. ^45But if that servant shall say in his heart, My lord delayeth his coming; and shall begin to beat the menservants and the maidservants, and to eat and drink, and to be drunken; ^46the lord of that servant shall come in a day when he expecteth not, and in an hour when he knoweth not, and shall cut him asunder, and appoint his portion with the unfaithful. ^47And that servant, who knew his lord's will, and made not ready, nor did according to his will, shall be beaten with many stripes; ^48but he that knew not, and did things worthy of stripes, shall be beaten with few stripes. And to whomsoever much is given, of him shall much be required: and to whom they commit much, of him will they ask the more. ^49I came to cast fire upon the earth; and what do I desire, if it is already kindled? ^50But I have a baptism to be baptized with; and how am I straitened till it be accomplished! ^51Think ye that I am come to give peace in the earth? I tell you, Nay; but rather division: ^52for there shall be from henceforth five in one house divided, three against two, and two against three. ^53They shall be divided, father against son, and son against father; mother against daughter, and daughter against her mother; mother in law against her daughter in law, and daughter in law against her mother in law. ^54And he said to the multitudes also, When ye see a cloud rising in the west, straightway ye say, There cometh a shower; and so it cometh to pass. ^55And when ye see a south wind blowing, ye say, There will be a scorching heat; and it cometh to pass. ^56Ye hypocrites, ye know how to interpret the face of the earth and the heaven; but how is it that ye know not how to interpret this time? ^57And why even of yourselves judge ye not what is right? ^58For as thou art going with thine adversary before the magistrate, on the way give diligence to be quit of him; lest haply he drag thee unto the judge, and the judge shall deliver thee to the officer, and the officer shall cast thee into prison. ^59I say unto thee, Thou shalt by no means come out thence, till thou have paid the very last mite.

Luke 13

13

^1Now there were some present at that very season who told him of the Galilaeans, whose blood Pilate had mingled with their sacrifices. ^2And he answered and said unto them, Think ye that these Galilaeans were sinners above all the Galilaeans, because they have suffered these things? ^3I tell you, Nay: but, except ye repent, ye shall all in like manner perish. ^4Or those eighteen, upon whom the tower in Siloam fell, and killed them, think ye that they were offenders above all the men that dwell in Jerusalem? ^5I tell you, Nay: but, except ye repent, ye shall all likewise perish. ^6And he spake this parable; A certain man had a fig tree planted in his vineyard; and he came seeking fruit thereon, and found none. ^7And he said unto the vinedresser, Behold, these three years I come seeking fruit on this fig tree, and find none: cut it down; why doth it also cumber the ground? ^8And he answering saith unto him, Lord, let it alone this year also, till I shall dig about it, and dung it: ^9and if it bear fruit thenceforth, well; but if not, thou shalt cut it down. ^10And he was teaching in one of the synagogues on the sabbath day. ^11And behold, a woman that had a spirit of infirmity eighteen years; and she was bowed together, and could in no wise lift herself up. ^12And when Jesus saw her, he called her, and said to her, Woman, thou art loosed from thine infirmity. ^13And he laid his hands upon her: and immediately she was made straight, and glorified God. ^14And the ruler of the synagogue, being moved with indignation because Jesus had healed on the sabbath, answered and said to the multitude, There are six days in which men ought to work: in them therefore come and be healed, and not on the day of the sabbath. ^15But the Lord answered him, and said, Ye hypocrites, doth not each one of you on the sabbath loose his ox or his ass from the stall, and lead him away to watering? ^16And ought not this woman, being a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan had bound, lo, these eighteen years, to have been loosed from this bond on the day of the sabbath? ^17And as he said these things, all his adversaries were put to shame: and all the multitude rejoiced for all the glorious things that were done by him. ^18He said therefore, Unto what is the kingdom of God like? and whereunto shall I liken it? ^19It is like unto a grain of mustard seed, which a man took, and cast into his own garden; and it grew, and became a tree; and the birds of the heaven lodged in the branches thereof. ^20And again he said, Whereunto shall I liken the kingdom of God? ^21It is like unto leaven, which a woman took and hid in three measures of meal, till it was all leavened. ^22And he went on his way through cities and villages, teaching, and journeying on unto Jerusalem. ^23And one said unto him, Lord, are they few that are saved? And he said unto them, ^24Strive to enter in by the narrow door: for many, I say unto you, shall seek to enter in, and shall not be able. ^25When once the master of the house is risen up, and hath shut to the door, and ye begin to stand without, and to knock at the door, saying, Lord, open to us; and he shall answer and say to you, I know you not whence ye are; ^26then shall ye begin to say, We did eat and drink in thy presence, and thou didst teach in our streets; ^27and he shall say, I tell you, I know not whence ye are; depart from me, all ye workers of iniquity. ^28There shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth, when ye shall see Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, and all the prophets, in the kingdom of God, and yourselves cast forth without. ^29And they shall come from the east and west, and from the north and south, and shall sit down in the kingdom of God. ^30And behold, there are last who shall be first, and there are first who shall be last. ^31In that very hour there came certain Pharisees, saying to him, Get thee out, and go hence: for Herod would fain kill thee. ^32And he said unto them, Go and say to that fox, Behold, I cast out demons and perform cures to-day and to-morrow, and the third day I am perfected. ^33Nevertheless I must go on my way to-day and to-morrow and the day following: for it cannot be that a prophet perish out of Jerusalem. ^34O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, that killeth the prophets, and stoneth them that are sent unto her! how often would I have gathered thy children together, even as a hen gathereth her own brood under her wings, and ye would not! ^35Behold, your house is left unto you desolate: and I say unto you, Ye shall not see me, until ye shall say, Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.

Luke 14

14

^1And it came to pass, when he went into the house of one of the rulers of the Pharisees on a sabbath to eat bread, that they were watching him. ^2And behold, there was before him a certain man that had the dropsy. ^3And Jesus answering spake unto the lawyers and Pharisees, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath, or not? ^4But they held their peace. And he took him, and healed him, and let him go. ^5And he said unto them, Which of you shall have an ass or an ox fallen into a well, and will not straightway draw him up on a sabbath day? ^6And they could not answer again unto these things. ^7And he spake a parable unto those that were bidden, when he marked how they chose out the chief seats; saying unto them, ^8When thou art bidden of any man to a marriage feast, sit not down in the chief seat; lest haply a more honorable man than thou be bidden of him, ^9and he that bade thee and him shall come and say to thee, Give this man place; and then thou shalt begin with shame to take the lowest place. ^10But when thou art bidden, go and sit down in the lowest place; that when he that hath bidden thee cometh, he may say to thee, Friend, go up higher: then shalt thou have glory in the presence of all that sit at meat with thee. ^11For everyone that exalteth himself shall be humbled; and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted. ^12And he said to him also that had bidden him, When thou makest a dinner or a supper, call not thy friends, nor thy brethren, nor thy kinsmen, nor rich neighbors; lest haply they also bid thee again, and a recompense be made thee. ^13But when thou makest a feast, bid the poor, the maimed, the lame, the blind: ^14and thou shalt be blessed; because they have not wherewith to recompense thee: for thou shalt be recompensed in the resurrection of the just. ^15And when one of them that sat at meat with him heard these things, he said unto him, Blessed is he that shall eat bread in the kingdom of God. ^16But he said unto him, A certain man made a great supper; and he bade many: ^17and he sent forth his servant at supper time to say to them that were bidden, Come; for all things are now ready. ^18And they all with one consent began to make excuse. The first said unto him, I have bought a field, and I must needs go out and see it; I pray thee have me excused. ^19And another said, I have bought five yoke of oxen, and I go to prove them; I pray thee have me excused. ^20And another said, I have married a wife, and therefore I cannot come. ^21And the servant came, and told his lord these things. Then the master of the house being angry said to his servant, Go out quickly into the streets and lanes of the city, and bring in hither the poor and maimed and blind and lame. ^22And the servant said, Lord, what thou didst command is done, and yet there is room. ^23And the lord said unto the servant, Go out into the highways and hedges, and constrain them to come in, that my house may be filled. ^24For I say unto you, that none of those men that were bidden shall taste of my supper. ^25Now there went with him great multitudes: and he turned, and said unto them, ^26If any man cometh unto me, and hateth not his own father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brethren, and sisters, yea, and his own life also, he cannot be my disciple. ^27Whosoever doth not bear his own cross, and come after me, cannot be my disciple. ^28For which of you, desiring to build a tower, doth not first sit down and count the cost, whether he have wherewith to complete it? ^29Lest haply, when he hath laid a foundation, and is not able to finish, all that behold begin to mock him, ^30saying, This man began to build, and was not able to finish. ^31Or what king, as he goeth to encounter another king in war, will not sit down first and take counsel whether he is able with ten thousand to meet him that cometh against him with twenty thousand? ^32Or else, while the other is yet a great way off, he sendeth an ambassage, and asketh conditions of peace. ^33So therefore whosoever he be of you that renounceth not all that he hath, he cannot be my disciple. ^34Salt therefore is good: but if even the salt have lost its savor, wherewith shall it be seasoned? ^35It is fit neither for the land nor for the dunghill: men cast it out. He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.

Luke 15

15

^1Now all the publicans and sinners were drawing near unto him to hear him. ^2And both the Pharisees and the scribes murmured, saying, This man receiveth sinners, and eateth with them. ^3And he spake unto them this parable, saying, ^4What man of you, having a hundred sheep, and having lost one of them, doth not leave the ninety and nine in the wilderness, and go after that which is lost, until he find it? ^5And when he hath found it, he layeth it on his shoulders, rejoicing. ^6And when he cometh home, he calleth together his friends and his neighbors, saying unto them, Rejoice with me, for I have found my sheep which was lost. ^7I say unto you, that even so there shall be joy in heaven over one sinner that repenteth, more than over ninety and nine righteous persons, who need no repentance. ^8Or what woman having ten pieces of silver, if she lose one piece, doth not light a lamp, and sweep the house, and seek diligently until she find it? ^9And when she hath found it, she calleth together her friends and neighbors, saying, Rejoice with me, for I have found the piece which I had lost. ^10Even so, I say unto you, there is joy in the presence of the angels of God over one sinner that repenteth. ^11And he said, A certain man had two sons: ^12and the younger of them said to his father, Father, give me the portion of thy substance that falleth to me. And he divided unto them his living. ^13And not many days after, the younger son gathered all together and took his journey into a far country; and there he wasted his substance with riotous living. ^14And when he had spent all, there arose a mighty famine in that country; and he began to be in want. ^15And he went and joined himself to one of the citizens of that country; and he sent him into his fields to feed swine. ^16And he would fain have filled his belly with the husks that the swine did eat: and no man gave unto him. ^17But when he came to himself he said, How many hired servants of my father's have bread enough and to spare, and I perish here with hunger! ^18I will arise and go to my father, and will say unto him, Father, I have sinned against heaven, and in thy sight: ^19I am no more worthy to be called your son: make me as one of thy hired servants. ^20And he arose, and came to his father. But while he was yet afar off, his father saw him, and was moved with compassion, and ran, and fell on his neck, and kissed him. ^21And the son said unto him, Father, I have sinned against heaven, and in thy sight: I am no more worthy to be called thy son. ^22But the father said to his servants, Bring forth quickly the best robe, and put it on him; and put a ring on his hand, and shoes on his feet: ^23and bring the fatted calf, and kill it, and let us eat, and make merry: ^24for this my son was dead, and is alive again; he was lost, and is found. And they began to be merry. ^25Now his elder son was in the field: and as he came and drew nigh to the house, he heard music and dancing. ^26And he called to him one of the servants, and inquired what these things might be. ^27And he said unto him, Thy brother is come; and thy father hath killed the fatted calf, because he hath received him safe and sound. ^28But he was angry, and would not go in: and his father came out, and entreated him. ^29But he answered and said to his father, Lo, these many years do I serve thee, and I never transgressed a commandment of thine; and yet thou never gavest me a kid, that I might make merry with my friends: ^30but when this thy son came, who hath devoured thy living with harlots, thou killedst for him the fatted calf. ^31And he said unto him, Son, thou art ever with me, and all that is mine is thine. ^32But it was meet to make merry and be glad: for this thy brother was dead, and is alive again; and was lost, and is found.

Luke 16

16

^1And he said also unto the disciples, There was a certain rich man, who had a steward; and the same was accused unto him that he was wasting his goods. ^2And he called him, and said unto him, What is this that I hear of thee? render the account of thy stewardship; for thou canst be no longer steward. ^3And the steward said within himself, What shall I do, seeing that my lord taketh away the stewardship from me? I have not strength to dig; to beg I am ashamed. ^4I am resolved what to do, that, when I am put out of the stewardship, they may receive me into their houses. ^5And calling to him each one of his lord's debtors, he said to the first, How much owest thou unto my lord? ^6And he said, A hundred measures of oil. And he said unto him, Take thy bond, and sit down quickly and write fifty. ^7Then said he to another, And how much owest thou? And he said, A hundred measures of wheat. He saith unto him, Take thy bond, and write fourscore. ^8And his lord commended the unrighteous steward because he had done wisely: for the sons of this world are for their own generation wiser than the sons of the light. ^9And I say unto you, Make to yourselves friends by means of the mammon of unrighteousness; that, when it shall fail, they may receive you into the eternal tabernacles. ^10He that is faithful in a very little is faithful also in much: and he that is unrighteous in a very little is unrighteous also in much. ^11If therefore ye have not been faithful in the unrighteous mammon, who will commit to your trust the true riches? ^12And if ye have not been faithful in that which is another's, who will give you that which is your own? ^13No servant can serve two masters: for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or else he will hold to one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon. ^14And the Pharisees, who were lovers of money, heard all these things; and they scoffed at him. ^15And he said unto them, Ye are they that justify yourselves in the sight of men; but God knoweth your hearts: for that which is exalted among men is an abomination in the sight of God. ^16The law and the prophets were until John: from that time the gospel of the kingdom of God is preached, and every man entereth violently into it. ^17But it is easier for heaven and earth to pass away, than for one tittle of the law to fall. ^18Every one that putteth away his wife, and marrieth another, committeth adultery: and he that marrieth one that is put away from a husband committeth adultery. ^19Now there was a certain rich man, and he was clothed in purple and fine linen, faring sumptuously every day: ^20and a certain beggar named Lazarus was laid at his gate, full of sores, ^21and desiring to be fed with the crumbs that fell from the rich man's table; yea, even the dogs come and licked his sores. ^22And it came to pass, that the beggar died, and that he was carried away by the angels into Abraham's bosom: and the rich man also died, and was buried. ^23And in Hades he lifted up his eyes, being in torments, and seeth Abraham afar off, and Lazarus in his bosom. ^24And he cried and said, Father Abraham, have mercy on me, and send Lazarus, that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and cool my tongue; for I am in anguish in this flame. ^25But Abraham said, Son, remember that thou in thy lifetime receivedst thy good things, and Lazarus in like manner evil things: but now here he is comforted and thou art in anguish. ^26And besides all this, between us and you there is a great gulf fixed, that they that would pass from hence to you may not be able, and that none may cross over from thence to us. ^27And he said, I pray thee therefore, father, that thou wouldest send him to my father's house; ^28for I have five brethren; that he may testify unto them, lest they also come into this place of torment. ^29But Abraham saith, They have Moses and the prophets; let them hear them. ^30And he said, Nay, father Abraham: but if one go to them from the dead, they will repent. ^31And he said unto him, If they hear not Moses and the prophets, neither will they be persuaded, if one rise from the dead.

Luke 17

17

^1And he said unto his disciples, It is impossible but that occasions of stumbling should come; but woe unto him, through whom they come! ^2It were well for him if a millstone were hanged about his neck, and he were thrown into the sea, rather than that he should cause one of these little ones to stumble. ^3Take heed to yourselves: if thy brother sin, rebuke him; and if he repent, forgive him. ^4And if he sin against thee seven times in the day, and seven times turn again to thee, saying, I repent; thou shalt forgive him. ^5And the apostles said unto the Lord, Increase our faith. ^6And the Lord said, If ye had faith as a grain of mustard seed, ye would say unto this sycamine tree, Be thou rooted up, and be thou planted in the sea; and it would obey you. ^7But who is there of you, having a servant plowing or keeping sheep, that will say unto him, when he is come in from the field, Come straightway and sit down to meat; ^8and will not rather say unto him, Make ready wherewith I may sup, and gird thyself, and serve me, till I have eaten and drunken; and afterward thou shalt eat and drink? ^9Doth he thank the servant because he did the things that were commanded? ^10Even so ye also, when ye shall have done all the things that are commanded you, say, We are unprofitable servants; we have done that which it was our duty to do. ^11And it came to pass, as they were on their way to Jerusalem, that he was passing along the borders of Samaria and Galilee. ^12And as he entered into a certain village, there met him ten men that were lepers, who stood afar off: ^13and they lifted up their voices, saying, Jesus, Master, have mercy on us. ^14And when he saw them, he said unto them, Go and show yourselves unto the priests. And it came to pass, as they went, they were cleansed. ^15And one of them, when he saw that he was healed, turned back, with a loud voice glorifying God; ^16and he fell upon his face at his feet, giving him thanks: and he was a Samaritan. ^17And Jesus answering said, Were not the ten cleansed? but where are the nine? ^18Were there none found that returned to give glory to God, save this stranger? ^19And he said unto him, Arise, and go thy way: thy faith hath made thee whole. ^20And being asked by the Pharisees, when the kingdom of God cometh, he answered them and said, The kingdom of God cometh not with observation: ^21neither shall they say, Lo, here! or, There! for lo, the kingdom of God is within you. ^22And he said unto the disciples, The days will come, when ye shall desire to see one of the days of the Son of man, and ye shall not see it. ^23And they shall say to you, Lo, there! Lo, here! go not away, nor follow after them: ^24for as the lightning, when it lighteneth out of the one part under the heaven, shineth unto the other part under heaven; so shall the Son of man be in his day. ^25But first must he suffer many things and be rejected of this generation. ^26And as it came to pass in the days of Noah, even so shall it be also in the days of the Son of man. ^27They ate, they drank, they married, they were given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark, and the flood came, and destroyed them all. ^28Likewise even as it came to pass in the days of Lot; they ate, they drank, they bought, they sold, they planted, they builded; ^29but in the day that Lot went out from Sodom it rained fire and brimstone from heaven, and destroyed them all: ^30after the same manner shall it be in the day that the Son of man is revealed. ^31In that day, he that shall be on the housetop, and his goods in the house, let him not go down to take them away: and let him that is in the field likewise not return back. ^32Remember Lot's wife. ^33Whosoever shall seek to gain his life shall lose it: but whosoever shall lose his life shall preserve it. ^34I say unto you, In that night there shall be two men on one bed; the one shall be taken, and the other shall be left. ^35There shall be two women grinding together; the one shall be taken, and the other shall be left. ^36There shall be two men in the field; the one shall be taken, and the other shall be left. ^37And they answering say unto him, Where, Lord? And he said unto them, Where the body is, thither will the eagles also be gathered together.

Luke 18

18

^1And he spake a parable unto them to the end that they ought always to pray, and not to faint; ^2saying, There was in a city a judge, who feared not God, and regarded not man: ^3and there was a widow in that city; and she came oft unto him, saying, Avenge me of mine adversary. ^4And he would not for a while: but afterward he said within himself, Though I fear not God, nor regard man; ^5yet because this widow troubleth me, I will avenge her, lest she wear me out by her continual coming. ^6And the Lord said, Hear what the unrighteous judge saith. ^7And shall not God avenge his elect, that cry to him day and night, and yet he is longsuffering over them? ^8I say unto you, that he will avenge them speedily. Nevertheless, when the Son of man cometh, shall he find faith on the earth? ^9And he spake also this parable unto certain who trusted in themselves that they were righteous, and set all others at nought: ^10Two men went up into the temple to pray; the one a Pharisee, and the other a publican. ^11The Pharisee stood and prayed thus with himself, God, I thank thee, that I am not as the rest of men, extortioners, unjust, adulterers, or even as this publican. ^12I fast twice in the week; I give tithes of all that I get. ^13But the publican, standing afar off, would not lift up so much as his eyes unto heaven, but smote his breast, saying, God, be thou merciful to me a sinner. ^14I say unto you, This man went down to his house justified rather than the other: for every one that exalteth himself shall be humbled; but he that humbleth himself shall be exalted. ^15And they were bringing unto him also their babes, that he should touch them: but when the disciples saw it, they rebuked them. ^16But Jesus called them unto him, saying, Suffer the little children to come unto me, and forbid them not: for to such belongeth the kingdom of God. ^17Verily I say unto you, Whosoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child, he shall in no wise enter therein. ^18And a certain ruler asked him, saying, Good Teacher, what shall I do to inherit eternal life? ^19And Jesus said unto him, Why callest thou me good? none is good, save one, even God. ^20Thou knowest the commandments, Do not commit adultery, Do not kill, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Honor thy father and mother. ^21And he said, All these things have I observed from my youth up. ^22And when Jesus heard it, he said unto him, One thing thou lackest yet: sell all that thou hast, and distribute unto the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come, follow me. ^23But when he heard these things, he became exceeding sorrowful; for he was very rich. ^24And Jesus seeing him said, How hardly shall they that have riches enter into the kingdom of God! ^25For it is easier for a camel to enter in through a needle's eye, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God. ^26And they that heard it said, Then who can be saved? ^27But he said, The things which are impossible with men are possible with God. ^28And Peter said, Lo, we have left our own, and followed thee. ^29And he said unto them, Verily I say unto you, There is no man that hath left house, or wife, or brethren, or parents, or children, for the kingdom of God's sake, ^30who shall not receive manifold more in this time, and in the world to come eternal life. ^31And he took unto him the twelve, and said unto them, Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and all the things that are written through the prophets shall be accomplished unto the Son of man. ^32For he shall be delivered up unto the Gentiles, and shall be mocked, and shamefully treated, and spit upon: ^33and they shall scourge and kill him: and the third day he shall rise again. ^34And they understood none of these things; and this saying was hid from them, and they perceived not the things that were said. ^35And it came to pass, as he drew nigh unto Jericho, a certain blind man sat by the way side begging: ^36and hearing a multitude going by, he inquired what this meant. ^37And they told him that Jesus of Nazareth passeth by. ^38And he cried, saying, Jesus, thou son of David, have mercy on me. ^39And they that went before rebuked him, that he should hold his peace: but he cried out the more a great deal, Thou son of David, have mercy on me. ^40And Jesus stood, and commanded him to be brought unto him: and when he was come near, he asked him, ^41What wilt thou that I should do unto thee? And he said, Lord, that I may receive my sight. ^42And Jesus said unto him, Receive thy sight; thy faith hath made thee whole. ^43And immediately he received his sight, and followed him, glorifying God: and all the people, when they saw it, gave praise unto God.

Luke 19

19

^1And he entered and was passing through Jericho. ^2And behold, a man called by name Zacchaeus; and he was a chief publican, and he was rich. ^3And he sought to see Jesus who he was; and could not for the crowd, because he was little of stature. ^4And he ran on before, and climbed up into a sycomore tree to see him: for he was to pass that way. ^5And when Jesus came to the place, he looked up, and said unto him, Zacchaeus, make haste, and come down; for to-day I must abide at thy house. ^6And he made haste, and came down, and received him joyfully. ^7And when they saw it, they all murmured, saying, He is gone in to lodge with a man that is a sinner. ^8And Zacchaeus stood, and said unto the Lord, Behold, Lord, the half of my goods I give to the poor; and if I have wrongfully exacted aught of any man, I restore fourfold. ^9And Jesus said unto him, To-day is salvation come to this house, forasmuch as he also is a son of Abraham. ^10For the Son of man came to seek and to save that which was lost. ^11And as they heard these things, he added and spake a parable, because he was nigh to Jerusalem, and because they supposed that the kingdom of God was immediately to appear. ^12He said therefore, A certain nobleman went into a far country, to receive for himself a kingdom, and to return. ^13And he called ten servants of his, and gave them ten pounds, and said unto them, Trade ye herewith till I come. ^14But his citizens hated him, and sent an ambassage after him, saying, We will not that this man reign over us. ^15And it came to pass, when he was come back again, having received the kingdom, that he commanded these servants, unto whom he had given the money, to be called to him, that he might know what they had gained by trading. ^16And the first came before him, saying, Lord, thy pound hath made ten pounds more. ^17And he said unto him, Well done, thou good servant: because thou wast found faithful in a very little, have thou authority over ten cities. ^18And the second came, saying, Thy pound, Lord, hath made five pounds. ^19And he said unto him also, Be thou also over five cities. ^20And another came, saying, Lord, behold, here is thy pound, which I kept laid up in a napkin: ^21for I feared thee, because thou art an austere man: thou takest up that which thou layedst not down, and reapest that which thou didst not sow. ^22He saith unto him, Out of thine own mouth will I judge thee, thou wicked servant. Thou knewest that I am an austere man, taking up that which I laid not down, and reaping that which I did not sow; ^23then wherefore gavest thou not my money into the bank, and I at my coming should have required it with interest? ^24And he said unto them that stood by, Take away from him the pound, and give it unto him that hath the ten pounds. ^25And they said unto him, Lord, he hath ten pounds. ^26I say unto you, that unto every one that hath shall be given; but from him that hath not, even that which he hath shall be taken away from him. ^27But these mine enemies, that would not that I should reign over them, bring hither, and slay them before me. ^28And when he had thus spoken, he went on before, going up to Jerusalem. ^29And it came to pass, when he drew nigh unto Bethphage and Bethany, at the mount that is called Olivet, he sent two of the disciples, ^30saying, Go your way into the village over against you; in which as ye enter ye shall find a colt tied, whereon no man ever yet sat: loose him, and bring him. ^31And if any one ask you, Why do ye loose him? thus shall ye say, The Lord hath need of him. ^32And they that were sent went away, and found even as he had said unto them. ^33And as they were loosing the colt, the owners thereof said unto them, Why loose ye the colt? ^34And they said, The Lord hath need of him. ^35And they brought him to Jesus: and they threw their garments upon the colt, and set Jesus thereon. ^36And as he went, they spread their garments in the way. ^37And as he was now drawing nigh, even at the descent of the mount of Olives, the whole multitude of the disciples began to rejoice and praise God with a loud voice for all the mighty works which they had seen; ^38saying, Blessed is the King that cometh in the name of the Lord: peace in heaven, and glory in the highest. ^39And some of the Pharisees from the multitude said unto him, Teacher, rebuke thy disciples. ^40And he answered and said, I tell you that, if these shall hold their peace, the stones will cry out. ^41And when he drew nigh, he saw the city and wept over it, ^42saying, If thou hadst known in this day, even thou, the things which belong unto peace! but now they are hid from thine eyes. ^43For the days shall come upon thee, when thine enemies shall cast up a bank about thee, and compass thee round, and keep thee in on every side, ^44and shall dash thee to the ground, and thy children within thee; and they shall not leave in thee one stone upon another; because thou knewest not the time of thy visitation. ^45And he entered into the temple, and began to cast out them that sold, ^46saying unto them, It is written, And my house shall be a house of prayer: but ye have made it a den of robbers. ^47And he was teaching daily in the temple. But the chief priests and the scribes and the principal men of the people sought to destroy him: ^48and they could not find what they might do; for the people all hung upon him, listening.

Luke 20

20

^1And it came to pass, on one of the days, as he was teaching the people in the temple, and preaching the gospel, there came upon him the chief priests and the scribes with the elders; ^2and they spake, saying unto him, Tell us: By what authority doest thou these things? or who is he that gave thee this authority? ^3And he answered and said unto them, I also will ask you a question; and tell me: ^4The baptism of John, was it from heaven, or from men? ^5And they reasoned with themselves, saying, If we shall say, From heaven; he will say, Why did ye not believe him? ^6But if we shall say, From men; all the people will stone us: for they are persuaded that John was a prophet. ^7And they answered, that they knew not whence it was. ^8And Jesus said unto them, Neither tell I you by what authority I do these things. ^9And he began to speak unto the people this parable: A man planted a vineyard, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into another country for a long time. ^10And at the season he sent unto the husbandmen a servant, that they should give him of the fruit of the vineyard: but the husbandmen beat him, and sent him away empty. ^11And he sent yet another servant: and him also they beat, and handled him shamefully, and sent him away empty. ^12And he sent yet a third: and him also they wounded, and cast him forth. ^13And the lord of the vineyard said, What shall I do? I will send my beloved son; it may be they will reverence him. ^14But when the husbandmen saw him, they reasoned one with another, saying, This is the heir; let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours. ^15And they cast him forth out of the vineyard, and killed him. What therefore will the lord of the vineyard do unto them? ^16He will come and destroy these husbandmen, and will give the vineyard unto others. And when they heard it, they said, God forbid. ^17But he looked upon them, and said, What then is this that is written,

The stone which the builders rejected,

The same was made the head of the corner?

^18Every one that falleth on that stone shall be broken to pieces; but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will scatter him as dust. ^19And the scribes and the chief priests sought to lay hands on him in that very hour; and they feared the people: for they perceived that he spake this parable against them. ^20And they watched him, and sent forth spies, who feigned themselves to be righteous, that they might take hold of his speech, so as to deliver him up to the rule and to the authority of the governor. ^21And they asked him, saying, Teacher, we know that thou sayest and teachest rightly, and acceptest not the person of any, but of a truth teachest the way of God: ^22Is it lawful for us to give tribute unto Caesar, or not? ^23But he perceived their craftiness, and said unto them, ^24Show me a denarius. Whose image and superscription hath it? And they said, Caesar's. ^25And he said unto them, Then render unto Caesar the things that are Caesar's, and unto God the things that are God's. ^26And they were not able to take hold of the saying before the people: and they marvelled at his answer, and held their peace. ^27And there came to him certain of the Sadducees, they that say that there is no resurrection; ^28and they asked him, saying, Teacher, Moses wrote unto us, that if a man's brother die, having a wife, and he be childless, his brother should take the wife, and raise up seed unto his brother. ^29There were therefore seven brethren: and the first took a wife, and died childless; ^30and the second: ^31and the third took her; and likewise the seven also left no children, and died. ^32Afterward the woman also died. ^33In the resurrection therefore whose wife of them shall she be? for the seven had her to wife. ^34And Jesus said unto them, The sons of this world marry, and are given in marriage: ^35but they that are accounted worthy to attain to that world, and the resurrection from the dead, neither marry, nor are given in marriage: ^36for neither can they die any more: for they are equal unto the angels; and are sons of God, being sons of the resurrection. ^37But that the dead are raised, even Moses showed, in the place concerning the Bush, when he calleth the Lord the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. ^38Now he is not the God of the dead, but of the living: for all live unto him. ^39And certain of the scribes answering said, Teacher, thou hast well said. ^40For they durst not any more ask him any question. ^41And he said unto them, How say they that the Christ is David's son? ^42For David himself saith in the book of Psalms,

The Lord said unto my Lord,

Sit thou on my right hand,

^43Till I make thine enemies the footstool of thy feet.

^44David therefore calleth him Lord, and how is he his son? ^45And in the hearing of all the people he said unto his disciples, ^46Beware of the scribes, who desire to walk in long robes, and love salutations in the marketplaces, and chief seats in the synagogues, and chief places at feasts; ^47who devour widows' houses, and for a pretence make long prayers: these shall receive greater condemnation.

Luke 21

21

^1And he looked up, and saw the rich men that were casting their gifts into the treasury. ^2And he saw a certain poor widow casting in thither two mites. ^3And he said, Of a truth I say unto you, This poor widow cast in more than they all: ^4for all these did of their superfluity cast in unto the gifts; but she of her want did cast in all the living that she had. ^5And as some spake of the temple, how it was adorned with goodly stones and offerings, he said, ^6As for these things which ye behold, the days will come, in which there shall not be left here one stone upon another, that shall not be thrown down. ^7And they asked him, saying, Teacher, when therefore shall these things be? and what shall be the sign when these things are about to come to pass? ^8And he said, Take heed that ye be not led astray: for many shall come in my name, saying, I am he; and, The time is at hand: go ye not after them. ^9And when ye shall hear of wars and tumults, be not terrified: for these things must needs come to pass first; but the end is not immediately. ^10Then said he unto them, Nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; ^11and there shall be great earthquakes, and in divers places famines and pestilences; and there shall be terrors and great signs from heaven. ^12But before all these things, they shall lay their hands on you, and shall persecute you, delivering you up to the synagogues and prisons, bringing you before kings and governors for my name's sake. ^13It shall turn out unto you for a testimony. ^14Settle it therefore in your hearts, not to meditate beforehand how to answer: ^15for I will give you a mouth and wisdom, which all your adversaries shall not be able to withstand or to gainsay. ^16But ye shall be delivered up even by parents, and brethren, and kinsfolk, and friends; and some of you shall they cause to be put to death. ^17And ye shall be hated of all men for my name's sake. ^18And not a hair of your head shall perish. ^19In your patience ye shall win your souls. ^20But when ye see Jerusalem compassed with armies, then know that her desolation is at hand. ^21Then let them that are in Judaea flee unto the mountains; and let them that are in the midst of her depart out; and let not them that are in the country enter therein. ^22For these are days of vengeance, that all things which are written may be fulfilled. ^23Woe unto them that are with child and to them that give suck in those days! for there shall be great distress upon the land, and wrath unto this people. ^24And they shall fall by the edge of the sword, and shall be led captive into all the nations: and Jerusalem shall be trodden down of the Gentiles, until the times of the Gentiles be fulfilled. ^25And there shall be signs in sun and moon and stars; and upon the earth distress of nations, in perplexity for the roaring of the sea and the billows; ^26men fainting for fear, and for expectation of the things which are coming on the world: for the powers of the heavens shall be shaken. ^27And then shall they see the Son of man coming in a cloud with power and great glory. ^28But when these things begin to come to pass, look up, and lift up your heads; because your redemption draweth nigh. ^29And he spake to them a parable: Behold the fig tree, and all the trees: ^30when they now shoot forth, ye see it and know of your own selves that the summer is now nigh. ^31Even so ye also, when ye see these things coming to pass, know ye that the kingdom of God is nigh. ^32Verily I say unto you, This generation shall not pass away, till all things be accomplished. ^33Heaven and earth shall pass away: but my words shall not pass away. ^34But take heed to yourselves, lest haply your hearts be overcharged with surfeiting, and drunkenness, and cares of this life, and that day come on you suddenly as a snare: ^35for so shall it come upon all them that dwell on the face of all the earth. ^36But watch ye at every season, making supplication, that ye may prevail to escape all these things that shall come to pass, and to stand before the Son of man. ^37And every day he was teaching in the temple; and every night he went out, and lodged in the mount that is called Olivet. ^38And all the people came early in the morning to him in the temple, to hear him.

Luke 23

23

^1And the whole company of them rose up, and brought him before Pilate. ^2And they began to accuse him, saying, We found this man perverting our nation, and forbidding to give tribute to Caesar, and saying that he himself is Christ a king. ^3And Pilate asked him, saying, Art thou the King of the Jews? And he answered him and said, Thou sayest. ^4And Pilate said unto the chief priests and the multitudes, I find no fault in this man. ^5But they were the more urgent, saying, He stirreth up the people, teaching throughout all Judaea, and beginning from Galilee even unto this place. ^6But when Pilate heard it, he asked whether the man were a Galilaean. ^7And when he knew that he was of Herod's jurisdiction, he sent him unto Herod, who himself also was at Jerusalem in these days. ^8Now when Herod saw Jesus, he was exceeding glad: for he was of a long time desirous to see him, because he had heard concerning him; and he hoped to see some miracle done by him. ^9And he questioned him in many words; but he answered him nothing. ^10And the chief priests and the scribes stood, vehemently accusing him. ^11And Herod with his soldiers set him at nought, and mocked him, and arraying him in gorgeous apparel sent him back to Pilate. ^12And Herod and Pilate became friends with each other that very day: for before they were at enmity between themselves. ^13And Pilate called together the chief priests and the rulers and the people, ^14and said unto them, Ye brought unto me this man, as one that perverteth the people: and behold, I having examined him before you, found no fault in this man touching those things whereof ye accuse him: ^15no, nor yet Herod: for he sent him back unto us; and behold, nothing worthy of death hath been done by him. ^16I will therefore chastise him, and release him. ^17Now he must needs release unto them at the feast one prisoner. ^18But they cried out all together, saying, Away with this man, and release unto us Barabbas: -- ^19one who for a certain insurrection made in the city, and for murder, was cast into prison. ^20And Pilate spake unto them again, desiring to release Jesus; ^21but they shouted, saying, Crucify, crucify him. ^22And he said unto them the third time, Why, what evil hath this man done? I have found no cause of death in him: I will therefore chastise him and release him. ^23But they were urgent with loud voices, asking that he might be crucified. And their voices prevailed. ^24And Pilate gave sentence that what they asked for should be done. ^25And he released him that for insurrection and murder had been cast into prison, whom they asked for; but Jesus he delivered up to their will. ^26And when they led him away, they laid hold upon one Simon of Cyrene, coming from the country, and laid on him the cross, to bear it after Jesus. ^27And there followed him a great multitude of the people, and of women who bewailed and lamented him. ^28But Jesus turning unto them said, Daughters of Jerusalem, weep not for me, but weep for yourselves, and for your children. ^29For behold, the days are coming, in which they shall say, Blessed are the barren, and the wombs that never bare, and the breasts that never gave suck. ^30Then shall they begin to say to the mountains, Fall on us; and to the hills, Cover us. ^31For if they do these things in the green tree, what shall be done in the dry? ^32And there were also two others, malefactors, led with him to be put to death. ^33And when they came unto the place which is called The skull, there they crucified him, and the malefactors, one on the right hand and the other on the left. ^34And Jesus said, Father, forgive them; for they know not what they do. And parting his garments among them, they cast lots. ^35And the people stood beholding. And the rulers also scoffed at him, saying, He saved others; let him save himself, if this is the Christ of God, his chosen. ^36And the soldiers also mocked him, coming to him, offering him vinegar, ^37and saying, If thou art the King of the Jews, save thyself. ^38And there was also a superscription over him, THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS. ^39And one of the malefactors that were hanged railed on him, saying, Art not thou the Christ? save thyself and us. ^40But the other answered, and rebuking him said, Dost thou not even fear God, seeing thou art in the same condemnation? ^41And we indeed justly; for we receive the due reward of our deeds: but this man hath done nothing amiss. ^42And he said, Jesus, remember me when thou comest in thy kingdom. ^43And he said unto him, Verily I say unto thee, To-day shalt thou be with me in Paradise. ^44And it was now about the sixth hour, and a darkness came over the whole land until the ninth hour, ^45the sun's light failing: and the veil of the temple was rent in the midst. ^46And Jesus, crying with a loud voice, said, Father, into thy hands I commend my spirit: and having said this, he gave up the ghost. ^47And when the centurion saw what was done, he glorified God, saying, Certainly this was a righteous man. ^48And all the multitudes that came together to this sight, when they beheld the things that were done, returned smiting their breasts. ^49And all his acquaintance, and the women that followed with him from Galilee, stood afar off, seeing these things. ^50And behold, a man named Joseph, who was a councillor, a good and righteous man ^51(he had not consented to their counsel and deed), a man of Arimathaea, a city of the Jews, who was looking for the kingdom of God: ^52this man went to Pilate, and asked for the body of Jesus. ^53And he took it down, and wrapped it in a linen cloth, and laid him in a tomb that was hewn in stone, where never man had yet lain. ^54And it was the day of the Preparation, and the sabbath drew on. ^55And the women, who had come with him out of Galilee, followed after, and beheld the tomb, and how his body was laid. ^56And they returned, and prepared spices and ointments. And on the sabbath they rested according to the commandment.

Luke 24

24

^1But on the first day of the week, at early dawn, they came unto the tomb, bringing the spices which they had prepared. ^2And they found the stone rolled away from the tomb. ^3And they entered in, and found not the body of the Lord Jesus. ^4And it came to pass, while they were perplexed thereabout, behold, two men stood by them in dazzling apparel: ^5and as they were affrighted and bowed down their faces to the earth, they said unto them, Why seek ye the living among the dead? ^6He is not here, but is risen: remember how he spake unto you when he was yet in Galilee, ^7saying that the Son of man must be delivered up into the hands of sinful men, and be crucified, and the third day rise again. ^8And they remembered his words, ^9and returned from the tomb, and told all these things to the eleven, and to all the rest. ^10Now they were Mary Magdalene, and Joanna, and Mary the mother of James: and the other women with them told these things unto the apostles. ^11And these words appeared in their sight as idle talk; and they disbelieved them. ^12But Peter arose, and ran unto the tomb; and stooping and looking in, he seeth the linen cloths by themselves; and he departed to his home, wondering at that which was come to pass. ^13And behold, two of them were going that very day to a village named Emmaus, which was threescore furlongs from Jerusalem. ^14And they communed with each other of all these things which had happened. ^15And it came to pass, while they communed and questioned together, that Jesus himself drew near, and went with them. ^16But their eyes were holden that they should not know him. ^17And he said unto them, What communications are these that ye have one with another, as ye walk? And they stood still, looking sad. ^18And one of them, named Cleopas, answering said unto him, Dost thou alone sojourn in Jerusalem and not know the things which are come to pass there in these days? ^19And he said unto them, What things? And they said unto him, The things concerning Jesus the Nazarene, who was a prophet mighty in deed and word before God and all the people: ^20and how the chief priests and our rulers delivered him up to be condemned to death, and crucified him. ^21But we hoped that it was he who should redeem Israel. Yea and besides all this, it is now the third day since these things came to pass. ^22Moreover certain women of our company amazed us, having been early at the tomb; ^23and when they found not his body, they came, saying, that they had also seen a vision of angels, who said that he was alive. ^24And certain of them that were with us went to the tomb, and found it even so as the women had said: but him they saw not. ^25And he said unto them, O foolish men, and slow of heart to believe in all that the prophets have spoken! ^26Behooved it not the Christ to suffer these things, and to enter into his glory? ^27And beginning from Moses and from all the prophets, he interpreted to them in all the spans the things concerning himself. ^28And they drew nigh unto the village, whither they were going: and he made as though he would go further. ^29And they constrained him, saying, Abide with us; for it is toward evening, and the day is now far spent. And he went in to abide with them. ^30And it came to pass, when he had sat down with them to meat, he took the bread and blessed; and breaking it he gave to them. ^31And their eyes were opened, and they knew him; and he vanished out of their sight. ^32And they said one to another, Was not our heart burning within us, while he spake to us in the way, while he opened to us the spans? ^33And they rose up that very hour, and returned to Jerusalem, and found the eleven gathered together, and them that were with them, ^34saying, The Lord is risen indeed, and hath appeared to Simon. ^35And they rehearsed the things that happened in the way, and how he was known of them in the breaking of the bread. ^36And as they spake these things, he himself stood in the midst of them, and saith unto them, Peace be unto you. ^37But they were terrified and affrighted, and supposed that they beheld a spirit. ^38And he said unto them, Why are ye troubled? and wherefore do questionings arise in your heart? ^39See my hands and my feet, that it is I myself: handle me, and see; for a spirit hath not flesh and bones, as ye behold me having. ^40And when he had said this, he showed them his hands and his feet. ^41And while they still disbelieved for joy, and wondered, he said unto them, Have ye here anything to eat? ^42And they gave him a piece of a broiled fish. ^43And he took it, and ate before them. ^44And he said unto them, These are my words which I spake unto you, while I was yet with you, that all things must needs be fulfilled, which are written in the law of Moses, and the prophets, and the psalms, concerning me. ^45Then opened he their mind, that they might understand the spans; ^46and he said unto them, Thus it is written, that the Christ should suffer, and rise again from the dead the third day; ^47and that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in his name unto all the nations, beginning from Jerusalem. ^48Ye are witnesses of these things. ^49And behold, I send forth the promise of my Father upon you: but tarry ye in the city, until ye be clothed with power from on high. ^50And he led them out until they were over against Bethany: and he lifted up his hands, and blessed them. ^51And it came to pass, while he blessed them, he parted from them, and was carried up into heaven. ^52And they worshipped him, and returned to Jerusalem with great joy: ^53and were continually in the temple, blessing God.

Malachi 2

2

^1And now, O ye priests, this commandment is for you. ^2If ye will not hear, and if ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory unto my name, saith Jehovah of hosts, then will I send the curse upon you, and I will curse your blessings; yea, I have cursed them already, because ye do not lay it to heart. ^3Behold, I will rebuke your seed, and will spread dung upon your faces, even the dung of your feasts; and ye shall be taken away with it. ^4And ye shall know that I have sent this commandment unto you, that my covenant may be with Levi, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^5My covenant was with him of life and peace; and I gave them to him that he might fear; and he feared me, and stood in awe of my name. ^6The law of truth was in his mouth, and unrighteousness was not found in his lips: he walked with me in peace and uprightness, and turned many away from iniquity. ^7For the priest's lips should keep knowledge, and they should seek the law at his mouth; for he is the messenger of Jehovah of hosts. ^8But ye are turned aside out of the way; ye have caused many to stumble in the law; ye have corrupted the covenant of Levi, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^9Therefore have I also made you contemptible and base before all the people, according as ye have not kept my ways, but have had respect of persons in the law. ^10Have we not all one father? hath not one God created us? why do we deal treacherously every man against his brother, profaning the covenant of our fathers? ^11Judah hath dealt treacherously, and an abomination is committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah hath profaned the holiness of Jehovah which he loveth, and hath married the daughter of a foreign god. ^12Jehovah will cut off, to the man that doeth this, him that waketh and him that answereth, out of the tents of Jacob, and him that offereth an offering unto Jehovah of hosts. ^13And this again ye do: ye cover the altar of Jehovah with tears, with weeping, and with sighing, insomuch that he regardeth not the offering any more, neither receiveth it with good will at your hand. ^14Yet ye say, Wherefore? Because Jehovah hath been witness between thee and the wife of thy youth, against whom thou hast dealt treacherously, though she is thy companion, and the wife of thy covenant. ^15And did he not make one, although he had the residue of the Spirit? And wherefore one? He sought a godly seed. Therefore take heed to your spirit, and let none deal treacherously against the wife of his youth. ^16For I hate putting away, saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, and him that covereth his garment with violence, saith Jehovah of hosts: therefore take heed to your spirit, that ye deal not treacherously. ^17Ye have wearied Jehovah with your words. Yet ye say, Wherein have we wearied him? In that ye say, Every one that doeth evil is good in the sight of Jehovah, and he delighteth in them; or where is the God of justice?

Malachi 3

3

^1Behold, I send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way before me: and the Lord, whom ye seek, will suddenly come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant, whom ye desire, behold, he cometh, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^2But who can abide the day of his coming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is like a refiner's fire, and like fuller's soap: ^3and he will sit as a refiner and purifier of silver, and he will purify the sons of Levi, and refine them as gold and silver; and they shall offer unto Jehovah offerings in righteousness. ^4Then shall the offering of Judah and Jerusalem be pleasant unto Jehovah, as in the days of old, and as in ancient years. ^5And I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers, and against the adulterers, and against the false swearers, and against those that oppress the hireling in his wages, the widow, and the fatherless, and that turn aside the sojourner from his right, and fear not me, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^6For I, Jehovah, change not; therefore ye, O sons of Jacob, are not consumed. ^7From the days of your fathers ye have turned aside from mine ordinances, and have not kept them. Return unto me, and I will return unto you, saith Jehovah of hosts. But ye say, Wherein shall we return? ^8Will a man rob God? yet ye rob me. But ye say, Wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes and offerings. ^9Ye are cursed with the curse; for ye rob me, even this whole nation. ^10Bring ye the whole tithe into the store-house, that there may be food in my house, and prove me now herewith, saith Jehovah of hosts, if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a blessing, that there shall not be room enough to receive it. ^11And I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes, and he shall not destroy the fruits of your ground; neither shall your vine cast its fruit before the time in the field, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^12And all nations shall call you happy; for ye shall be a delightsome land, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^13Your words have been stout against me, saith Jehovah. Yet ye say, What have we spoken against thee? ^14Ye have said, It is vain to serve God; and what profit is it that we have kept his charge, and that we have walked mournfully before Jehovah of hosts? ^15And now we call the proud happy; yea, they that work wickedness are built up; yea, they tempt God, and escape. ^16Then they that feared Jehovah spake one with another; and Jehovah hearkened, and heard, and a book of remembrance was written before him, for them that feared Jehovah, and that thought upon his name. ^17And they shall be mine, saith Jehovah of hosts, even mine own possession, in the day that I make; and I will spare them, as a man spareth his own son that serveth him. ^18Then shall ye return and discern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that serveth God and him that serveth him not.

Mark 2

2

^1And when he entered again into Capernaum after some days, it was noised that he was in the house. ^2And many were gathered together, so that there was no longer room for them, no, not even about the door: and he spake the word unto them. ^3And they come, bringing unto him a man sick of the palsy, borne of four. ^4And when they could not come nigh unto him for the crowd, they uncovered the roof where he was: and when they had broken it up, they let down the bed whereon the sick of the palsy lay. ^5And Jesus seeing their faith saith unto the sick of the palsy, Son, thy sins are forgiven. ^6But there were certain of the scribes sitting there, and reasoning in their hearts, ^7Why doth this man thus speak? he blasphemeth: who can forgive sins but one, even God? ^8And straightway Jesus, perceiving in his spirit that they so reasoned within themselves, saith unto them, Why reason ye these things in your hearts? ^9Which is easier, to say to the sick of the palsy, Thy sins are forgiven; or to say, Arise, and take up thy bed, and walk? ^10But that ye may know that the Son of man hath authority on earth to forgive sins (he saith to the sick of the palsy), ^11I say unto thee, Arise, take up thy bed, and go unto thy house. ^12And he arose, and straightway took up the bed, and went forth before them all; insomuch that they were all amazed, and glorified God, saying, We never saw it on this fashion. ^13And he went forth again by the sea side; and all the multitude resorted unto him, and he taught them. ^14And as he passed by, he saw Levi the son of Alphaeus sitting at the place of toll, and he saith unto him, Follow me. And he arose and followed him. ^15And it came to pass, that he was sitting at meat in his house, and many publicans and sinners sat down with Jesus and his disciples: for there were many, and they followed him. ^16And the scribes of the Pharisees, when they saw that he was eating with the sinners and publicans, said unto his disciples, How is it that he eateth and drinketh with publicans and sinners? ^17And when Jesus heard it, he saith unto them, They that are whole have no need of a physician, but they that are sick: I came not to call the righteous, but sinners. ^18And John's disciples and the Pharisees were fasting: and they come and say unto him, Why do John's disciples and the disciples of the Pharisees fast, but thy disciples fast not? ^19And Jesus said unto them, Can the sons of the bridechamber fast, while the bridegroom is with them? as long as they have the bridegroom with them, they cannot fast. ^20But the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken away from them, and then will they fast in that day. ^21No man seweth a piece of undressed cloth on an old garment: else that which should fill it up taketh from it, the new from the old, and a worse rent is made. ^22And no man putteth new wine into old wineskins; else the wine will burst the skins, and the wine perisheth, and the skins: but they put new wine into fresh wine-skins. ^23And it came to pass, that he was going on the sabbath day through the grainfields; and his disciples began, as they went, to pluck the ears. ^24And the Pharisees said unto him, Behold, why do they on the sabbath day that which is not lawful? ^25And he said unto them, Did ye never read what David did, when he had need, and was hungry, he, and they that were with him? ^26How he entered into the house of God when Abiathar was high priest, and ate the showbread, which it is not lawful to eat save for the priests, and gave also to them that were with him? ^27And he said unto them, The sabbath was made for man, and not man for the sabbath: ^28so that the Son of man is lord even of the sabbath.

Mark 3

3

^1And he entered again into the synagogue; and there was a man there who had his hand withered. ^2And they watched him, whether he would heal him on the sabbath day; that they might accuse him. ^3And he saith unto the man that had his hand withered, Stand forth. ^4And he saith unto them, Is it lawful on the sabbath day to do good, or to do harm? to save a life, or to kill? But they held their peace. ^5And when he had looked round about on them with anger, being grieved at the hardening of their heart, he saith unto the man, Stretch forth thy hand. And he stretched it forth; and his hand was restored. ^6And the Pharisees went out, and straightway with the Herodians took counsel against him, how they might destroy him. ^7And Jesus with his disciples withdrew to the sea: and a great multitude from Galilee followed; and from Judaea, ^8and from Jerusalem, and from Idumaea, and beyond the Jordan, and about Tyre and Sidon, a great multitude, hearing what great things he did, came unto him. ^9And he spake to his disciples, that a little boat should wait on him because of the crowd, lest they should throng him: ^10for he had healed many; insomuch that as many as had plagues pressed upon him that they might touch him. ^11And the unclean spirits, whensoever they beheld him, fell down before him, and cried, saying, Thou art the Son of God. ^12And he charged them much that they should not make him known. ^13And he goeth up into the mountain, and calleth unto him whom he himself would; and they went unto him. ^14And he appointed twelve, that they might be with him, and that he might send them forth to preach, ^15and to have authority to cast out demons: ^16and Simon he surnamed Peter; ^17and James the son of Zebedee, and John the brother of James; and them he surnamed Boanerges, which is, Sons of thunder: ^18and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James the son of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus, and Simon the Cananaean, ^19and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him. And he cometh into a house. ^20And the multitude cometh together again, so that they could not so much as eat bread. ^21And when his friends heard it, they went out to lay hold on him: for they said, He is beside himself. ^22And the scribes that came down from Jerusalem said, He hath Beelzebub, and, By the prince of the demons casteth he out the demons. ^23And he called them unto him, and said unto them in parables, How can Satan cast out Satan? ^24And if a kingdom be divided against itself, that kingdom cannot stand. ^25And if a house be divided against itself, that house will not be able to stand. ^26And if Satan hath rise up against himself, and is divided, he cannot stand, but hath an end. ^27But no one can enter into the house of the strong man, and spoil his goods, except he first bind the strong man; and then he will spoil his house. ^28Verily I say unto you, All their sins shall be forgiven unto the sons of men, and their blasphemies wherewith soever they shall blaspheme: ^29but whosoever shall blaspheme against the Holy Spirit hath never forgiveness, but is guilty of an eternal sin: ^30because they said, He hath an unclean spirit. ^31And there come his mother and his brethren; and, standing without, they sent unto him, calling him. ^32And a multitude was sitting about him; and they say unto him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren without seek for thee. ^33And he answereth them, and saith, Who is my mother and my brethren? ^34And looking round on them that sat round about him, he saith, Behold, my mother and my brethren! ^35For whosoever shall do the will of God, the same is my brother, and sister, and mother.

Mark 4

4

^1And again he began to teach by the sea side. And there is gathered unto him a very great multitude, so that he entered into a boat, and sat in the sea; and all the multitude were by the sea on the land. ^2And he taught them many things in parables, and said unto them in his teaching, ^3Hearken: Behold, the sower went forth to sow: ^4and it came to pass, as he sowed, some seed fell by the way side, and the birds came and devoured it. ^5And other fell on the rocky ground, where it had not much earth; and straightway it sprang up, because it had no deepness of earth: ^6and when the sun was risen, it was scorched; and because it had no root, it withered away. ^7And other fell among the thorns, and the thorns grew up, and choked it, and it yielded no fruit. ^8And others fell into the good ground, and yielded fruit, growing up and increasing; and brought forth, thirtyfold, and sixtyfold, and a hundredfold. ^9And he said, Who hath ears to hear, let him hear. ^10And when he was alone, they that were about him with the twelve asked of him the parables. ^11And he said unto them, Unto you is given the mystery of the kingdom of God: but unto them that are without, all things are done in parables: ^12that seeing they may see, and not perceive; and hearing they may hear, and not understand; lest haply they should turn again, and it should be forgiven them. ^13And he saith unto them, Know ye not this parable? and how shall ye know all the parables? ^14The sower soweth the word. ^15And these are they by the way side, where the word is sown; and when they have heard, straightway cometh Satan, and taketh away the word which hath been sown in them. ^16And these in like manner are they that are sown upon the rocky places, who, when they have heard the word, straightway receive it with joy; ^17and they have no root in themselves, but endure for a while; then, when tribulation or persecution ariseth because of the word, straightway they stumble. ^18And others are they that are sown among the thorns; these are they that have heard the word, ^19and the cares of the world, and the deceitfulness of riches, and the lusts of other things entering in, choke the word, and it becometh unfruitful. ^20And those are they that were sown upon the good ground; such as hear the word, and accept it, and bear fruit, thirtyfold, and sixtyfold, and a hundredfold. ^21And he said unto them, Is the lamp brought to be put under the bushel, or under the bed, and not to be put on the stand? ^22For there is nothing hid, save that it should be manifested; neither was anything made secret, but that it should come to light. ^23If any man hath ears to hear, let him hear. ^24And he said unto them, Take heed what ye hear: with what measure ye mete it shall be measured unto you; and more shall be given unto you. ^25For he that hath, to him shall be given: and he that hath not, from him shall be taken away even that which he hath. ^26And he said, So is the kingdom of God, as if a man should cast seed upon the earth; ^27and should sleep and rise night and day, and the seed should spring up and grow, he knoweth not how. ^28The earth beareth fruit of herself; first the blade, then the ear, then the full grain in the ear. ^29But when the fruit is ripe, straightway he putteth forth the sickle, because the harvest is come. ^30And he said, How shall we liken the kingdom of God? or in what parable shall we set it forth? ^31It is like a grain of mustard seed, which, when it is sown upon the earth, though it be less than all the seeds that are upon the earth, ^32yet when it is sown, groweth up, and becometh greater than all the herbs, and putteth out great branches; so that the birds of the heaven can lodge under the shadow thereof. ^33And with many such parables spake he the word unto them, as they were able to hear it; ^34and without a parable spake he not unto them: but privately to his own disciples he expounded all things. ^35And on that day, when even was come, he saith unto them, Let us go over unto the other side. ^36And leaving the multitude, they take him with them, even as he was, in the boat. And other boats were with him. ^37And there ariseth a great storm of wind, and the waves beat into the boat, insomuch that the boat was now filling. ^38And he himself was in the stern, asleep on the cushion: and they awake him, and say unto him, Teacher, carest thou not that we perish? ^39And he awoke, and rebuked the wind, and said unto the sea, Peace, be still. And the wind ceased, and there was a great calm. ^40And he said unto them, Why are ye fearful? have ye not yet faith? ^41And they feared exceedingly, and said one to another, Who then is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?

Mark 5

5

^1And they came to the other side of the sea, into the country of the Gerasenes. ^2And when he was come out of the boat, straightway there met him out of the tombs a man with an unclean spirit, ^3who had his dwelling in the tombs: and no man could any more bind him, no, not with a chain; ^4because that he had been often bound with fetters and chains, and the chains had been rent asunder by him, and the fetters broken in pieces: and no man had strength to tame him. ^5And always, night and day, in the tombs and in the mountains, he was crying out, and cutting himself with stones. ^6And when he saw Jesus from afar, he ran and worshipped him; ^7and crying out with a loud voice, he saith, What have I to do with thee, Jesus, thou Son of the Most High God? I adjure thee by God, torment me not. ^8For he said unto him, Come forth, thou unclean spirit, out of the man. ^9And he asked him, What is thy name? And he saith unto him, My name is Legion; for we are many. ^10And he besought him much that he would not send them away out of the country. ^11Now there was there on the mountain side a great herd of swine feeding. ^12And they besought him, saying, Send us into the swine, that we may enter into them. ^13And he gave them leave. And the unclean spirits came out, and entered into the swine: and the herd rushed down the steep into the sea, in number about two thousand; and they were drowned in the sea. ^14And they that fed them fled, and told it in the city, and in the country. And they came to see what it was that had come to pass. ^15And they come to Jesus, and behold him that was possessed with demons sitting, clothed and in his right mind, even him that had the legion: and they were afraid. ^16And they that saw it declared unto them how it befell him that was possessed with demons, and concerning the swine. ^17And they began to beseech him to depart from their borders. ^18And as he was entering into the boat, he that had been possessed with demons besought him that he might be with him. ^19And he suffered him not, but saith unto him, Go to thy house unto thy friends, and tell them how great things the Lord hath done for thee, and how he had mercy on thee. ^20And he went his way, and began to publish in Decapolis how great things Jesus had done for him: and all men marvelled. ^21And when Jesus had crossed over again in the boat unto the other side, a great multitude was gathered unto him; and he was by the sea. ^22And there cometh one of the rulers of the synagogue, Jairus by name; and seeing him, he falleth at his feet, ^23and beseecheth him much, saying, My little daughter is at the point of death: I pray thee, that thou come and lay thy hands on her, that she may be made whole, and live. ^24And he went with him; and a great multitude followed him, and they thronged him. ^25And a woman, who had an issue of blood twelve years, ^26and had suffered many things of many physicians, and had spent all that she had, and was nothing bettered, but rather grew worse, ^27having heard the things concerning Jesus, came in the crowd behind, and touched his garment. ^28For she said, If I touch but his garments, I shall be made whole. ^29And straightway the fountain of her blood was dried up; and she felt in her body that she was healed of her plague. ^30And straightway Jesus, perceiving in himself that the power proceeding from him had gone forth, turned him about in the crowd, and said, Who touched my garments? ^31And his disciples said unto him, Thou seest the multitude thronging thee, and sayest thou, Who touched me? ^32And he looked round about to see her that had done this thing. ^33But the woman fearing and trembling, knowing what had been done to her, came and fell down before him, and told him all the truth. ^34And he said unto her, Daughter, thy faith hath made thee whole; go in peace, and be whole of thy plague. ^35While he yet spake, they come from the ruler of the synagogue's house saying, Thy daughter is dead: why troublest thou the Teacher any further? ^36But Jesus, not heeding the word spoken, saith unto the ruler of the synagogue, Fear not, only believe. ^37And he suffered no man to follow with him, save Peter, and James, and John the brother of James. ^38And they come to the house of the ruler of the synagogue; and he beholdeth a tumult, and many weeping and wailing greatly. ^39And when he was entered in, he saith unto them, Why make ye a tumult, and weep? the child is not dead, but sleepeth. ^40And they laughed him to scorn. But he, having put them all forth, taketh the father of the child and her mother and them that were with him, and goeth in where the child was. ^41And taking the child by the hand, he saith unto her, Talitha cumi; which is, being interpreted, Damsel, I say unto thee, Arise. ^42And straightway the damsel rose up, and walked; for she was twelve years old. And they were amazed straightway with a great amazement. ^43And he charged them much that no man should know this: and he commanded that something should be given her to eat.

Mark 6

6

^1And he went out from thence; and he cometh into his own country; and his disciples follow him. ^2And when the sabbath was come, he began to teach in the synagogue: and many hearing him were astonished, saying, Whence hath this man these things? and, What is the wisdom that is given unto this man, and what mean such mighty works wrought by his hands? ^3Is not this the carpenter, the son of Mary, and brother of James, and Joses, and Judas, and Simon? and are not his sisters here with us? And they were offended in him. ^4And Jesus said unto them, A prophet is not without honor, save in his own country, and among his own kin, and in his own house. ^5And he could there do no mighty work, save that he laid his hands upon a few sick folk, and healed them. ^6And he marvelled because of their unbelief. And he went round about the villages teaching. ^7And he calleth unto him the twelve, and began to send them forth by two and two; and he gave them authority over the unclean spirits; ^8and he charged them that they should take nothing for their journey, save a staff only; no bread, no wallet, no money in their purse; ^9but to go shod with sandals: and, said he, put not on two coats. ^10And he said unto them, Wheresoever ye enter into a house, there abide till ye depart thence. ^11And whatsoever place shall not receive you, and they hear you not, as ye go forth thence, shake off the dust that is under your feet for a testimony unto them. ^12And they went out, and preached that men should repent. ^13And they cast out many demons, and anointed with oil many that were sick, and healed them. ^14And king Herod heard thereof; for his name had become known: and he said, John the Baptizer is risen from the dead, and therefore do these powers work in him. ^15But others said, It is Elijah. And others said, It is a prophet, even as one of the prophets. ^16But Herod, when he heard thereof, said, John, whom I beheaded, he is risen. ^17For Herod himself had sent forth and laid hold upon John, and bound him in prison for the sake of Herodias, his brother Philip's wife; for he had married her. ^18For John said unto Herod, It is not lawful for thee to have thy brother's wife. ^19And Herodias set herself against him, and desired to kill him; and she could not; ^20for Herod feared John, knowing that he was a righteous and holy man, and kept him safe. And when he heard him, he was much perplexed; and he heard him gladly. ^21And when a convenient day was come, that Herod on his birthday made a supper to his lords, and the high captains, and the chief men of Galilee; ^22and when the daughter of Herodias herself came in and danced, she pleased Herod and them that sat at meat with him; and the king said unto the damsel, Ask of me whatsoever thou wilt, and I will give it thee. ^23And he sware unto her, Whatsoever thou shalt ask of me, I will give it thee, unto the half of my kingdom. ^24And she went out, and said unto her mother, What shall I ask? And she said, The head of John the Baptizer. ^25And she came in straightway with haste unto the king, and asked, saying, I will that thou forthwith give me on a platter the head of John the Baptist. ^26And the king was exceeding sorry; but for the sake of his oaths, and of them that sat at meat, he would not reject her. ^27And straightway the king sent forth a soldier of his guard, and commanded to bring his head: and he went and beheaded him in the prison, ^28and brought his head on a platter, and gave it to the damsel; and the damsel gave it to her mother. ^29And when his disciples heard thereof, they came and took up his corpse, and laid it in a tomb. ^30And the apostles gather themselves together unto Jesus; and they told him all things, whatsoever they had done, and whatsoever they had taught. ^31And he saith unto them, Come ye yourselves apart into a desert place, and rest a while. For there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure so much as to eat. ^32And they went away in the boat to a desert place apart. ^33And the people saw them going, and many knew them, and they ran together there on foot from all the cities, and outwent them. ^34And he came forth and saw a great multitude, and he had compassion on them, because they were as sheep not having a shepherd: and he began to teach them many things. ^35And when the day was now far spent, his disciples came unto him, and said, The place is desert, and the day is now far spent; ^36send them away, that they may go into the country and villages round about, and buy themselves somewhat to eat. ^37But he answered and said unto them, Give ye them to eat. And they say unto him, Shall we go and buy two hundred shillings' worth of bread, and give them to eat? ^38And he saith unto them, How many loaves have ye? go and see. And when they knew, they say, Five, and two fishes. ^39And he commanded them that all should sit down by companies upon the green grass. ^40And they sat down in ranks, by hundreds, and by fifties. ^41And he took the five loaves and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, he blessed, and brake the loaves; and he gave to the disciples to set before them; and the two fishes divided he among them all. ^42And they all ate, and were filled. ^43And they took up broken pieces, twelve basketfuls, and also of the fishes. ^44And they that ate the loaves were five thousand men. ^45And straightway he constrained his disciples to enter into the boat, and to go before him unto the other side to Bethsaida, while he himself sendeth the multitude away. ^46And after he had taken leave of them, he departed into the mountain to pray. ^47And when even was come, the boat was in the midst of the sea, and he alone on the land. ^48And seeing them distressed in rowing, for the wind was contrary unto them, about the fourth watch of the night he cometh unto them, walking on the sea; and he would have passed by them: ^49but they, when they saw him walking on the sea, supposed that it was a ghost, and cried out; ^50for they all saw him, and were troubled. But he straightway spake with them, and saith unto them, Be of good cheer: it is I; be not afraid. ^51And he went up unto them into the boat; and the wind ceased: and they were sore amazed in themselves; ^52for they understood not concerning the loaves, but their heart was hardened. ^53And when they had crossed over, they came to the land unto Gennesaret, and moored to the shore. ^54And when they were come out of the boat, straightway the people knew him, ^55and ran round about that whole region, and began to carry about on their beds those that were sick, where they heard he was. ^56And wheresoever he entered, into villages, or into cities, or into the country, they laid the sick in the marketplaces, and besought him that they might touch if it were but the border of his garment: and as many as touched him were made whole.

Mark 8

8

^1In those days, when there was again a great multitude, and they had nothing to eat, he called unto him his disciples, and saith unto them, ^2I have compassion on the multitude, because they continue with me now three days, and have nothing to eat: ^3and if I send them away fasting to their home, they will faint on the way; and some of them are come from far. ^4And his disciples answered him, Whence shall one be able to fill these men with bread here in a desert place? ^5And he asked them, How many loaves have ye? And they said, Seven. ^6And he commandeth the multitude to sit down on the ground: and he took the seven loaves, and having given thanks, he brake, and gave to his disciples, to set before them; and they set them before the multitude. ^7And they had a few small fishes: and having blessed them, he commanded to set these also before them. ^8And they ate, and were filled: and they took up, of broken pieces that remained over, seven baskets. ^9And they were about four thousand: and he sent them away. ^10And straightway he entered into the boat with his disciples, and came into the parts of Dalmanutha. ^11And the Pharisees came forth, and began to question with him, seeking of him a sign from heaven, trying him. ^12And he sighed deeply in his spirit, and saith, Why doth this generation seek a sign? verily I say unto you, There shall no sign be given unto this generation. ^13And he left them, and again entering into the boat departed to the other side. ^14And they forgot to take bread; and they had not in the boat with them more than one loaf. ^15And he charged them, saying, Take heed, beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the leaven of Herod. ^16And they reasoned one with another, saying, We have no bread. ^17And Jesus perceiving it saith unto them, Why reason ye, because ye have no bread? do ye not yet perceive, neither understand? have ye your heart hardened? ^18Having eyes, see ye not? and having ears, hear ye not? and do ye not remember? ^19When I brake the five loaves among the five thousand, how many baskets full of broken pieces took ye up? They say unto him, Twelve. ^20And when the seven among the four thousand, how many basketfuls of broken pieces took ye up? And they say unto him, Seven. ^21And he said unto them, Do ye not yet understand? ^22And they come unto Bethsaida. And they bring to him a blind man, and beseech him to touch him. ^23And he took hold of the blind man by the hand, and brought him out of the village; and when he had spit on his eyes, and laid his hands upon him, he asked him, Seest thou aught? ^24And he looked up, and said, I see men; for I behold them as trees, walking. ^25Then again he laid his hands upon his eyes; and he looked stedfastly, and was restored, and saw all things clearly. ^26And he sent him away to his home, saying, Do not even enter into the village. ^27And Jesus went forth, and his disciples, into the villages of Caesarea Philippi: and on the way he asked his disciples, saying unto them, Who do men say that I am? ^28And they told him, saying, John the Baptist; and others, Elijah; but others, One of the prophets. ^29And he asked them, But who say ye that I am? Peter answereth and saith unto him, Thou art the Christ. ^30And he charged them that they should tell no man of him. ^31And he began to teach them, that the Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders, and the chief priests, and the scribes, and be killed, and after three days rise again. ^32And he spake the saying openly. And Peter took him, and began to rebuke him. ^33But he turning about, and seeing his disciples, rebuked Peter, and saith, Get thee behind me, Satan; for thou mindest not the things of God, but the things of men. ^34And he called unto him the multitude with his disciples, and said unto them, If any man would come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me. ^35For whosoever would save his life shall lose it; and whosoever shall lose his life for my sake and the gospel's shall save it. ^36For what doth it profit a man, to gain the whole world, and forfeit his life? ^37For what should a man give in exchange for his life? ^38For whosoever shall be ashamed of me and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of man also shall be ashamed of him, when he cometh in the glory of his Father with the holy angels.

Mark 9

9

^1And he said unto them, Verily I say unto you, There are some here of them that stand by, who shall in no wise taste of death, till they see the kingdom of God come with power. ^2And after six days Jesus taketh with him Peter, and James, and John, and bringeth them up into a high mountain apart by themselves: and he was transfigured before them; ^3and his garments became glistering, exceeding white, so as no fuller on earth can whiten them. ^4And there appeared unto them Elijah with Moses: and they were talking with Jesus. ^5And Peter answereth and saith to Jesus, Rabbi, it is good for us to be here: and let us make three tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah. ^6For he knew not what to answer; for they became sore afraid. ^7And there came a cloud overshadowing them: and there came a voice out of the cloud, This is my beloved Son: hear ye him. ^8And suddenly looking round about, they saw no one any more, save Jesus only with themselves. ^9And as they were coming down from the mountain, he charged them that they should tell no man what things they had seen, save when the Son of man should have risen again from the dead. ^10And they kept the saying, questioning among themselves what the rising again from the dead should mean. ^11And they asked him, saying, How is it that the scribes say that Elijah must first come? ^12And he said unto them, Elijah indeed cometh first, and restoreth all things: and how is it written of the Son of man, that he should suffer many things and be set at nought? ^13But I say unto you, that Elijah is come, and they have also done unto him whatsoever they would, even as it is written of him. ^14And when they came to the disciples, they saw a great multitude about them, and scribes questioning with them. ^15And straightway all the multitude, when they saw him, were greatly amazed, and running to him saluted him. ^16And he asked them, What question ye with them? ^17And one of the multitude answered him, Teacher, I brought unto thee my son, who hath a dumb spirit; ^18and wheresoever it taketh him, it dasheth him down: and he foameth, and grindeth his teeth, and pineth away: and I spake to thy disciples that they should cast it out; and they were not able. ^19And he answereth them and saith, O faithless generation, how long shall I be with you? how long shall I bear with you? bring him unto me. ^20And they brought him unto him: and when he saw him, straightway the spirit tare him grievously; and he fell on the ground, and wallowed foaming. ^21And he asked his father, How long time is it since this hath come unto him? And he said, From a child. ^22And oft-times it hath cast him both into the fire and into the waters, to destroy him: but if thou canst do anything, have compassion on us, and help us. ^23And Jesus said unto him, If thou canst! All things are possible to him that believeth. ^24Straightway the father of the child cried out, and said, I believe; help thou mine unbelief. ^25And when Jesus saw that a multitude came running together, he rebuked the unclean spirit, saying unto him, Thou dumb and deaf spirit, I command thee, come out of him, and enter no more into him. ^26And having cried out, and torn him much, he came out: and the boy became as one dead; insomuch that the more part said, He is dead. ^27But Jesus took him by the hand, and raised him up; and he arose. ^28And when he was come into the house, his disciples asked him privately, How is it that we could not cast it out? ^29And he said unto them, This kind can come out by nothing, save by prayer. ^30And they went forth from thence, and passed through Galilee; and he would not that any man should know it. ^31For he taught his disciples, and said unto them, The Son of man is delivered up into the hands of men, and they shall kill him; and when he is killed, after three days he shall rise again. ^32But they understood not the saying, and were afraid to ask him. ^33And they came to Capernaum: and when he was in the house he asked them, What were ye reasoning on the way? ^34But they held their peace: for they had disputed one with another on the way, who was the greatest. ^35And he sat down, and called the twelve; and he saith unto them, If any man would be first, he shall be last of all, and servant of all. ^36And he took a little child, and set him in the midst of them: and taking him in his arms, he said unto them, ^37Whosoever shall receive one of such little children in my name, receiveth me: and whosoever receiveth me, receiveth not me, but him that sent me. ^38John said unto him, Teacher, we saw one casting out demons in thy name; and we forbade him, because he followed not us. ^39But Jesus said, Forbid him not: for there is no man who shall do a mighty work in my name, and be able quickly to speak evil of me. ^40For he that is not against us is for us. ^41For whosoever shall give you a cup of water to drink, because ye are Christ's, verily I say unto you, he shall in no wise lose his reward. ^42And whosoever shall cause one of these little ones that believe on me to stumble, it were better for him if a great millstone were hanged about his neck, and he were cast into the sea. ^43And if thy hand cause thee to stumble, cut it off: it is good for thee to enter into life maimed, rather than having thy two hands to go into hell, into the unquenchable fire. ^44where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched. ^45And if thy foot cause thee to stumble, cut it off: it is good for thee to enter into life halt, rather than having thy two feet to be cast into hell. ^46where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched. ^47And if thine eye cause thee to stumble, cast it out: it is good for thee to enter into the kingdom of God with one eye, rather than having two eyes to be cast into hell; ^48where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched. ^49For every one shall be salted with fire. ^50Salt is good: but if the salt have lost its saltness, wherewith will ye season it? Have salt in yourselves, and be at peace one with another.

Mark 10

10

^1And he arose from thence and cometh into the borders of Judaea and beyond the Jordan: and multitudes come together unto him again; and, as he was wont, he taught them again. ^2And there came unto him Pharisees, and asked him, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife? trying him. ^3And he answered and said unto them, What did Moses command you? ^4And they said, Moses suffered to write a bill of divorcement, and to put her away. ^5But Jesus said unto them, For your hardness of heart he wrote you this commandment. ^6But from the beginning of the creation, Male and female made he them. ^7For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife; ^8and the two shall become one flesh: so that they are no more two, but one flesh. ^9What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder. ^10And in the house the disciples asked him again of this matter. ^11And he saith unto them, Whosoever shall put away his wife, and marry another, committeth adultery against her: ^12and if she herself shall put away her husband, and marry another, she committeth adultery. ^13And they were bringing unto him little children, that he should touch them: and the disciples rebuked them. ^14But when Jesus saw it, he was moved with indignation, and said unto them, Suffer the little children to come unto me; forbid them not: for to such belongeth the kingdom of God. ^15Verily I say unto you, Whosoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child, he shall in no wise enter therein. ^16And he took them in his arms, and blessed them, laying his hands upon them. ^17And as he was going forth into the way, there ran one to him, and kneeled to him, and asked him, Good Teacher, what shall I do that I may inherit eternal life? ^18And Jesus said unto him, Why callest thou me good? none is good save one, even God. ^19Thou knowest the commandments, Do not kill, Do not commit adultery, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Do not defraud, Honor thy father and mother. ^20And he said unto him, Teacher, all these things have I observed from my youth. ^21And Jesus looking upon him loved him, and said unto him, One thing thou lackest: go, sell whatsoever thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come, follow me. ^22But his countenance fell at the saying, and he went away sorrowful: for he was one that had great possessions. ^23And Jesus looked round about, and saith unto his disciples, How hardly shall they that have riches enter into the kingdom of God! ^24And the disciples were amazed at his words. But Jesus answereth again, and saith unto them, Children, how hard is it for them that trust in riches to enter into the kingdom of God! ^25It is easier for a camel to go through a needle's eye, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God. ^26And they were astonished exceedingly, saying unto him, Then who can be saved? ^27Jesus looking upon them saith, With men it is impossible, but not with God: for all things are possible with God. ^28Peter began to say unto him, Lo, we have left all, and have followed thee. ^29Jesus said, Verily I say unto you, There is no man that hath left house, or brethren, or sisters, or mother, or father, or children, or lands, for my sake, and for the gospel's sake, ^30but he shall receive a hundredfold now in this time, houses, and brethren, and sisters, and mothers, and children, and lands, with persecutions; and in the world to come eternal life. ^31But many that are first shall be last; and the last first. ^32And they were on the way, going up to Jerusalem; and Jesus was going before them: and they were amazed; and they that followed were afraid. And he took again the twelve, and began to tell them the things that were to happen unto him, ^33saying, Behold, we go up to Jerusalem; and the Son of man shall be delivered unto the chief priests and the scribes; and they shall condemn him to death, and shall deliver him unto the Gentiles: ^34and they shall mock him, and shall spit upon him, and shall scourge him, and shall kill him; and after three days he shall rise again. ^35And there come near unto him James and John, the sons of Zebedee, saying unto him, Teacher, we would that thou shouldest do for us whatsoever we shall ask of thee. ^36And he said unto them, What would ye that I should do for you? ^37And they said unto him, Grant unto us that we may sit, one on thy right hand, and one on thy left hand, in thy glory. ^38But Jesus said unto them, Ye know not what ye ask. Are ye able to drink the cup that I drink? or to be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with? ^39And they said unto him, We are able. And Jesus said unto them, The cup that I drink ye shall drink; and with the baptism that I am baptized withal shall ye be baptized: ^40but to sit on my right hand or on my left hand is not mine to give; but it is for them for whom it hath been prepared. ^41And when the ten heard it, they began to be moved with indignation concerning James and John. ^42And Jesus called them to him, and saith unto them, Ye know that they who are accounted to rule over the Gentiles lord it over them; and their great ones exercise authority over them. ^43But it is not so among you: but whosoever would become great among you, shall be your minister; ^44and whosoever would be first among you, shall be servant of all. ^45For the Son of man also came not to be ministered unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransom for many. ^46And they come to Jericho: and as he went out from Jericho, with his disciples and a great multitude, the son of Timaeus, Bartimaeus, a blind beggar, was sitting by the way side. ^47And when he heard that it was Jesus the Nazarene, he began to cry out, and say, Jesus, thou son of David, have mercy on me. ^48And many rebuked him, that he should hold his peace: but he cried out the more a great deal, Thou son of David, have mercy on me. ^49And Jesus stood still, and said, Call ye him. And they call the blind man, saying unto him, Be of good cheer: rise, he calleth thee. ^50And he, casting away his garment, sprang up, and came to Jesus. ^51And Jesus answered him, and said, What wilt thou that I should do unto thee? And the blind man said unto him, Rabboni, that I may receive my sight. ^52And Jesus said unto him, Go thy way; thy faith hath made thee whole. And straightway he received his sight, and followed him in the way.

Mark 11

11

^1And when they draw nigh unto Jerusalem, unto Bethphage and Bethany, at the mount of Olives, he sendeth two of his disciples, ^2and saith unto them, Go your way into the village that is over against you: and straightway as ye enter into it, ye shall find a colt tied, whereon no man ever yet sat; loose him, and bring him. ^3And if any one say unto you, Why do ye this? say ye, The Lord hath need of him; and straightway he will send him back hither. ^4And they went away, and found a colt tied at the door without in the open street; and they loose him. ^5And certain of them that stood there said unto them, What do ye, loosing the colt? ^6And they said unto them even as Jesus had said: and they let them go. ^7And they bring the colt unto Jesus, and cast on him their garments; and he sat upon him. ^8And many spread their garments upon the way; and others branches, which they had cut from the fields. ^9And they that went before, and they that followed, cried, Hosanna; Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord: ^10Blessed is the kingdom that cometh, the kingdom of our father David: Hosanna in the highest. ^11And he entered into Jerusalem, into the temple; and when he had looked round about upon all things, it being now eventide, he went out unto Bethany with the twelve. ^12And on the morrow, when they were come out from Bethany, he hungered. ^13And seeing a fig tree afar off having leaves, he came, if haply he might find anything thereon: and when he came to it, he found nothing but leaves; for it was not the season of figs. ^14And he answered and said unto it, No man eat fruit from thee henceforward for ever. And his disciples heard it. ^15And they come to Jerusalem: and he entered into the temple, and began to cast out them that sold and them that bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the money-changers, and the seats of them that sold the doves; ^16and he would not suffer that any man should carry a vessel through the temple. ^17And he taught, and said unto them, Is it not written, My house shall be called a house of prayer for all the nations? but ye have made it a den of robbers. ^18And the chief priests and the scribes heard it, and sought how they might destroy him: for they feared him, for all the multitude was astonished at his teaching. ^19And every evening he went forth out of the city. ^20And as they passed by in the morning, they saw the fig tree withered away from the roots. ^21And Peter calling to remembrance saith unto him, Rabbi, behold, the fig tree which thou cursedst is withered away. ^22And Jesus answering saith unto them, Have faith in God. ^23Verily I say unto you, Whosoever shall say unto this mountain, Be thou taken up and cast into the sea; and shall not doubt in his heart, but shall believe that what he saith cometh to pass; he shall have it. ^24Therefore I say unto you, All things whatsoever ye pray and ask for, believe that ye receive them, and ye shall have them. ^25And whensoever ye stand praying, forgive, if ye have aught against any one; that your Father also who is in heaven may forgive you your trespasses. ^26But if ye do not forgive, neither will your Father who is in heaven forgive your trespasses. ^27And they come again to Jerusalem: and as he was walking in the temple, there come to him the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders; ^28and they said unto him, By what authority doest thou these things? or who gave thee this authority to do these things? ^29And Jesus said unto them, I will ask of you one question, and answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things. ^30The baptism of John, was it from heaven, or from men? answer me. ^31And they reasoned with themselves, saying, If we shall say, From heaven; He will say, Why then did ye not believe him? ^32But should we say, From men--they feared the people: for all verily held John to be a prophet. ^33And they answered Jesus and say, We know not. And Jesus saith unto them, Neither tell I you by what authority I do these things.

Mark 12

12

^1And he began to speak unto them in parables. A man planted a vineyard, and set a hedge about it, and digged a pit for the winepress, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into another country. ^2And at the season he sent to the husbandmen a servant, that he might receive from the husbandmen of the fruits of the vineyard. ^3And they took him, and beat him, and sent him away empty. ^4And again he sent unto them another servant; and him they wounded in the head, and handled shamefully. ^5And he sent another; and him they killed: and many others; beating some, and killing some. ^6He had yet one, a beloved son: he sent him last unto them, saying, They will reverence my son. ^7But those husbandmen said among themselves, This is the heir; come, let us kill him, and the inheritance shall be ours. ^8And they took him, and killed him, and cast him forth out of the vineyard. ^9What therefore will the lord of the vineyard do? he will come and destroy the husbandmen, and will give the vineyard unto others. ^10Have ye not read even this span:

The stone which the builders rejected,

The same was made the head of the corner;

^11This was from the Lord,

And it is marvellous in our eyes?

^12And they sought to lay hold on him; and they feared the multitude; for they perceived that he spake the parable against them: and they left him, and went away. ^13And they send unto him certain of the Pharisees and of the Herodians, that they might catch him in talk. ^14And when they were come, they say unto him, Teacher, we know that thou art true, and carest not for any one; for thou regardest not the person of men, but of a truth teachest the way of God: Is it lawful to give tribute unto Caesar, or not? ^15Shall we give, or shall we not give? But he, knowing their hypocrisy, said unto them, Why make ye trial of me? bring me a denarius, that I may see it. ^16And they brought it. And he saith unto them, Whose is this image and superscription? And they said unto him, Caesar's. ^17And Jesus said unto them, Render unto Caesar the things that are Caesar's, and unto God the things that are God's. And they marvelled greatly at him. ^18And there come unto him Sadducees, who say that there is no resurrection; and they asked him, saying, ^19Teacher, Moses wrote unto us, If a man's brother die, and leave a wife behind him, and leave no child, that his brother should take his wife, and raise up seed unto his brother. ^20There were seven brethren: and the first took a wife, and dying left no seed; ^21and the second took her, and died, leaving no seed behind him; and the third likewise: ^22and the seven left no seed. Last of all the woman also died. ^23In the resurrection whose wife shall she be of them? for the seven had her to wife. ^24Jesus said unto them, Is it not for this cause that ye err, that ye know not the spans, nor the power of God? ^25For when they shall rise from the dead, they neither marry, nor are given in marriage; but are as angels in heaven. ^26But as touching the dead, that they are raised; have ye not read in the book of Moses, in the place concerning the Bush, how God spake unto him, saying, I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? ^27He is not the God of the dead, but of the living: ye do greatly err. ^28And one of the scribes came, and heard them questioning together, and knowing that he had answered them well, asked him, What commandment is the first of all? ^29Jesus answered, The first is, Hear, O Israel; The Lord our God, the Lord is one: ^30and thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind, and with all thy strength. ^31The second is this, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. There is none other commandment greater than these. ^32And the scribe said unto him, Of a truth, Teacher, thou hast well said that he is one; and there is none other but he: ^33and to love him with all the heart, and with all the understanding, and with all the strength, and to love his neighbor as himself, is much more than all whole burnt-offerings and sacrifices. ^34And when Jesus saw that he answered discreetly, he said unto him, Thou art not far from the kingdom of God. And no man after that durst ask him any question. ^35And Jesus answered and said, as he taught in the temple, How say the scribes that the Christ is the son of David? ^36David himself said in the Holy Spirit,

The Lord said unto my Lord,

Sit thou on my right hand,

Till I make thine enemies the footstool of thy feet.

^37David himself calleth him Lord; and whence is he his son? And the common people heard him gladly. ^38And in his teaching he said, Beware of the scribes, who desire to walk in long robes, and to have salutations in the marketplaces, ^39and chief seats in the synagogues, and chief places at feasts: ^40they that devour widows' houses, and for a pretence make long prayers; these shall receive greater condemnation. ^41And he sat down over against the treasury, and beheld how the multitude cast money into the treasury: and many that were rich cast in much. ^42And there came a poor widow, and she cast in two mites, which make a farthing. ^43And he called unto him his disciples, and said unto them, Verily I say unto you, This poor widow cast in more than all they that are casting into the treasury: ^44for they all did cast in of their superfluity; but she of her want did cast in all that she had, even all her living.

Mark 13

13

^1And as he went forth out of the temple, one of his disciples saith unto him, Teacher, behold, what manner of stones and what manner of buildings! ^2And Jesus said unto him, Seest thou these great buildings? there shall not be left here one stone upon another, which shall not be thrown down. ^3And as he sat on the mount of Olives over against the temple, Peter and James and John and Andrew asked him privately, ^4Tell us, when shall these things be? and what shall be the sign when these things are all about to be accomplished? ^5And Jesus began to say unto them, Take heed that no man lead you astray. ^6Many shall come in my name, saying, I am he; and shall lead many astray. ^7And when ye shall hear of wars and rumors of wars, be not troubled: these things must needs come to pass; but the end is not yet. ^8For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; there shall be earthquakes in divers places; there shall be famines: these things are the beginning of travail. ^9But take ye heed to yourselves: for they shall deliver you up to councils; and in synagogues shall ye be beaten; and before governors and kings shall ye stand for my sake, for a testimony unto them. ^10And the gospel must first be preached unto all the nations. ^11And when they lead you to judgment, and deliver you up, be not anxious beforehand what ye shall speak: but whatsoever shall be given you in that hour, that speak ye; for it is not ye that speak, but the Holy Spirit. ^12And brother shall deliver up brother to death, and the father his child; and children shall rise up against parents, and cause them to be put to death. ^13And ye shall be hated of all men for my name's sake: but he that endureth to the end, the same shall be saved. ^14But when ye see the abomination of desolation standing where he ought not (let him that readeth understand), then let them that are in Judaea flee unto the mountains: ^15and let him that is on the housetop not go down, nor enter in, to take anything out his house: ^16and let him that is in the field not return back to take his cloak. ^17But woe unto them that are with child and to them that give suck in those days! ^18And pray ye that it be not in the winter. ^19For those days shall be tribulation, such as there hath not been the like from the beginning of the creation which God created until now, and never shall be. ^20And except the Lord had shortened the days, no flesh would have been saved; but for the elect's sake, whom he chose, he shortened the days. ^21And then if any man shall say unto you, Lo, here is the Christ; or, Lo, there; believe it not: ^22for there shall arise false Christs and false prophets, and shall show signs and wonders, that they may lead astray, if possible, the elect. ^23But take ye heed: behold, I have told you all things beforehand. ^24But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun shall be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light, ^25and the stars shall be falling from heaven, and the powers that are in the heavens shall be shaken. ^26And then shall they see the Son of man coming in clouds with great power and glory. ^27And then shall he send forth the angels, and shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from the uttermost part of the earth to the uttermost part of heaven. ^28Now from the fig tree learn her parable: when her branch is now become tender, and putteth forth its leaves, ye know that the summer is nigh; ^29even so ye also, when ye see these things coming to pass, know ye that he is nigh, even at the doors. ^30Verily I say unto you, This generation shall not pass away, until all these things be accomplished. ^31Heaven and earth shall pass away: but my words shall not pass away. ^32But of that day or that hour knoweth no one, not even the angels in heaven, neither the Son, but the Father. ^33Take ye heed, watch and pray: for ye know not when the time is. ^34It is as when a man, sojourning in another country, having left his house, and given authority to his servants, to each one his work, commanded also the porter to watch. ^35Watch therefore: for ye know not when the lord of the house cometh, whether at even, or at midnight, or at cockcrowing, or in the morning; ^36lest coming suddenly he find you sleeping. ^37And what I say unto you I say unto all, Watch.

Mark 14

14

^1Now after two days was the feast of the passover and the unleavened bread: and the chief priests and the scribes sought how they might take him with subtlety, and kill him: ^2for they said, Not during the feast, lest haply there shall be a tumult of the people. ^3And while he was in Bethany in the house of Simon the leper, as he sat at meat, there came a woman having an alabaster cruse of ointment of pure nard very costly; and she brake the cruse, and poured it over his head. ^4But there were some that had indignation among themselves, saying, To what purpose hath this waste of the ointment been made? ^5For this ointment might have been sold for above three hundred shillings, and given to the poor. And they murmured against her. ^6But Jesus said, Let her alone; why trouble ye her? she hath wrought a good work on me. ^7For ye have the poor always with you, and whensoever ye will ye can do them good: but me ye have not always. ^8She hath done what she could; she hath anointed my body beforehand for the burying. ^9And verily I say unto you, Wheresoever the gospel shall be preached throughout the whole world, that also which this woman hath done shall be spoken of for a memorial of her. ^10And Judas Iscariot, he that was one of the twelve, went away unto the chief priests, that he might deliver him unto them. ^11And they, when they heard it, were glad, and promised to give him money. And he sought how he might conveniently deliver him unto them. ^12And on the first day of unleavened bread, when they sacrificed the passover, his disciples say unto him, Where wilt thou that we go and make ready that thou mayest eat the passover? ^13And he sendeth two of his disciples, and saith unto them, Go into the city, and there shall meet you a man bearing a pitcher of water: follow him; ^14and wheresoever he shall enter in, say to the master of the house, The Teacher saith, Where is my guest-chamber, where I shall eat the passover with my disciples? ^15And he will himself show you a large upper room furnished and ready: and there make ready for us. ^16And the disciples went forth, and came into the city, and found as he had said unto them: and they made ready the passover. ^17And when it was evening he cometh with the twelve. ^18And as they sat and were eating, Jesus said, Verily I say unto you, One of you shall betray me, even he that eateth with me. ^19They began to be sorrowful, and to say unto him one by one, Is it I? ^20And he said unto them, It is one of the twelve, he that dippeth with me in the dish. ^21For the Son of man goeth, even as it is written of him: but woe unto that man through whom the Son of man is betrayed! good were it for that man if he had not been born. ^22And as they were eating, he took bread, and when he had blessed, he brake it, and gave to them, and said, Take ye: this is my body. ^23And he took a cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave to them: and they all drank of it. ^24And he said unto them, This is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many. ^25Verily I say unto you, I shall no more drink of the fruit of the vine, until that day when I drink it new in the kingdom of God. ^26And when they had sung a hymn, they went out unto the mount of Olives. ^27And Jesus saith unto them, All ye shall be offended: for it is written, I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep shall be scattered abroad. ^28Howbeit, after I am raised up, I will go before you into Galilee. ^29But Peter said unto him, Although all shall be offended, yet will not I. ^30And Jesus saith unto him, Verily I say unto thee, that thou to-day, even this night, before the cock crow twice, shalt deny me thrice. ^31But he spake exceedingly vehemently, If I must die with thee, I will not deny thee. And in like manner also said they all. ^32And they come unto a place which was named Gethsemane: and he saith unto his disciples, Sit ye here, while I pray. ^33And he taketh with him Peter and James and John, and began to be greatly amazed, and sore troubled. ^34And he saith unto them, My soul is exceeding sorrowful even unto death: abide ye here, and watch. ^35And he went forward a little, and fell on the ground, and prayed that, if it were possible, the hour might pass away from him. ^36And he said, Abba, Father, all things are possible unto thee; remove this cup from me: howbeit not what I will, but what thou wilt. ^37And he cometh, and findeth them sleeping, and saith unto Peter, Simon, sleepest thou? couldest thou not watch one hour? ^38Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation: the spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak. ^39And again he went away, and prayed, saying the same words. ^40And again he came, and found them sleeping, for their eyes were very heavy; and they knew not what to answer him. ^41And he cometh the third time, and saith unto them, Sleep on now, and take your rest: it is enough; the hour is come; behold, the Son of man is betrayed into the hands of sinners. ^42Arise, let us be going: behold, he that betrayeth me is at hand. ^43And straightway, while he yet spake, cometh Judas, one of the twelve, and with him a multitude with swords and staves, from the chief priests and the scribes and the elders. ^44Now he that betrayed him had given them a token, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, that is he; take him, and lead him away safely. ^45And when he was come, straightway he came to him, and saith, Rabbi; and kissed him. ^46And they laid hands on him, and took him. ^47But a certain one of them that stood by drew his sword, and smote the servant of the high priest, and struck off his ear. ^48And Jesus answered and said unto them, Are ye come out, as against a robber, with swords and staves to seize me? ^49I was daily with you in the temple teaching, and ye took me not: but this is done that the spans might be fulfilled. ^50And they all left him, and fled. ^51And a certain young man followed with him, having a linen cloth cast about him, over his naked body: and they lay hold on him; ^52but he left the linen cloth, and fled naked. ^53And they led Jesus away to the high priest: and there come together with him all the chief priests and the elders and the scribes. ^54And Peter had followed him afar off, even within, into the court of the high priest; and he was sitting with the officers, and warming himself in the light of the fire. ^55Now the chief priests and the whole council sought witness against Jesus to put him to death; and found it not. ^56For many bare false witness against him, and their witness agreed not together. ^57And there stood up certain, and bare false witness against him, saying, ^58We heard him say, I will destroy this temple that is made with hands, and in three days I will build another made without hands. ^59And not even so did their witness agree together. ^60And the high priest stood up in the midst, and asked Jesus, saying, Answerest thou nothing? what is it which these witness against thee? ^61But he held his peace, and answered nothing. Again the high priest asked him, and saith unto him, Art thou the Christ, the Son of the Blessed? ^62And Jesus said, I am: and ye shall see the Son of man sitting at the right hand of Power, and coming with the clouds of heaven. ^63And the high priest rent his clothes, and saith, What further need have we of witnesses? ^64Ye have heard the blasphemy: what think ye? And they all condemned him to be worthy of death. ^65And some began to spit on him, and to cover his face, and to buffet him, and to say unto him, Prophesy: and the officers received him with blows of their hands. ^66And as Peter was beneath in the court, there cometh one of the maids of the high priest; ^67and seeing Peter warming himself, she looked upon him, and saith, Thou also wast with the Nazarene, even Jesus. ^68But he denied, saying, I neither know, nor understand what thou sayest: and he went out into the porch; and the cock crew. ^69And the maid saw him, and began again to say to them that stood by, This is one of them. ^70But he again denied it. And after a little while again they that stood by said to Peter, of a truth thou art one of them; for thou art a Galilaean. ^71But he began to curse, and to swear, I know not this man of whom ye speak. ^72And straightway the second time the cock crew. And Peter called to mind the word, how that Jesus said unto him, Before the cock crow twice, thou shalt deny me thrice. And when he thought thereon, he wept.

Mark 15

15

^1And straightway in the morning the chief priests with the elders and scribes, and the whole council, held a consultation, and bound Jesus, and carried him away, and delivered him up to Pilate. ^2And Pilate asked him, Art thou the King of the Jews? And he answering saith unto him, Thou sayest. ^3And the chief priests accused him of many things. ^4And Pilate again asked him, saying, Answerest thou nothing? behold how many things they accuse thee of. ^5But Jesus no more answered anything; insomuch that Pilate marvelled. ^6Now at the feast he used to release unto them one prisoner, whom they asked of him. ^7And there was one called Barabbas, lying bound with them that had made insurrection, men who in the insurrection had committed murder. ^8And the multitude went up and began to ask him to do as he was wont to do unto them. ^9And Pilate answered them, saying, Will ye that I release unto you the King of the Jews? ^10For he perceived that for envy the chief priests had delivered him up. ^11But the chief priests stirred up the multitude, that he should rather release Barabbas unto them. ^12And Pilate again answered and said unto them, What then shall I do unto him whom ye call the King of the Jews? ^13And they cried out again, Crucify him. ^14And Pilate said unto them, Why, what evil hath he done? But they cried out exceedingly, Crucify him. ^15And Pilate, wishing to content the multitude, released unto them Barabbas, and delivered Jesus, when he had scourged him, to be crucified. ^16And the soldiers led him away within the court, which is the Praetorium; and they call together the whole band. ^17And they clothe him with purple, and platting a crown of thorns, they put it on him; ^18and they began to salute him, Hail, King of the Jews! ^19And they smote his head with a reed, and spat upon him, and bowing their knees worshipped him. ^20And when they had mocked him, they took off from him the purple, and put on him his garments. And they lead him out to crucify him. ^21And they compel one passing by, Simon of Cyrene, coming from the country, the father of Alexander and Rufus, to go with them, that he might bear his cross. ^22And they bring him unto the place Golgotha, which is, being interpreted, The place of a skull. ^23And they offered him wine mingled with myrrh: but he received it not. ^24And they crucify him, and part his garments among them, casting lots upon them, what each should take. ^25And it was the third hour, and they crucified him. ^26And the superscription of his accusation was written over, THE KING OF THE JEWS. ^27And with him they crucify two robbers; one on his right hand, and one on his left. ^28And the span was fulfilled, which saith, And he was reckoned with transgressors. ^29And they that passed by railed on him, wagging their heads, and saying, Ha! Thou that destroyest the temple, and buildest it in three days, ^30save thyself, and come down from the cross. ^31In like manner also the chief priests mocking him among themselves with the scribes said, He saved others; himself he cannot save. ^32Let the Christ, the King of Israel, now come down from the cross, that we may see and believe. And they that were crucified with him reproached him. ^33And when the sixth hour was come, there was darkness over the whole land until the ninth hour. ^34And at the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani? which is, being interpreted, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? ^35And some of them that stood by, when they heard it, said, Behold, he calleth Elijah. ^36And one ran, and filling a sponge full of vinegar, put it on a reed, and gave him to drink, saying, Let be; let us see whether Elijah cometh to take him down. ^37And Jesus uttered a loud voice, and gave up the ghost. ^38And the veil of the temple was rent in two from the top to the bottom. ^39And when the centurion, who stood by over against him, saw that he so gave up the ghost, he said, Truly this man was the Son of God. ^40And there were also women beholding from afar: among whom were both Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James the less and of Joses, and Salome; ^41who, when he was in Galilee, followed him, and ministered unto him; and many other women that came up with him unto Jerusalem. ^42And when even was now come, because it was the Preparation, that is, the day before the sabbath, ^43there came Joseph of Arimathaea, a councillor of honorable estate, who also himself was looking for the kingdom of God; and he boldly went in unto Pilate, and asked for the body of Jesus. ^44And Pilate marvelled if he were already dead: and calling unto him the centurion, he asked him whether he had been any while dead. ^45And when he learned it of the centurion, he granted the corpse to Joseph. ^46And he bought a linen cloth, and taking him down, wound him in the linen cloth, and laid him in a tomb which had been hewn out of a rock; and he rolled a stone against the door of the tomb. ^47And Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of Joses beheld where he was laid.

Mark 16

16

^1And when the sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James, and Salome, bought spices, that they might come and anoint him. ^2And very early on the first day of the week, they come to the tomb when the sun was risen. ^3And they were saying among themselves, Who shall roll us away the stone from the door of the tomb? ^4and looking up, they see that the stone is rolled back: for it was exceeding great. ^5And entering into the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, arrayed in a white robe; and they were amazed. ^6And he saith unto them, Be not amazed: ye seek Jesus, the Nazarene, who hath been crucified: he is risen; he is not here: behold, the place where they laid him! ^7But go, tell his disciples and Peter, He goeth before you into Galilee: there shall ye see him, as he said unto you. ^8And they went out, and fled from the tomb; for trembling and astonishment had come upon them: and they said nothing to any one; for they were afraid. ^9Now when he was risen early on the first day of the week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, from whom he had cast out seven demons. ^10She went and told them that had been with him, as they mourned and wept. ^11And they, when they heard that he was alive, and had been seen of her, disbelieved. ^12And after these things he was manifested in another form unto two of them, as they walked, on their way into the country. ^13And they went away and told it unto the rest: neither believed they them. ^14And afterward he was manifested unto the eleven themselves as they sat at meat; and he upbraided them with their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they believed not them that had seen him after he was risen. ^15And he said unto them, Go ye into all the world, and preach the gospel to the whole creation. ^16He that believeth and is baptized shall be saved; but he that disbelieveth shall be condemned. ^17And these signs shall accompany them that believe: in my name shall they cast out demons; they shall speak with new tongues; ^18they shall take up serpents, and if they drink any deadly thing, it shall in no wise hurt them; they shall lay hands on the sick, and they shall recover. ^19So then the Lord Jesus, after he had spoken unto them, was received up into heaven, and sat down at the right hand of God. ^20And they went forth, and preached everywhere, the Lord working with them, and confirming the word by the signs that followed. Amen.

Matthew 2

2

^1Now when Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judaea in the days of Herod the king, behold, Wise-men from the east came to Jerusalem, saying, ^2Where is he that is born King of the Jews? for we saw his star in the east, and are come to worship him. ^3And when Herod the king heard it, he was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him. ^4And gathering together all the chief priests and scribes of the people, he inquired of them where the Christ should be born. ^5And they said unto him, In Bethlehem of Judaea: for thus it is written through the prophet,

^6And thou Bethlehem, land of Judah,

Art in no wise least among the princes of Judah:

For out of thee shall come forth a governor,

Who shall be shepherd of my people Israel.

^7Then Herod privily called the Wise-men, and learned of them exactly what time the star appeared. ^8And he sent them to Bethlehem, and said, Go and search out exactly concerning the young child; and when ye have found him, bring me word, that I also may come and worship him. ^9And they, having heard the king, went their way; and lo, the star, which they saw in the east, went before them, till it came and stood over where the young child was. ^10And when they saw the star, they rejoiced with exceeding great joy. ^11And they came into the house and saw the young child with Mary his mother; and they fell down and worshipped him; and opening their treasures they offered unto him gifts, gold and frankincense and myrrh. ^12And being warned of God in a dream that they should not return to Herod, they departed into their own country another way.

^13Now when they were departed, behold, an angel of the Lord appeareth to Joseph in a dream, saying, Arise and take the young child and his mother, and flee into Egypt, and be thou there until I tell thee: for Herod will seek the young child to destroy him. ^14And he arose and took the young child and his mother by night, and departed into Egypt; ^15and was there until the death of Herod: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the Lord through the prophet, saying, Out of Egypt did I call my son.

^16Then Herod, when he saw that he was mocked of the Wise-men, was exceeding wroth, and sent forth, and slew all the male children that were in Bethlehem, and in all the borders thereof, from two years old and under, according to the time which he had exactly learned of the Wise-men. ^17Then was fulfilled that which was spoken through Jeremiah the prophet, saying,

^18A voice was heard in Ramah,

Weeping and great mourning,

Rachel weeping for her children;

And she would not be comforted, because they are not.

^19But when Herod was dead, behold, an angel of the Lord appeareth in a dream to Joseph in Egypt, saying, ^20Arise and take the young child and his mother, and go into the land of Israel: for they are dead that sought the young child's life. ^21And he arose and took the young child and his mother, and came into the land of Israel. ^22But when he heard that Archelaus was reigning over Judaea in the room of his father Herod, he was afraid to go thither; and being warned of God in a dream, he withdrew into the parts of Galilee, ^23and came and dwelt in a city called Nazareth; that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophets, that he should be called a Nazarene.

Matthew 3

3

^1And in those days cometh John the Baptist, preaching in the wilderness of Judaea, saying, ^2Repent ye; for the kingdom of heaven is at hand. ^3For this is he that was spoken of through Isaiah the prophet, saying,

The voice of one crying in the wilderness,

Make ye ready the way of the Lord,

Make his paths straight.

^4Now John himself had his raiment of camel's hair, and a leathern girdle about his loins; and his food was locusts and wild honey. ^5Then went out unto him Jerusalem, and all Judaea, and all the region round about the Jordan; ^6and they were baptized of him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins. ^7But when he saw many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to his baptism, he said unto them, Ye offspring of vipers, who warned you to flee from the wrath to come? ^8Bring forth therefore fruit worthy of repentance: ^9and think not to say within yourselves, We have Abraham to our father: for I say unto you, that God is able of these stones to raise up children unto Abraham. ^10And even now the axe lieth at the root of the trees: every tree therefore that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire. ^11I indeed baptize you in water unto repentance: but he that cometh after me is mightier than I, whose shoes I am not worthy to bear: he shall baptize you in the Holy Spirit and in fire: ^12whose fan is in his hand, and he will thoroughly cleanse his threshing-floor; and he will gather his wheat into the garner, but the chaff he will burn up with unquenchable fire.

^13Then cometh Jesus from Galilee to the Jordan unto John, to be baptized of him. ^14But John would have hindered him, saying, I have need to be baptized of thee, and comest thou to me? ^15But Jesus answering said unto him, Suffer it now: for thus it becometh us to fulfil all righteousness. Then he suffereth him. ^16And Jesus when he was baptized, went up straightway from the water: and lo, the heavens were opened unto him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending as a dove, and coming upon him; ^17and lo, a voice out of the heavens, saying, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.

Matthew 4

4

^1Then was Jesus led up of the Spirit into the wilderness to be tempted of the devil. ^2And when he had fasted forty days and forty nights, he afterward hungered. ^3And the tempter came and said unto him, If thou art the Son of God, command that these stones become bread. ^4But he answered and said, It is written, Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God. ^5Then the devil taketh him into the holy city; and he set him on the pinnacle of the temple, ^6and saith unto him, If thou art the Son of God, cast thyself down: for it is written,

He shall give his angels charge concerning thee:

and,

On their hands they shall bear thee up,

Lest haply thou dash thy foot against a stone.

^7Jesus said unto him, Again it is written, Thou shalt not make trial of the Lord thy God. ^8Again, the devil taketh him unto an exceeding high mountain, and showeth him all the kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them; ^9and he said unto him, All these things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worship me. ^10Then saith Jesus unto him, Get thee hence, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve. ^11Then the devil leaveth him; and behold, angels came and ministered unto him.

^12Now when he heard that John was delivered up, he withdrew into Galilee; ^13and leaving Nazareth, he came and dwelt in Capernaum, which is by the sea, in the borders of Zebulun and Naphtali: ^14that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying,

^15The land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali,

Toward the sea, beyond the Jordan,

Galilee of the Gentiles,

^16The people that sat in darkness

Saw a great light,

And to them that sat in the region and shadow of death,

To them did light spring up.

^17From that time began Jesus to preach, and to say, Repent ye; for the kingdom of heaven is at hand.

^18And walking by the sea of Galilee, he saw two brethren, Simon who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the sea; for they were fishers. ^19And he saith unto them, Come ye after me, and I will make you fishers of men. ^20And they straightway left the nets, and followed him. ^21And going on from thence he saw two other brethren, James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, in the boat with Zebedee their father, mending their nets; and he called them. ^22And they straightway left the boat and their father, and followed him.

^23And Jesus went about in all Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing all manner of disease and all manner of sickness among the people. ^24And the report of him went forth into all Syria: and they brought unto him all that were sick, holden with divers diseases and torments, possessed with demons, and epileptic, and palsied; and he healed them. ^25And there followed him great multitudes from Galilee and Decapolis and Jerusalem and Judaea and from beyond the Jordan.

Matthew 5

5

^1And seeing the multitudes, he went up into the mountain: and when he had sat down, his disciples came unto him: ^2and he opened his mouth and taught them, saying,

^3Blessed are the poor in spirit: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.

^4Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be comforted.

^5Blessed are the meek: for they shall inherit the earth.

^6Blessed are they that hunger and thirst after righteousness: for they shall be filled.

^7Blessed are the merciful: for they shall obtain mercy.

^8Blessed are the pure in heart: for they shall see God.

^9Blessed are the peacemakers: for they shall be called sons of God.

^10Blessed are they that have been persecuted for righteousness' sake: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven. ^11Blessed are ye when men shall reproach you, and persecute you, and say all manner of evil against you falsely, for my sake. ^12Rejoice, and be exceeding glad: for great is your reward in heaven: for so persecuted they the prophets that were before you.

^13Ye are the salt of the earth: but if the salt have lost its savor, wherewith shall it be salted? it is thenceforth good for nothing, but to be cast out and trodden under foot of men. ^14Ye are the light of the world. A city set on a hill cannot be hid. ^15Neither do men light a lamp, and put it under the bushel, but on the stand; and it shineth unto all that are in the house. ^16Even so let your light shine before men; that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father who is in heaven.

^17Think not that I came to destroy the law or the prophets: I came not to destroy, but to fulfil. ^18For verily I say unto you, Till heaven and earth pass away, one jot or one tittle shall in no wise pass away from the law, till all things be accomplished. ^19Whosoever therefore shall break one of these least commandments, and shall teach men so, shall be called least in the kingdom of heaven: but whosoever shall do and teach them, he shall be called great in the kingdom of heaven. ^20For I say unto you, that except your righteousness shall exceed the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no wise enter into the kingdom of heaven.

^21Ye have heard that it was said to them of old time, Thou shalt not kill; and whosoever shall kill shall be in danger of the judgment: ^22but I say unto you, that every one who is angry with his brother shall be in danger of the judgment; and whosoever shall say to his brother, Raca, shall be in danger of the council; and whosoever shall say, Thou fool, shall be in danger of the hell of fire. ^23If therefore thou art offering thy gift at the altar, and there rememberest that thy brother hath aught against thee, ^24leave there thy gift before the altar, and go thy way, first be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift. ^25Agree with thine adversary quickly, while thou art with him in the way; lest haply the adversary deliver thee to the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the officer, and thou be cast into prison. ^26Verily I say unto thee, thou shalt by no means come out thence, till thou have paid the last farthing.

^27Ye have heard that it was said, Thou shalt not commit adultery: ^28but I say unto you, that every one that looketh on a woman to lust after her hath committed adultery with her already in his heart. ^29And if thy right eye causeth thee to stumble, pluck it out, and cast it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not thy whole body be cast into hell. ^30And if thy right hand causeth thee to stumble, cut it off, and cast it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not thy whole body go into hell. ^31It was said also, Whosoever shall put away his wife, let him give her a writing of divorcement: ^32but I say unto you, that every one that putteth away his wife, saving for the cause of fornication, maketh her an adulteress: and whosoever shall marry her when she is put away committeth adultery.

^33Again, ye have heard that it was said to them of old time, Thou shalt not forswear thyself, but shalt perform unto the Lord thine oaths: ^34but I say unto you, swear not at all; neither by the heaven, for it is the throne of God; ^35nor by the earth, for it is the footstool of his feet; nor by Jerusalem, for it is the city of the great King. ^36Neither shalt thou swear by thy head, for thou canst not make one hair white or black. ^37But let your speech be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay: and whatsoever is more than these is of the evil one.

^38Ye have heard that it was said, An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth: ^39but I say unto you, resist not him that is evil: but whosoever smiteth thee on thy right cheek, turn to him the other also. ^40And if any man would go to law with thee, and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloak also. ^41And whosoever shall compel thee to go one mile, go with him two. ^42Give to him that asketh thee, and from him that would borrow of thee turn not thou away.

^43Ye have heard that it was said, Thou shalt love thy neighbor, and hate thine enemy: ^44but I say unto you, love your enemies, and pray for them that persecute you; ^45that ye may be sons of your Father who is in heaven: for he maketh his sun to rise on the evil and the good, and sendeth rain on the just and the unjust. ^46For if ye love them that love you, what reward have ye? do not even the publicans the same? ^47And if ye salute your brethren only, what do ye more than others? do not even the Gentiles the same? ^48Ye therefore shall be perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect.

Matthew 6

6

^1Take heed that ye do not your righteousness before men, to be seen of them: else ye have no reward with your Father who is in heaven. ^2When therefore thou doest alms, sound not a trumpet before thee, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, that they may have glory of men. Verily I say unto you, They have received their reward. ^3But when thou doest alms, let not thy left hand know what thy right hand doeth: ^4that thine alms may be in secret: and thy Father who seeth in secret shall recompense thee.

^5And when ye pray, ye shall not be as the hypocrites: for they love to stand and pray in the synagogues and in the corners of the streets, that they may be seen of men. Verily I say unto you, They have received their reward. ^6But thou, when thou prayest, enter into thine inner chamber, and having shut thy door, pray to thy Father who is in secret, and thy Father who seeth in secret shall recompense thee. ^7And in praying use not vain repetitions, as the Gentiles do: for they think that they shall be heard for their much speaking. ^8Be not therefore like unto them: for your Father knoweth what things ye have need of, before ye ask him. ^9After this manner therefore pray ye. Our Father who art in heaven, Hallowed be thy name. ^10Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done, as in heaven, so on earth. ^11Give us this day our daily bread. ^12And forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors. ^13And bring us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one. ^14For if ye forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you. ^15But if ye forgive not men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.

^16Moreover when ye fast, be not, as the hypocrites, of a sad countenance: for they disfigure their faces, that they may be seen of men to fast. Verily I say unto you, They have received their reward. ^17But thou, when thou fastest, anoint thy head, and wash thy face; ^18that thou be not seen of men to fast, but of thy Father who is in secret: and thy Father, who seeth in secret, shall recompense thee.

^19Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon the earth, where moth and rust consume, and where thieves break through and steal: ^20but lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust doth consume, and where thieves do not break through nor steal: ^21for where thy treasure is, there will thy heart be also. ^22The lamp of the body is the eye: if therefore thine eye be single, thy whole body shall be full of light. ^23But if thine eye be evil, thy whole body shall be full of darkness. If therefore the light that is in thee be darkness, how great is the darkness! ^24No man can serve two masters; for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or else he will hold to one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon. ^25Therefore I say unto you, be not anxious for your life, what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink; nor yet for your body, what ye shall put on. Is not the life more than the food, and the body than the raiment? ^26Behold the birds of the heaven, that they sow not, neither do they reap, nor gather into barns; and your heavenly Father feedeth them. Are not ye of much more value then they? ^27And which of you by being anxious can add one cubit unto the measure of his life? ^28And why are ye anxious concerning raiment? Consider the lilies of the field, how they grow; they toil not, neither do they spin: ^29yet I say unto you, that even Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these. ^30But if God doth so clothe the grass of the field, which to-day is, and to-morrow is cast into the oven, shall he not much more clothe you, O ye of little faith? ^31Be not therefore anxious, saying, What shall we eat? or, What shall we drink? or, Wherewithal shall we be clothed? ^32For after all these things do the Gentiles seek; for your heavenly Father knoweth that ye have need of all these things. ^33But seek ye first his kingdom, and his righteousness; and all these things shall be added unto you. ^34Be not therefore anxious for the morrow: for the morrow will be anxious for itself. Sufficient unto the day is the evil thereof.

Matthew 7

7

^1Judge not, that ye be not judged. ^2For with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged: and with what measure ye mete, it shall be measured unto you. ^3And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother's eye, but considerest not the beam that is in thine own eye? ^4Or how wilt thou say to thy brother, Let me cast out the mote out of thine eye; and lo, the beam is in thine own eye? ^5Thou hypocrite, cast out first the beam out of thine own eye; and then shalt thou see clearly to cast out the mote out of thy brother's eye.

^6Give not that which is holy unto the dogs, neither cast your pearls before the swine, lest haply they trample them under their feet, and turn and rend you.

^7Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you: ^8for every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth; and to him that knocketh it shall be opened. ^9Or what man is there of you, who, if his son shall ask him for a loaf, will give him a stone; ^10or if he shall ask for a fish, will give him a serpent? ^11If ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your children, how much more shall your Father who is in heaven give good things to them that ask him? ^12All things therefore whatsoever ye would that men should do unto you, even so do ye also unto them: for this is the law and the prophets.

^13Enter ye in by the narrow gate: for wide is the gate, and broad is the way, that leadeth to destruction, and many are they that enter in thereby. ^14For narrow is the gate, and straitened the way, that leadeth unto life, and few are they that find it.

^15Beware of false prophets, who come to you in sheep's clothing, but inwardly are ravening wolves. ^16By their fruits ye shall know them. Do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles? ^17Even so every good tree bringeth forth good fruit; but the corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit. ^18A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit. ^19Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire. ^20Therefore by their fruits ye shall know them. ^21Not every one that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of my Father who is in heaven. ^22Many will say to me in that day, Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy by thy name, and by thy name cast out demons, and by thy name do many mighty works? ^23And then will I profess unto them, I never knew you: depart from me, ye that work iniquity.

^24Every one therefore that heareth these words of mine, and doeth them, shall be likened unto a wise man, who built his house upon the rock: ^25and the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house; and if fell not: for it was founded upon the rock. ^26And every one that heareth these words of mine, and doeth them not, shall be likened unto a foolish man, who built his house upon the sand: ^27and the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and smote upon that house; and it fell: and great was the fall thereof.

^28And it came to pass, when Jesus had finished these words, the multitudes were astonished at his teaching: ^29for he taught them as one having authority, and not as their scribes.

Matthew 8

8

^1And when he was come down from the mountain, great multitudes followed him. ^2And behold, there came to him a leper and worshipped him, saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean. ^3And he stretched forth his hand, and touched him, saying, I will; be thou made clean. And straightway his leprosy was cleansed. ^4And Jesus saith unto him, See thou tell no man; but go, show thyself to the priest, and offer the gift that Moses commanded, for a testimony unto them.

^5And when he was entered into Capernaum, there came unto him a centurion, beseeching him, ^6and saying, Lord, my servant lieth in the house sick of the palsy, grievously tormented. ^7And he saith unto him, I will come and heal him. ^8And the centurion answered and said, Lord, I am not worthy that thou shouldest come under my roof; but only say the word, and my servant shall be healed. ^9For I also am a man under authority, having under myself soldiers: and I say to this one, Go, and he goeth; and to another, Come, and he cometh; and to my servant, Do this, and he doeth it. ^10And when Jesus heard it, he marvelled, and said to them that followed, Verily I say unto you, I have not found so great faith, no, not in Israel. ^11And I say unto you, that many shall come from the east and the west, and shall sit down with Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, in the kingdom of heaven: ^12but the sons of the kingdom shall be cast forth into the outer darkness: there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth. ^13And Jesus said unto the centurion, Go thy way; as thou hast believed, so be it done unto thee. And the servant was healed in that hour.

^14And when Jesus was come into Peter's house, he saw his wife's mother lying sick of a fever. ^15And he touched her hand, and the fever left her; and she arose, and ministered unto him. ^16And when even was come, they brought unto him many possessed with demons: and he cast out the spirits with a word, and healed all that were sick: ^17that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying: Himself took our infirmities, and bare our diseases.

^18Now when Jesus saw great multitudes about him, he gave commandments to depart unto the other side. ^19And there came a scribe, and said unto him, Teacher, I will follow thee whithersoever thou goest. ^20And Jesus saith unto him, The foxes have holes, and the birds of the heaven have nests; but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head. ^21And another of the disciples said unto him, Lord, suffer me first to go and bury my father. ^22But Jesus saith unto him, Follow me; and leave the dead to bury their own dead.

^23And when he was entered into a boat, his disciples followed him. ^24And behold, there arose a great tempest in the sea, insomuch that the boat was covered with the waves: but he was asleep. ^25And they came to him, and awoke him, saying, Save, Lord; we perish. ^26And he saith unto them, Why are ye fearful, O ye of little faith? Then he arose, and rebuked the winds and the sea; and there was a great calm. ^27And the men marvelled, saying, What manner of man is this, that even the winds and the sea obey him?

^28And when he was come to the other side into the country of the Gadarenes, there met him two possessed with demons, coming forth out of the tombs, exceeding fierce, so that no man could pass by that way. ^29And behold, they cried out, saying, What have we to do with thee, thou Son of God? art thou come hither to torment us before the time? ^30Now there was afar off from them a herd of many swine feeding. ^31And the demons besought him, saying, If thou cast us out, send us away into the herd of swine. ^32And he said unto them, Go. And they came out, and went into the swine: and behold, the whole herd rushed down the steep into the sea, and perished in the waters. ^33And they that fed them fled, and went away into the city, and told everything, and what was befallen to them that were possessed with demons. ^34And behold, all the city came out to meet Jesus: and when they saw him, they besought him that he would depart from their borders.

Matthew 9

9

^1And he entered into a boat, and crossed over, and came into his own city. ^2And behold, they brought to him a man sick of the palsy, lying on a bed: and Jesus seeing their faith said unto the sick of the palsy, Son, be of good cheer; thy sins are forgiven. ^3And behold, certain of the scribes said within themselves, This man blasphemeth. ^4And Jesus knowing their thoughts said, Wherefore think ye evil in your hearts? ^5For which is easier, to say, Thy sins are forgiven; or to say, Arise, and walk? ^6But that ye may know that the Son of man hath authority on earth to forgive sins (then saith he to the sick of the palsy), Arise, and take up thy bed, and go up unto thy house. ^7And he arose, and departed to his house. ^8But when the multitudes saw it, they were afraid, and glorified God, who had given such authority unto men.

^9And as Jesus passed by from thence, he saw a man, called Matthew, sitting at the place of toll: and he saith unto him, Follow me. And he arose, and followed him.

^10And it came to pass, as he sat at meat in the house, behold, many publicans and sinners came and sat down with Jesus and his disciples. ^11And when the Pharisees saw it, they said unto his disciples, Why eateth your Teacher with the publicans and sinners? ^12But when he heard it, he said, They that are whole have no need of a physician, but they that are sick. ^13But go ye and learn what this meaneth, I desire mercy, and not sacrifice, for I came not to call the righteous, but sinners.

^14Then come to him the disciples of John, saying, Why do we and the Pharisees fast oft, but thy disciples fast not? ^15And Jesus said unto them, Can the sons of the bridechamber mourn, as long as the bridegroom is with them? but the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken away from them, and then will they fast. ^16And no man putteth a piece of undressed cloth upon an old garment; for that which should fill it up taketh from the garment, and a worse rent is made. ^17Neither do men put new wine into old wine-skins: else the skins burst, and the wine is spilled, and the skins perish: but they put new wine into fresh wine-skins, and both are preserved.

^18While he spake these things unto them, behold, there came a ruler, and worshipped him, saying, My daughter is even now dead: but come and lay thy hand upon her, and she shall live. ^19And Jesus arose, and followed him, and so did his disciples. ^20And behold, a woman, who had an issue of blood twelve years, came behind him, and touched the border of his garment: ^21for she said within herself, If I do but touch his garment, I shall be made whole. ^22But Jesus turning and seeing her said, Daughter, be of good cheer; thy faith hath made thee whole. And the woman was made whole from that hour. ^23And when Jesus came into the ruler's house, and saw the flute-players, and the crowd making a tumult, ^24he said, Give place: for the damsel is not dead, but sleepeth. And they laughed him to scorn. ^25But when the crowd was put forth, he entered in, and took her by the hand; and the damsel arose. ^26And the fame hereof went forth into all that land.

^27And as Jesus passed by from thence, two blind men followed him, crying out, and saying, Have mercy on us, thou son of David. ^28And when he was come into the house, the blind men came to him: and Jesus saith unto them, Believe ye that I am able to do this? They say unto him, Yea, Lord. ^29Then touched he their eyes, saying, According to your faith be it done unto you. ^30And their eyes were opened. And Jesus strictly charged them, saying, See that no man know it. ^31But they went forth, and spread abroad his fame in all that land.

^32And as they went forth, behold, there was brought to him a dumb man possessed with a demon. ^33And when the demon was cast out, the dumb man spake: and the multitudes marvelled, saying, It was never so seen in Israel. ^34But the Pharisees said, By the prince of the demons casteth he out demons.

^35And Jesus went about all the cities and the villages, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing all manner of disease and all manner of sickness. ^36But when he saw the multitudes, he was moved with compassion for them, because they were distressed and scattered, as sheep not having a shepherd. ^37Then saith he unto his disciples, The harvest indeed is plenteous, but the laborers are few. ^38Pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he send forth laborers into his harvest.

Matthew 10

10

^1And he called unto him his twelve disciples, and gave them authority over unclean spirits, to cast them out, and to heal all manner of disease and all manner of sickness.

^2Now the names of the twelve apostles are these: The first, Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother; James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother; ^3Philip, and Bartholomew; Thomas, and Matthew the publican; James the son of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus; ^4Simon the Cananaean, and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.

^5These twelve Jesus sent forth, and charged them, saying, Go not into any way of the Gentiles, and enter not into any city of the Samaritans: ^6but go rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. ^7And as ye go, preach, saying, The kingdom of heaven is at hand. ^8Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse the lepers, cast out demons: freely ye received, freely give. ^9Get you no gold, nor silver, nor brass in your purses; ^10no wallet for your journey, neither two coats, nor shoes, nor staff: for the laborer is worthy of his food. ^11And into whatsoever city or village ye shall enter, search out who in it is worthy; and there abide till ye go forth. ^12And as ye enter into the house, salute it. ^13And if the house be worthy, let your peace come upon it: but if it be not worthy, let your peace return to you. ^14And whosoever shall not receive you, nor hear your words, as ye go forth out of that house or that city, shake off the dust of your feet. ^15Verily I say unto you, It shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgment, than for that city.

^16Behold, I send you forth as sheep in the midst of wolves: be ye therefore wise as serpents, and harmless as doves. ^17But beware of men: for they will deliver you up to councils, and in theirs synagogues they will scourge you; ^18yea and before governors and kings shall ye be brought for my sake, for a testimony to them and to the Gentiles. ^19But when they deliver you up, be not anxious how or what ye shall speak: for it shall be given you in that hour what ye shall speak. ^20For it is not ye that speak, but the Spirit of your Father that speaketh in you. ^21And brother shall deliver up brother to death, and the father his child: and children shall rise up against parents, and cause them to be put to death. ^22And ye shall be hated of all men for my name's sake: but he that endureth to the end, the same shall be saved. ^23But when they persecute you in this city, flee into the next: for verily I say unto you, Ye shall not have gone through the cities of Israel, till the Son of man be come.

^24A disciple is not above his teacher, nor a servant above his lord. ^25It is enough for the disciple that he be as his teacher, and the servant as his lord. If they have called the master of the house Beelzebub, how much more them of his household! ^26Fear them not therefore: for there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed; and hid, that shall not be known. ^27What I tell you in the darkness, speak ye in the light; and what ye hear in the ear, proclaim upon the house-tops. ^28And be not afraid of them that kill the body, but are not able to kill the soul: but rather fear him who is able to destroy both soul and body in hell. ^29Are not two sparrows sold for a penny? and not one of them shall fall on the ground without your Father: ^30but the very hairs of your head are all numbered. ^31Fear not therefore: ye are of more value than many sparrows. ^32Every one therefore who shall confess me before men, him will I also confess before my Father who is in heaven. ^33But whosoever shall deny me before men, him will I also deny before my Father who is in heaven.

^34Think not that I came to send peace on the earth: I came not to send peace, but a sword. ^35For I came to set a man at variance against his father, and the daughter against her mother, and the daughter in law against her mother in law: ^36and a man's foes shall be they of his own household. ^37He that loveth father or mother more than me is not worthy of me; and he that loveth son or daughter more than me is not worthy of me. ^38And he that doth not take his cross and follow after me, is not worthy of me. ^39He that findeth his life shall lose it; and he that loseth his life for my sake shall find it.

^40He that receiveth you receiveth me, and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me. ^41He that receiveth a prophet in the name of a prophet shall receive a prophet's reward: and he that receiveth a righteous man in the name of a righteous man shall receive a righteous man's reward. ^42And whosoever shall give to drink unto one of these little ones a cup of cold water only, in the name of a disciple, verily I say unto you he shall in no wise lose his reward.

Matthew 11

11

^1And it came to pass when Jesus had finished commanding his twelve disciples, he departed thence to teach and preach in their cities. ^2Now when John heard in the prison the works of the Christ, he sent by his disciples ^3and said unto him, Art thou he that cometh, or look we for another? ^4And Jesus answered and said unto them, Go and tell John the things which ye hear and see: ^5the blind receive their sight, and the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, and the deaf hear, and the dead are raised up, and the poor have good tidings preached to them. ^6And blessed is he, whosoever shall find no occasion of stumbling in me.

^7And as these went their way, Jesus began to say unto the multitudes concerning John, What went ye out into the wilderness to behold? a reed shaken with the wind? ^8But what went ye out to see? a man clothed in soft raiment? Behold, they that wear soft raiment are in king's houses. ^9But wherefore went ye out? to see a prophet? Yea, I say unto you, and much more than a prophet. ^10This is he, of whom it is written,

Behold, I send my messenger before thy face,

Who shall prepare thy way before thee.

^11Verily I say unto you, Among them that are born of women there hath not arisen a greater than John the Baptist: yet he that is but little in the kingdom of heaven is greater than he. ^12And from the days of John the Baptist until now the kingdom of heaven suffereth violence, and men of violence take it by force. ^13For all the prophets and the law prophesied until John. ^14And if ye are willing to receive it, this is Elijah, that is to come. ^15He that hath ears to hear, let him hear. ^16But whereunto shall I liken this generation? It is like unto children sitting in the marketplaces, who call unto their fellows ^17and say, We piped unto you, and ye did not dance; we wailed, and ye did not mourn. ^18For John came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, He hath a demon. ^19The Son of man came eating and drinking, and they say, Behold, a gluttonous man and a winebibber, a friend of publicans and sinners! And wisdom is justified by her works.

^20Then began he to upbraid the cities wherein most of his mighty works were done, because they repented not. ^21Woe unto thee, Chorazin! woe unto thee, Bethsaida! for if the mighty works had been done in Tyre and Sidon which were done in you, they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes. ^22But I say unto you, it shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon in the day of judgment than for you. ^23And thou, Capernaum, shalt thou be exalted unto heaven? thou shalt go down unto Hades: for if the mighty works had been done in Sodom which were done in thee, it would have remained until this day. ^24But I say unto you that it shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom in the day of judgment, than for thee.

^25At that season Jesus answered and said, I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that thou didst hide these things from the wise and understanding, and didst reveal them unto babes: ^26yea, Father, for so it was well-pleasing in thy sight. ^27All things have been delivered unto me of my Father: and no one knoweth the Son, save the Father; neither doth any know the Father, save the Son, and he to whomsoever the Son willeth to reveal him. ^28Come unto me, all ye that labor and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest. ^29Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall find rest unto your souls. ^30For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.

Matthew 12

12

^1At that season Jesus went on the sabbath day through the grainfields; and his disciples were hungry and began to pluck ears and to eat. ^2But the Pharisees, when they saw it, said unto him, Behold, thy disciples do that which it is not lawful to do upon the sabbath. ^3But he said unto them, Have ye not read what David did, when he was hungry, and they that were with him; ^4how he entered into the house of God, and ate the showbread, which it was not lawful for him to eat, neither for them that were with him, but only for the priests? ^5Or have ye not read in the law, that on the sabbath day the priests in the temple profane the sabbath, and are guiltless? ^6But I say unto you, that one greater than the temple is here. ^7But if ye had known what this meaneth, I desire mercy, and not sacrifice, ye would not have condemned the guiltless. ^8For the Son of man is lord of the sabbath.

^9And he departed thence, and went into their synagogue: ^10and behold, a man having a withered hand. And they asked him, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath day? that they might accuse him. ^11And he said unto them, What man shall there be of you, that shall have one sheep, and if this fall into a pit on the sabbath day, will he not lay hold on it, and lift it out? ^12How much then is a man of more value than a sheep! Wherefore it is lawful to do good on the sabbath day. ^13Then saith he to the man, Stretch forth thy hand. And he stretched it forth; and it was restored whole, as the other. ^14But the Pharisees went out, and took counsel against him, how they might destroy him.

^15And Jesus perceiving it withdrew from thence: and many followed him; and he healed them all, ^16and charged them that they should not make him known: ^17that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying,

^18Behold, my servant whom I have chosen;

My beloved in whom my soul is well pleased:

I will put my Spirit upon him,

And he shall declare judgment to the Gentiles.

^19He shall not strive, nor cry aloud;

Neither shall any one hear his voice in the streets.

^20A bruised reed shall he not break,

And smoking flax shall he not quench,

Till he send forth judgment unto victory.

^21And in his name shall the Gentiles hope.

^22Then was brought unto him one possessed with a demon, blind and dumb: and he healed him, insomuch that the dumb man spake and saw. ^23And all the multitudes were amazed, and said, Can this be the son of David? ^24But when the Pharisees heard it, they said, This man doth not cast out demons, but by Beelzebub the prince of the demons. ^25And knowing their thoughts he said unto them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation; and every city or house divided against itself shall not stand: ^26and if Satan casteth out Satan, he is divided against himself; how then shall his kingdom stand? ^27And if I by Beelzebub cast out demons, by whom do your sons cast them out? therefore shall they be your judges. ^28But if I by the Spirit of God cast out demons, then is the kingdom of God come upon you. ^29Or how can one enter into the house of the strong man, and spoil his goods, except he first bind the strong man? and then he will spoil his house. ^30He that is not with me is against me, and he that gathereth not with me scattereth. ^31Therefore I say unto you, Every sin and blasphemy shall be forgiven unto men; but the blasphemy against the Spirit shall not be forgiven. ^32And whosoever shall speak a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him; but whosoever shall speak against the Holy Spirit, it shall not be forgiven him, neither in this world, nor in that which is to come. ^33Either make the tree good, and its fruit good; or make the tree corrupt, and its fruit corrupt: for the tree is known by its fruit. ^34Ye offspring of vipers, how can ye, being evil, speak good things? for out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaketh. ^35The good man out of his good treasure bringeth forth good things: and the evil man out of his evil treasure bringeth forth evil things. ^36And I say unto you, that every idle word that men shall speak, they shall give account thereof in the day of judgment. ^37For by thy words thou shalt be justified, and by thy words thou shalt be condemned.

^38Then certain of the scribes and Pharisees answered him, saying, Teacher, we would see a sign from thee. ^39But he answered and said unto them, An evil and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign; and there shall no sign be given it but the sign of Jonah the prophet: ^40for as Jonah was three days and three nights in the belly of the whale; so shall the Son of man be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth. ^41The men of Nineveh shall stand up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for they repented at the preaching of Jonah; and behold, a greater than Jonah is here. ^42The queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and behold, a greater than Solomon is here. ^43But the unclean spirit, when he is gone out of the man, passeth through waterless places, seeking rest, and findeth it not. ^44Then he saith, I will return into my house whence I came out; and when he is come, he findeth it empty, swept, and garnished. ^45Then goeth he, and taketh with himself seven other spirits more evil than himself, and they enter in and dwell there: and the last state of that man becometh worse than the first. Even so shall it be also unto this evil generation.

^46While he was yet speaking to the multitudes, behold, his mother and his brethren stood without, seeking to speak to him. ^47And one said unto him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren stand without, seeking to speak to thee. ^48But he answered and said unto him that told him, Who is my mother? and who are my brethren? ^49And he stretched forth his hand towards his disciples, and said, Behold, my mother and my brethren! ^50For whosoever shall do the will of my Father who is in heaven, he is my brother, and sister, and mother.

Matthew 13

13

^1On that day went Jesus out of the house, and sat by the sea side. ^2And there were gathered unto him great multitudes, so that he entered into a boat, and sat; and all the multitude stood on the beach. ^3And he spake to them many things in parables, saying, Behold, the sower went forth to sow; ^4and as he sowed, some seeds fell by the way side, and the birds came and devoured them: ^5and others fell upon the rocky places, where they had not much earth: and straightway they sprang up, because they had no deepness of earth: ^6and when the sun was risen, they were scorched; and because they had no root, they withered away. ^7And others fell upon the thorns; and the thorns grew up and choked them: ^8and others fell upon the good ground, and yielded fruit, some a hundredfold, some sixty, some thirty. ^9He that hath ears, let him hear.

^10And the disciples came, and said unto him, Why speakest thou unto them in parables? ^11And he answered and said unto them, Unto you it is given to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven, but to them it is not given. ^12For whosoever hath, to him shall be given, and he shall have abundance: but whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that which he hath. ^13Therefore speak I to them in parables; because seeing they see not, and hearing they hear not, neither do they understand. ^14And unto them is fulfilled the prophecy of Isaiah, which saith,

By hearing ye shall hear, and shall in no wise understand;

And seeing ye shall see, and shall in no wise perceive:

^15For this people's heart is waxed gross,

And their ears are dull of hearing,

And their eyes they have closed;

Lest haply they should perceive with their eyes,

And hear with their ears,

And understand with their heart,

And should turn again,

And I should heal them.

^16But blessed are your eyes, for they see; and your ears, for they hear. ^17For verily I say unto you, that many prophets and righteous men desired to see the things which ye see, and saw them not; and to hear the things which ye hear, and heard them not. ^18Hear then ye the parable of the sower. ^19When any one heareth the word of the kingdom, and understandeth it not, then cometh the evil one, and snatcheth away that which hath been sown in his heart. This is he that was sown by the way side. ^20And he that was sown upon the rocky places, this is he that heareth the word, and straightway with joy receiveth it; ^21yet hath he not root in himself, but endureth for a while; and when tribulation or persecution ariseth because of the word, straightway he stumbleth. ^22And he that was sown among the thorns, this is he that heareth the word; and the care of the world, and the deceitfulness of riches, choke the word, and he becometh unfruitful. ^23And he that was sown upon the good ground, this is he that heareth the word, and understandeth it; who verily beareth fruit, and bringeth forth, some a hundredfold, some sixty, some thirty.

^24Another parable set he before them, saying, The kingdom of heaven is likened unto a man that sowed good seed in his field: ^25but while men slept, his enemy came and sowed tares also among the wheat, and went away. ^26But when the blade sprang up and brought forth fruit, then appeared the tares also. ^27And the servants of the householder came and said unto him, Sir, didst thou not sow good seed in thy field? whence then hath it tares? ^28And he said unto them, An enemy hath done this. And the servants say unto him, Wilt thou then that we go and gather them up? ^29But he saith, Nay; lest haply while ye gather up the tares, ye root up the wheat with them. ^30Let both grow together until the harvest: and in the time of the harvest I will say to the reapers, Gather up first the tares, and bind them in bundles to burn them; but gather the wheat into my barn.

^31Another parable set he before them, saying, The kingdom of heaven is like unto a grain of mustard seed, which a man took, and sowed in his field: ^32which indeed is less than all seeds; but when it is grown, it is greater than the herbs, and becometh a tree, so that the birds of the heaven come and lodge in the branches thereof.

^33Another parable spake he unto them; The kingdom of heaven is like unto leaven, which a woman took, and hid in three measures of meal, till it was all leavened.

^34All these things spake Jesus in parables unto the multitudes; and without a parable spake he nothing unto them: ^35that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophet, saying,

I will open my mouth in parables;

I will utter things hidden from the foundation of the world.

^36Then he left the multitudes, and went into the house: and his disciples came unto him, saying, Explain unto us the parable of the tares of the field. ^37And he answered and said, He that soweth the good seed is the Son of man; ^38and the field is the world; and the good seed, these are the sons of the kingdom; and the tares are the sons of the evil one; ^39and the enemy that sowed them is the devil: and the harvest is the end of the world; and the reapers are angels. ^40As therefore the tares are gathered up and burned with fire; so shall it be in the end of the world. ^41The Son of man shall send forth his angels, and they shall gather out of his kingdom all things that cause stumbling, and them that do iniquity, ^42and shall cast them into the furnace of fire: there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth. ^43Then shall the righteous shine forth as the sun in the kingdom of their Father. He that hath ears, let him hear.

^44The kingdom of heaven is like unto a treasure hidden in the field; which a man found, and hid; and in his joy he goeth and selleth all that he hath, and buyeth that field.

^45Again, the kingdom of heaven is like unto a man that is a merchant seeking goodly pearls: ^46and having found one pearl of great price, he went and sold all that he had, and bought it.

^47Again, the kingdom of heaven is like unto a net, that was cast into the sea, and gathered of every kind: ^48which, when it was filled, they drew up on the beach; and they sat down, and gathered the good into vessels, but the bad they cast away. ^49So shall it be in the end of the world: the angels shall come forth, and sever the wicked from among the righteous, ^50and shall cast them into the furnace of fire: there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth.

^51Have ye understood all these things? They say unto him, Yea. ^52And he said unto them, Therefore every scribe who hath been made a disciple to the kingdom of heaven is like unto a man that is a householder, who bringeth forth out of his treasure things new and old.

^53And it came to pass, when Jesus had finished these parables, he departed thence.

^54And coming into his own country he taught them in their synagogue, insomuch that they were astonished, and said, Whence hath this man this wisdom, and these mighty works? ^55Is not this the carpenter's son? is not his mother called Mary? and his brethren, James, and Joseph, and Simon, and Judas? ^56And his sisters, are they not all with us? Whence then hath this man all these things? ^57And they were offended in him. But Jesus said unto them, A prophet is not without honor, save in his own country, and in his own house. ^58And he did not many mighty works there because of their unbelief.

Matthew 14

14

^1At that season Herod the tetrarch heard the report concerning Jesus, ^2and said unto his servants, This is John the Baptist; he is risen from the dead; and therefore do these powers work in him. ^3For Herod had laid hold on John, and bound him, and put him in prison for the sake of Herodias, his brother Philip's wife. ^4For John said unto him, It is not lawful for thee to have her. ^5And when he would have put him to death, he feared the multitude, because they counted him as a prophet. ^6But when Herod's birthday came, the daughter of Herodias danced in the midst, and pleased Herod. ^7Whereupon he promised with an oath to give her whatsoever she should ask. ^8And she, being put forward by her mother, saith, Give me here on a platter the head of John the Baptist. ^9And the king was grieved; but for the sake of his oaths, and of them that sat at meat with him, he commanded it to be given; ^10and he sent and beheaded John in the prison. ^11And his head was brought on a platter, and given to the damsel: and she brought it to her mother. ^12And his disciples came, and took up the corpse, and buried him; and they went and told Jesus.

^13Now when Jesus heard it, he withdrew from thence in a boat, to a desert place apart: and when the multitudes heard thereof, they followed him on foot from the cities. ^14And he came forth, and saw a great multitude, and he had compassion on them, and healed their sick. ^15And when even was come, the disciples came to him, saying, The place is desert, and the time is already past; send the multitudes away, that they may go into the villages, and buy themselves food. ^16But Jesus said unto them, They have no need to go away; give ye them to eat. ^17And they say unto him, We have here but five loaves, and two fishes. ^18And he said, Bring them hither to me. ^19And he commanded the multitudes to sit down on the grass; and he took the five loaves, and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, he blessed, and brake and gave the loaves to the disciples, and the disciples to the multitudes. ^20And they all ate, and were filled: and they took up that which remained over of the broken pieces, twelve baskets full. ^21And they that did eat were about five thousand men, besides women and children.

^22And straightway he constrained the disciples to enter into the boat, and to go before him unto the other side, till he should send the multitudes away. ^23And after he had sent the multitudes away, he went up into the mountain apart to pray: and when even was come, he was there alone. ^24But the boat was now in the midst of the sea, distressed by the waves; for the wind was contrary. ^25And in the fourth watch of the night he came unto them, walking upon the sea. ^26And when the disciples saw him walking on the sea, they were troubled, saying, It is a ghost; and they cried out for fear. ^27But straightway Jesus spake unto them, saying Be of good cheer; it is I; be not afraid. ^28And Peter answered him and said, Lord, if it be thou, bid me come unto them upon the waters. ^29And he said, Come. And Peter went down from the boat, and walked upon the waters to come to Jesus. ^30But when he saw the wind, he was afraid; and beginning to sink, he cried out, saying, Lord, save me. ^31And immediately Jesus stretched forth his hand, and took hold of him, and saith unto him, O thou of little faith, wherefore didst thou doubt? ^32And when they were gone up into the boat, the wind ceased. ^33And they that were in the boat worshipped him, saying, Of a truth thou art the Son of God.

^34And when they had crossed over, they came to the land, unto Gennesaret. ^35And when the men of that place knew him, they sent into all that region round about, and brought unto him all that were sick, ^36and they besought him that they might only touch the border of his garment: and as many as touched were made whole.

Matthew 15

15

^1Then there come to Jesus from Jerusalem Pharisees and scribes, saying, ^2Why do thy disciples transgress the tradition of the elders? for they wash not their hands when they eat bread. ^3And he answered and said unto them, Why do ye also transgress the commandment of God because of your tradition? ^4For God said, Honor thy father and thy mother: and, He that speaketh evil of father or mother, let him die the death. ^5But ye say, whosoever shall say to his father or his mother, That wherewith thou mightest have been profited by me is given to God; ^6he shall not honor his father. And ye have made void the word of God because of your tradition. ^7Ye hypocrites, well did Isaiah prophesy of you, saying,

^8This people honoreth me with their lips;

But their heart is far from me.

^9But in vain do they worship me,

Teaching as their doctrines the precepts of men.

^10And he called to him the multitude, and said unto them, Hear, and understand: ^11Not that which entereth into the mouth defileth the man; but that which proceedeth out of the mouth, this defileth the man. ^12Then came the disciples, and said unto him, Knowest thou that the Pharisees were offended, when they heard this saying? ^13But he answered and said, Every plant which my heavenly Father planted not, shall be rooted up. ^14Let them alone: they are blind guides. And if the blind guide the blind, both shall fall into a pit. ^15And Peter answered and said unto him, Declare unto us the parable. ^16And he said, Are ye also even yet without understanding? ^17Perceive ye not, that whatsoever goeth into the mouth passeth into the belly, and is cast out into the draught? ^18But the things which proceed out of the mouth come forth out of the heart; and they defile the man. ^19For out of the heart come forth evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, false witness, railings: ^20these are the things which defile the man; but to eat with unwashen hands defileth not the man.

^21And Jesus went out thence, and withdrew into the parts of Tyre and Sidon. ^22And behold, a Canaanitish woman came out from those borders, and cried, saying, Have mercy on me, O Lord, thou son of David; my daughter is grievously vexed with a demon. ^23But he answered her not a word. And his disciples came and besought him, saying, Send her away; for she crieth after us. ^24But he answered and said, I was not sent but unto the lost sheep of the house of Israel. ^25But she came and worshipped him, saying, Lord, help me. ^26And he answered and said, It is not meet to take the children's bread and cast it to the dogs. ^27But she said, Yea, Lord: for even the dogs eat of the crumbs which fall from their masters' table. ^28Then Jesus answered and said unto her, O woman, great is thy faith: be it done unto thee even as thou wilt. And her daughter was healed from that hour.

^29And Jesus departed thence, and came nigh unto the sea of Galilee; and he went up into the mountain, and sat there. ^30And there came unto him great multitudes, having with them the lame, blind, dumb, maimed, and many others, and they cast them down at this feet; and he healed them: ^31insomuch that the multitude wondered, when they saw the dumb speaking, the maimed whole, and lame walking, and the blind seeing: and they glorified the God of Israel.

^32And Jesus called unto him his disciples, and said, I have compassion on the multitude, because they continue with me now three days and have nothing to eat: and I would not send them away fasting, lest haply they faint on the way. ^33And the disciples say unto him, Whence should we have so many loaves in a desert place as to fill so great a multitude? ^34And Jesus said unto them, How many loaves have ye? And they said, Seven, and a few small fishes. ^35And he commanded the multitude to sit down on the ground; ^36and he took the seven loaves and the fishes; and he gave thanks and brake, and gave to the disciples, and the disciples to the multitudes. ^37And they all ate, and were filled: and they took up that which remained over of the broken pieces, seven baskets full. ^38And they that did eat were four thousand men, besides women and children. ^39And he sent away the multitudes, and entered into the boat, and came into the borders of Magadan.

Matthew 16

16

^1And the Pharisees and Sadducees came, and trying him asked him to show them a sign from heaven. ^2But he answered and said unto them, When it is evening, ye say, It will be fair weather: for the heaven is red. ^3And in the morning, It will be foul weather to-day: for the heaven is red and lowering. Ye know how to discern the face of the heaven; but ye cannot discern the signs of the times. ^4An evil and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign; and there shall no sign be given unto it, but the sign of Jonah. And he left them, and departed.

^5And the disciples came to the other side and forgot to take bread. ^6And Jesus said unto them, Take heed and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees. ^7And they reasoned among themselves, saying, We took no bread. ^8And Jesus perceiving it said, O ye of little faith, why reason ye among yourselves, because ye have no bread? ^9Do ye not yet perceive, neither remember the five loaves of the five thousand, and how many baskets ye took up? ^10Neither the seven loaves of the four thousand, and how many baskets ye took up? ^11How is it that ye do not perceive that I spake not to you concerning bread? But beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees. ^12Then understood they that he bade them not beware of the leaven of bread, but of the teaching of the Pharisees and Sadducees.

^13Now when Jesus came into the parts of Caesarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, saying, Who do men say that the Son of man is? ^14And they said, Some say John the Baptist; some, Elijah; and others, Jeremiah, or one of the prophets. ^15He saith unto them, But who say ye that I am? ^16And Simon Peter answered and said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God. ^17And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou, Simon Bar-jonah: for flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father who is in heaven. ^18And I also say unto thee, that thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church; and the gates of Hades shall not prevail against it. ^19I will give unto thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven: and whatsoever thou shalt bind on earth shall be bound in heaven; and whatsoever thou shalt loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven. ^20Then charged he the disciples that they should tell no man that he was the Christ.

^21From that time began Jesus to show unto his disciples, that he must go unto Jerusalem, and suffer many things of the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and the third day be raised up. ^22And Peter took him, and began to rebuke him, saying, Be it far from thee, Lord: this shall never be unto thee. ^23But he turned, and said unto Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan: thou art a stumbling-block unto me: for thou mindest not the things of God, but the things of men. ^24Then said Jesus unto his disciples, If any man would come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me. ^25For whosoever would save his life shall lose it: and whosoever shall lose his life for my sake shall find it. ^26For what shall a man be profited, if he shall gain the whole world, and forfeit his life? or what shall a man give in exchange for his life? ^27For the Son of man shall come in the glory of his Father with his angels; and then shall he render unto every man according to his deeds. ^28Verily I say unto you, there are some of them that stand here, who shall in no wise taste of death, till they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom.

Matthew 17

17

^1And after six days Jesus taketh with him Peter, and James, and John his brother, and bringeth them up into a high mountain apart: ^2and he was transfigured before them; and his face did shine as the sun, and his garments became white as the light. ^3And behold, there appeared unto them Moses and Elijah talking with him. ^4And Peter answered, and said unto Jesus, Lord, it is good for us to be here: if thou wilt, I will make here three tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah. ^5While he was yet speaking, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them: and behold, a voice out of the cloud, saying, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased; hear ye him. ^6And when the disciples heard it, they fell on their face, and were sore afraid. ^7And Jesus came and touched them and said, Arise, and be not afraid. ^8And lifting up their eyes, they saw no one, save Jesus only.

^9And as they were coming down from the mountain, Jesus commanded them, saying, Tell the vision to no man, until the Son of man be risen from the dead. ^10And his disciples asked him, saying, Why then say the scribes that Elijah must first come? ^11And he answered and said, Elijah indeed cometh, and shall restore all things: ^12but I say unto you, that Elijah is come already, and they knew him not, but did unto him whatsoever they would. Even so shall the Son of man also suffer of them. ^13Then understood the disciples that he spake unto them of John the Baptist.

^14And when they were come to the multitude, there came to him a man, kneeling to him, saying, ^15Lord, have mercy on my son: for he is epileptic, and suffereth grievously; for oft-times he falleth into the fire, and off-times into the water. ^16And I brought him to thy disciples, and they could not cure him. ^17And Jesus answered and said, O faithless and perverse generation, how long shall I be with you? how long shall I bear with you? bring him hither to me. ^18And Jesus rebuked him; and the demon went out of him: and the boy was cured from that hour.

^19Then came the disciples to Jesus apart, and said, Why could not we cast it out? ^20And he saith unto them, Because of your little faith: for verily I say unto you, If ye have faith as a grain of mustard seed, ye shall say unto this mountain, Remove hence to yonder place; and it shall remove; and nothing shall be impossible unto you. ^21But this kind goeth not out save by prayer and fasting.

^22And while they abode in Galilee, Jesus said unto them, The Son of man shall be delivered up into the hands of men; ^23and they shall kill him, and the third day he shall be raised up. And they were exceeding sorry.

^24And when they were come to Capernaum, they that received the half-shekel came to Peter, and said, Doth not your teacher pay the half-shekel? ^25He saith, Yea. And when he came into the house, Jesus spake first to him, saying, What thinkest thou, Simon? the kings of the earth, from whom do they receive toll or tribute? from their sons, or from strangers? ^26And when he said, From strangers, Jesus said unto him, Therefore the sons are free. ^27But, lest we cause them to stumble, go thou to the sea, and cast a hook, and take up the fish that first cometh up; and when thou hast opened his mouth, thou shalt find a shekel: that take, and give unto them for me and thee.

Matthew 18

18

^1In that hour came the disciples unto Jesus, saying, Who then is greatest in the kingdom of heaven? ^2And he called to him a little child, and set him in the midst of them, ^3and said, Verily I say unto you, Except ye turn, and become as little children, ye shall in no wise enter into the kingdom of heaven. ^4Whosoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child, the same is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven. ^5And whoso shall receive one such little child in my name receiveth me: ^6But whoso shall cause one of these little ones that believe on me to stumble, it is profitable for him that a great millstone should be hanged about his neck, and that he should be sunk in the depth of the sea.

^7Woe unto the world because of occasions of stumbling! for it must needs be that the occasions come; but woe to that man through whom the occasion cometh! ^8And if thy hand or thy foot causeth thee to stumble, cut it off, and cast it from thee: it is good for thee to enter into life maimed or halt, rather than having two hands or two feet to be cast into the eternal fire. ^9And if thine eye causeth thee to stumble, pluck it out, and cast it from thee: it is good for thee to enter into life with one eye, rather than having two eyes to be cast into the hell of fire. ^10See that ye despise not one of these little ones; for I say unto you, that in heaven their angels do always behold the face of my Father who is in heaven. ^11For the Son of man came to save that which was lost. ^12How think ye? if any man have a hundred sheep, and one of them be gone astray, doth he not leave the ninety and nine, and go unto the mountains, and seek that which goeth astray? ^13And if so be that he find it, verily I say unto you, he rejoiceth over it more than over the ninety and nine which have not gone astray. ^14Even so it is not the will of your Father who is in heaven, that one of these little ones should perish.

^15And if thy brother sin against thee, go, show him his fault between thee and him alone: if he hear thee, thou hast gained thy brother. ^16But if he hear thee not, take with thee one or two more, that at the mouth of two witnesses or three every word may be established. ^17And if he refuse to hear them, tell it unto the church: and if he refuse to hear the church also, let him be unto thee as the Gentile and the publican. ^18Verily I say unto you, what things soever ye shall bind on earth shall be bound in heaven; and what things soever ye shall loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven. ^19Again I say unto you, that if two of you shall agree on earth as touching anything that they shall ask, it shall be done for them of my Father who is in heaven. ^20For where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midst of them.

^21Then came Peter and said to him, Lord, how oft shall my brother sin against me, and I forgive him? until seven times? ^22Jesus saith unto him, I say not unto thee, Until seven times; but, Until seventy times seven. ^23Therefore is the kingdom of heaven likened unto a certain king, who would make a reckoning with his servants. ^24And when he had begun to reckon, one was brought unto him, that owed him ten thousand talents. ^25But forasmuch as he had not wherewith to pay, his lord commanded him to be sold, and his wife, and children, and all that he had, and payment to be made. ^26The servant therefore fell down and worshipped him, saying, Lord, have patience with me, and I will pay thee all. ^27And the lord of that servant, being moved with compassion, released him, and forgave him the debt. ^28But that servant went out, and found one of his fellow-servants, who owed him a hundred shillings: and he laid hold on him, and took him by the throat, saying, Pay what thou owest. ^29So his fellow-servant fell down and besought him, saying, Have patience with me, and I will pay thee. ^30And he would not: but went and cast him into prison, till he should pay that which was due. ^31So when his fellow-servants saw what was done, they were exceeding sorry, and came and told unto their lord all that was done. ^32Then his lord called him unto him, and saith to him, Thou wicked servant, I forgave thee all that debt, because thou besoughtest me: ^33shouldest not thou also have had mercy on thy fellow-servant, even as I had mercy on thee? ^34And his lord was wroth, and delivered him to the tormentors, till he should pay all that was due. ^35So shall also my heavenly Father do unto you, if ye forgive not every one his brother from your hearts.

Matthew 19

19

^1And it came to pass when Jesus had finished these words, he departed from Galilee, and came into the borders of Judaea beyond the Jordan; ^2and great multitudes followed him; and he healed them there.

^3And there came unto him Pharisees, trying him, and saying, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife for every cause? ^4And he answered and said, Have ye not read, that he who made them from the beginning made them male and female, ^5and said, For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife; and the two shall become one flesh? ^6So that they are no more two, but one flesh. What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder. ^7They say unto him, Why then did Moses command to give a bill of divorcement, and to put her away? ^8He saith unto them, Moses for your hardness of heart suffered you to put away your wives: but from the beginning it hath not been so. ^9And I say unto you, Whosoever shall put away his wife, except for fornication, and shall marry another, committeth adultery: and he that marrieth her when she is put away committeth adultery. ^10The disciples say unto him, If the case of the man is so with his wife, it is not expedient to marry. ^11But he said unto them, Not all men can receive this saying, but they to whom it is given. ^12For there are eunuchs, that were so born from their mother's womb: and there are eunuchs, that were made eunuchs by men: and there are eunuchs, that made themselves eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven's sake. He that is able to receive it, let him receive it.

^13Then were there brought unto him little children, that he should lay his hands on them, and pray: and the disciples rebuked them. ^14But Jesus said, Suffer the little children, and forbid them not, to come unto me: for to such belongeth the kingdom of heaven. ^15And he laid his hands on them, and departed thence.

^16And behold, one came to him and said, Teacher, what good thing shall I do, that I may have eternal life? ^17And he said unto him, Why askest thou me concerning that which is good? One there is who is good: but if thou wouldest enter into life, keep the commandments. ^18He saith unto him, Which? And Jesus said, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness, ^19Honor thy father and mother; and, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. ^20The young man saith unto him, All these things have I observed: what lack I yet? ^21Jesus said unto him, If thou wouldest be perfect, go, sell that which thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come, follow me. ^22But when the young man heard the saying, he went away sorrowful; for he was one that had great possessions.

^23And Jesus said unto his disciples, Verily I say unto you, It is hard for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of heaven. ^24And again I say unto you, It is easier for a camel to go through a needle's eye, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God. ^25And when the disciples heard it, they were astonished exceedingly, saying, Who then can be saved? ^26And Jesus looking upon them said to them, With men this is impossible; but with God all things are possible. ^27Then answered Peter and said unto him, Lo, we have left all, and followed thee; what then shall we have? ^28And Jesus said unto them, Verily I say unto you, that ye who have followed me, in the regeneration when the Son of man shall sit on the throne of his glory, ye also shall sit upon twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel. ^29And every one that hath left houses, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or children, or lands, for my name's sake, shall receive a hundredfold, and shall inherit eternal life. ^30But many shall be last that are first; and first that are last.

Matthew 20

20

^1For the kingdom of heaven is like unto a man that was a householder, who went out early in the morning to hire laborers into his vineyard. ^2And when he had agreed with the laborers for a shilling a day, he sent them into his vineyard. ^3And he went out about the third hour, and saw others standing in the marketplace idle; ^4and to them he said, Go ye also into the vineyard, and whatsoever is right I will give you. And they went their way. ^5Again he went out about the sixth and the ninth hour, and did likewise. ^6And about the eleventh hour he went out, and found others standing; and he saith unto them, Why stand ye here all the day idle? ^7They say unto him, Because no man hath hired us. He saith unto them, Go ye also into the vineyard. ^8And when even was come, the lord of the vineyard saith unto his steward, Call the laborers, and pay them their hire, beginning from the last unto the first. ^9And when they came that were hired about the eleventh hour, they received every man a shilling. ^10And when the first came, they supposed that they would receive more; and they likewise received every man a shilling. ^11And when they received it, they murmured against the householder, ^12saying, These last have spent but one hour, and thou hast made them equal unto us, who have borne the burden of the day and the scorching heat. ^13But he answered and said to one of them, Friend, I do thee no wrong: didst not thou agree with me for a shilling? ^14Take up that which is thine, and go thy way; it is my will to give unto this last, even as unto thee. ^15Is it not lawful for me to do what I will with mine own? or is thine eye evil, because I am good? ^16So the last shall be first, and the first last.

^17And as Jesus was going up to Jerusalem, he took the twelve disciples apart, and on the way he said unto them, ^18Behold, we go up to Jerusalem; and the Son of man shall be delivered unto the chief priests and scribes; and they shall condemn him to death, ^19and shall deliver him unto the Gentiles to mock, and to scourge, and to crucify: and the third day he shall be raised up.

^20Then came to him the mother of the sons of Zebedee with her sons, worshipping him, and asking a certain thing of him. ^21And he said unto her, What wouldest thou? She saith unto him, Command that these my two sons may sit, one on thy right hand, and one on thy left hand, in thy kingdom. ^22But Jesus answered and said, Ye know not what ye ask. Are ye able to drink the cup that I am about to drink? They say unto him, We are able. ^23He saith unto them, My cup indeed ye shall drink: but to sit on my right hand, and on my left hand, is not mine to give; but it is for them for whom it hath been prepared of my Father. ^24And when the ten heard it, they were moved with indignation concerning the two brethren. ^25But Jesus called them unto him, and said, Ye know that the rulers of the Gentiles lord it over them, and their great ones exercise authority over them. ^26Not so shall it be among you: but whosoever would become great among you shall be your minister; ^27and whosoever would be first among you shall be your servant: ^28even as the Son of man came not to be ministered unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransom for many.

^29And as they went out from Jericho, a great multitude followed him. ^30And behold, two blind men sitting by the way side, when they heard that Jesus was passing by, cried out, saying, Lord, have mercy on us, thou son of David. ^31And the multitude rebuked them, that they should hold their peace: but they cried out the more, saying, Lord, have mercy on us, thou son of David. ^32And Jesus stood still, and called them, and said, What will ye that I should do unto you? ^33They say unto him, Lord, that our eyes may be opened. ^34And Jesus, being moved with compassion, touched their eyes; and straightway they received their sight, and followed him.

Matthew 21

21

^1And when they drew nigh unto Jerusalem, and came unto Bethphage, unto the mount of Olives, then Jesus sent two disciples, ^2saying unto them, Go into the village that is over against you, and straightway ye shall find an ass tied, and a colt with her: loose them, and bring them unto me. ^3And if any one say aught unto you, ye shall say, The Lord hath need of them; and straightway he will send them. ^4Now this is come to pass, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophet, saying,

^5Tell ye the daughter of Zion,

Behold, thy King cometh unto thee,

Meek, and riding upon an ass,

And upon a colt the foal of an ass.

^6And the disciples went, and did even as Jesus appointed them, ^7and brought the ass, and the colt, and put on them their garments; and he sat thereon. ^8And the most part of the multitude spread their garments in the way; and others cut branches from the trees, and spread them in the way. ^9And the multitudes that went before him, and that followed, cried, saying, Hosanna to the son of David: Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord; Hosanna in the highest. ^10And when he was come into Jerusalem, all the city was stirred, saying, Who is this? ^11And the multitudes said, This is the prophet, Jesus, from Nazareth of Galilee.

^12And Jesus entered into the temple of God, and cast out all them that sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of he money-changers, and the seats of them that sold the doves; ^13and he saith unto them, It is written, My house shall be called a house of prayer: but ye make it a den of robbers. ^14And the blind and the lame came to him in the temple; and he healed them. ^15But when the chief priests and the scribes saw the wonderful things that he did, and the children that were crying in the temple and saying, Hosanna to the son of David; they were moved with indignation, ^16and said unto him, Hearest thou what these are saying? And Jesus saith unto them, Yea: did ye never read, Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings thou has perfected praise? ^17And he left them, and went forth out of the city to Bethany, and lodged there.

^18Now in the morning as he returned to the city, he hungered. ^19And seeing a fig tree by the way side, he came to it, and found nothing thereon, but leaves only; and he saith unto it, Let there be no fruit from thee henceforward for ever. And immediately the fig tree withered away. ^20And when the disciples saw it, they marvelled, saying, How did the fig tree immediately wither away? ^21And Jesus answered and said unto them, Verily I say unto you, If ye have faith, and doubt not, ye shall not only do what is done to the fig tree, but even if ye shall say unto this mountain, Be thou taken up and cast into the sea, it shall be done. ^22And all things, whatsoever ye shall ask in prayer, believing, ye shall receive.

^23And when he was come into the temple, the chief priests and the elders of the people came unto him as he was teaching, and said, By what authority doest thou these things? and who gave thee this authority? ^24And Jesus answered and said unto them, I also will ask you one question, which if ye tell me, I likewise will tell you by what authority I do these things. ^25The baptism of John, whence was it? from heaven or from men? And they reasoned with themselves, saying, If we shall say, From heaven; he will say unto us, Why then did ye not believe him? ^26But if we shall say, From men; we fear the multitude; for all hold John as a prophet. ^27And they answered Jesus, and said, We know not. He also said unto them, Neither tell I you by what authority I do these things. ^28But what think ye? A man had two sons; and he came to the first, and said, Son, go work to-day in the vineyard. ^29And he answered and said, I will not: but afterward he repented himself, and went. ^30And he came to the second, and said likewise. And he answered and said, I go, sir: and went not. ^31Which of the two did the will of his father? They say, The first. Jesus saith unto them, Verily I say unto you, that the publicans and the harlots go into the kingdom of God before you. ^32For John came unto you in the way of righteousness, and ye believed him not; but the publicans and the harlots believed him: and ye, when ye saw it, did not even repent yourselves afterward, that ye might believe him.

^33Hear another parable: There was a man that was a householder, who planted a vineyard, and set a hedge about it, and digged a winepress in it, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into another country. ^34And when the season of the fruits drew near, he sent his servants to the husbandmen, to receive his fruits. ^35And the husbandmen took his servants, and beat one, and killed another, and stoned another. ^36Again, he sent other servants more than the first: and they did unto them in like manner. ^37But afterward he sent unto them his son, saying, They will reverence my son. ^38But the husbandmen, when they saw the son, said among themselves, This is the heir; come, let us kill him, and take his inheritance. ^39And they took him, and cast him forth out of the vineyard, and killed him. ^40When therefore the lord of the vineyard shall come, what will he do unto those husbandmen? ^41They say unto him, He will miserably destroy those miserable men, and will let out the vineyard unto other husbandmen, who shall render him the fruits in their seasons. ^42Jesus saith unto them, Did ye never read in the spans,

The stone which the builders rejected,

The same was made the head of the corner;

This was from the Lord,

And it is marvelous in our eyes?

^43Therefore say I unto you, The kingdom of God shall be taken away from you, and shall be given to a nation bringing forth the fruits thereof. ^44And he that falleth on this stone shall be broken to pieces: but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will scatter him as dust. ^45And when the chief priests and the Pharisees heard his parables, they perceived that he spake of them. ^46And when they sought to lay hold on him, they feared the multitudes, because they took him for a prophet.

Matthew 22

22

^1And Jesus answered and spake again in parables unto them, saying, ^2The kingdom of heaven is likened unto a certain king, who made a marriage feast for his son, ^3and sent forth his servants to call them that were bidden to the marriage feast: and they would not come. ^4Again he sent forth other servants, saying, Tell them that are bidden, Behold, I have made ready my dinner; my oxen and my fatlings are killed, and all things are ready: come to the marriage feast. ^5But they made light of it, and went their ways, one to his own farm, another to his merchandise; ^6and the rest laid hold on his servants, and treated them shamefully, and killed them. ^7But the king was wroth; and he sent his armies, and destroyed those murderers, and burned their city. ^8Then saith he to his servants, The wedding is ready, but they that were bidden were not worthy. ^9Go ye therefore unto the partings of the highways, and as many as ye shall find, bid to the marriage feast. ^10And those servants went out into the highways, and gathered together all as many as they found, both bad and good: and the wedding was filled with guests. ^11But when the king came in to behold the guests, he saw there a man who had not on a wedding-garment: ^12and he saith unto him, Friend, how camest thou in hither not having a wedding-garment? And he was speechless. ^13Then the king said to the servants, Bind him hand and foot, and cast him out into the outer darkness; there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth. ^14For many are called, but few chosen.

^15Then went the Pharisees, and took counsel how they might ensnare him in his talk. ^16And they send to him their disciples, with the Herodians, saying, Teacher, we know that thou art true, and teachest the way of God in truth, and carest not for any one: for thou regardest not the person of men. ^17Tell us therefore, What thinkest thou? Is it lawful to give tribute unto Caesar, or not? ^18But Jesus perceived their wickedness, and said, Why make ye trial of me, ye hypocrites? ^19Show me the tribute money. And they brought unto him a denarius. ^20And he saith unto them, Whose is this image and superscription? ^21They say unto him, Caesar's. Then saith he unto them, Render therefore unto Caesar the things that are Caesar's; and unto God the things that are God's. ^22And when they heard it, they marvelled, and left him, and went away.

^23On that day there came to him Sadducees, they that say that there is no resurrection: and they asked him, ^24saying, Teacher, Moses said, If a man die, having no children, his brother shall marry his wife, and raise up seed unto his brother. ^25Now there were with us seven brethren: and the first married and deceased, and having no seed left his wife unto his brother; ^26in like manner the second also, and the third, unto the seventh. ^27And after them all, the woman died. ^28In the resurrection therefore whose wife shall she be of the seven? for they all had her. ^29But Jesus answered and said unto them, Ye do err, not knowing the spans, nor the power of God. ^30For in the resurrection they neither marry, nor are given in marriage, but are as angels in heaven. ^31But as touching the resurrection of the dead, have ye not read that which was spoken unto you by God, saying, ^32I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? God is not the God of the dead, but of the living. ^33And when the multitudes heard it, they were astonished at his teaching.

^34But the Pharisees, when they heard that he had put the Sadducees to silence, gathered themselves together. ^35And one of them, a lawyer, asked him a question, trying him: ^36Teacher, which is the great commandment in the law? ^37And he said unto him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind. ^38This is the great and first commandment. ^39And a second like unto it is this, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. ^40On these two commandments the whole law hangeth, and the prophets.

^41Now while the Pharisees were gathered together, Jesus asked them a question, ^42saying, What think ye of the Christ? whose son is he? They say unto him, The son of David. ^43He saith unto them, How then doth David in the Spirit call him Lord, saying,

^44The Lord said unto my Lord,

Sit thou on my right hand,

Till I put thine enemies underneath thy feet?

^45If David then calleth him Lord, how is he his son? ^46And no one was able to answer him a word, neither durst any man from that day forth ask him any more questions.

Matthew 23

23

^1Then spake Jesus to the multitudes and to his disciples, ^2saying, The scribes and the Pharisees sit on Moses seat: ^3all things therefore whatsoever they bid you, these do and observe: but do not ye after their works; for they say, and do not. ^4Yea, they bind heavy burdens and grievous to be borne, and lay them on men's shoulders; but they themselves will not move them with their finger. ^5But all their works they do to be seen of men: for they make broad their phylacteries, and enlarge the borders of their garments, ^6and love the chief place at feasts, and the chief seats in the synagogues, ^7and the salutations in the marketplaces, and to be called of men, Rabbi. ^8But be not ye called Rabbi: for one is your teacher, and all ye are brethren. ^9And call no man your father on the earth: for one is your Father, even he who is in heaven. ^10Neither be ye called masters: for one is your master, even the Christ. ^11But he that is greatest among you shall be your servant. ^12And whosoever shall exalt himself shall be humbled; and whosoever shall humble himself shall be exalted.

^13But woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye shut the kingdom of heaven against men: for ye enter not in yourselves, neither suffer ye them that are entering in to enter ^14Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye devour widows' houses, even while for a pretence ye make long prayers: therefore ye shall receive greater condemnation.

^15Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye compass sea and land to make one proselyte; and when he is become so, ye make him twofold more a son of hell than yourselves.

^16Woe unto you, ye blind guides, that say, Whosoever shall swear by the temple, it is nothing; but whosoever shall swear by the gold of the temple, he is a debtor. ^17Ye fools and blind: for which is greater, the gold, or the temple that hath sanctified the gold? ^18And, Whosoever shall swear by the altar, it is nothing; but whosoever shall swear by the gift that is upon it, he is a debtor. ^19Ye blind: for which is greater, the gift, or the altar that sanctifieth the gift? ^20He therefore that sweareth by the altar, sweareth by it, and by all things thereon. ^21And he that sweareth by the temple, sweareth by it, and by him that dwelleth therein. ^22And he that sweareth by the heaven, sweareth by the throne of God, and by him that sitteth thereon.

^23Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye tithe mint and anise and cummin, and have left undone the weightier matters of the law, justice, and mercy, and faith: but these ye ought to have done, and not to have left the other undone. ^24Ye blind guides, that strain out the gnat, and swallow the camel!

^25Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye cleanse the outside of the cup and of the platter, but within they are full from extortion and excess. ^26Thou blind Pharisee, cleanse first the inside of the cup and of the platter, that the outside thereof may become clean also.

^27Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye are like unto whited sepulchres, which outwardly appear beautiful, but inwardly are full of dead men's bones, and of all uncleanness. ^28Even so ye also outwardly appear righteous unto men, but inwardly ye are full of hypocrisy and iniquity.

^29Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye build the sepulchres of the prophets, and garnish the tombs of the righteous, ^30and say, If we had been in the days of our fathers, we should not have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets. ^31Wherefore ye witness to yourselves, that ye are sons of them that slew the prophets. ^32Fill ye up then the measure of your fathers. ^33Ye serpents, ye offspring of vipers, how shall ye escape the judgment of hell? ^34Therefore, behold, I send unto you prophets, and wise men, and scribes: some of them shall ye kill and crucify; and some of them shall ye scourge in your synagogues, and persecute from city to city: ^35that upon you may come all the righteous blood shed on the earth, from the blood of Abel the righteous unto the blood of Zachariah son of Barachiah, whom ye slew between the sanctuary and the altar. ^36Verily I say unto you, All these things shall come upon this generation.

^37O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, that killeth the prophets, and stoneth them that are sent unto her! how often would I have gathered thy children together, even as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, and ye would not! ^38Behold, your house is left unto you desolate. ^39For I say unto you, Ye shall not see me henceforth, till ye shall say, Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.

Matthew 24

24

^1And Jesus went out from the temple, and was going on his way; and his disciples came to him to show him the buildings of the temple. ^2But he answered and said unto them, See ye not all these things? verily I say unto you, There shall not be left here one stone upon another, that shall not be thrown down.

^3And as he sat on the mount of Olives, the disciples came unto him privately, saying, Tell us, when shall these things be? and what shall be the sign of thy coming, and of the end of the world? ^4And Jesus answered and said unto them, Take heed that no man lead you astray. ^5For many shall come in my name, saying, I am the Christ; and shall lead many astray. ^6And ye shall hear of wars and rumors of wars; see that ye be not troubled: for these things must needs come to pass; but the end is not yet. ^7For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; and there shall be famines and earthquakes in divers places. ^8But all these things are the beginning of travail. ^9Then shall they deliver you up unto tribulation, and shall kill you: and ye shall be hated of all the nations for my name's sake. ^10And then shall many stumble, and shall deliver up one another, and shall hate one another. ^11And many false prophets shall arise, and shall lead many astray. ^12And because iniquity shall be multiplied, the love of the many shall wax cold. ^13But he that endureth to the end, the same shall be saved. ^14And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in the whole world for a testimony unto all the nations; and then shall the end come.

^15When therefore ye see the abomination of desolation, which was spoken of through Daniel the prophet, standing in the holy place (let him that readeth understand), ^16then let them that are in Judaea flee unto the mountains: ^17let him that is on the housetop not go down to take out things that are in his house: ^18and let him that is in the field not return back to take his cloak. ^19But woe unto them that are with child and to them that give suck in those days! ^20And pray ye that your flight be not in the winter, neither on a sabbath: ^21for then shall be great tribulation, such as hath not been from the beginning of the world until now, no, nor ever shall be. ^22And except those days had been shortened, no flesh would have been saved: but for the elect's sake those days shall be shortened. ^23Then if any man shall say unto you, Lo, here is the Christ, or, Here; believe it not. ^24For there shall arise false Christs, and false prophets, and shall show great signs and wonders; so as to lead astray, if possible, even the elect. ^25Behold, I have told you beforehand. ^26If therefore they shall say unto you, Behold, he is in the wilderness; go not forth: Behold, he is in the inner chambers; believe it not. ^27For as the lightning cometh forth from the east, and is seen even unto the west; so shall be the coming of the Son of man. ^28Wheresoever the carcase is, there will the eagles be gathered together.

^29But immediately after the tribulation of those days the sun shall be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light, and the stars shall fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens shall be shaken: ^30and then shall appear the sign of the Son of man in heaven: and then shall all the tribes of the earth mourn, and they shall see the Son of man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory. ^31And he shall send forth his angels with a great sound of a trumpet, and they shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from one end of heaven to the other.

^32Now from the fig tree learn her parable: when her branch is now become tender, and putteth forth its leaves, ye know that the summer is nigh; ^33even so ye also, when ye see all these things, know ye that he is nigh, even at the doors. ^34Verily I say unto you, This generation shall not pass away, till all these things be accomplished. ^35Heaven and earth shall pass away, but my words shall not pass away. ^36But of that day and hour knoweth no one, not even the angels of heaven, neither the Son, but the Father only. ^37And as were the days of Noah, so shall be the coming of the Son of man. ^38For as in those days which were before the flood they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark, ^39and they knew not until the flood came, and took them all away; so shall be the coming of the Son of man. ^40Then shall two man be in the field; one is taken, and one is left: ^41two women shall be grinding at the mill; one is taken, and one is left. ^42Watch therefore: for ye know not on what day your Lord cometh. ^43But know this, that if the master of the house had known in what watch the thief was coming, he would have watched, and would not have suffered his house to be broken through. ^44Therefore be ye also ready; for in an hour that ye think not the Son of man cometh.

^45Who then is the faithful and wise servant, whom his lord hath set over his household, to give them their food in due season? ^46Blessed is that servant, whom his lord when he cometh shall find so doing. ^47Verily I say unto you, that he will set him over all that he hath. ^48But if that evil servant shall say in his heart, My lord tarrieth; ^49and shall begin to beat his fellow-servants, and shall eat and drink with the drunken; ^50the lord of that servant shall come in a day when he expecteth not, and in an hour when he knoweth not, ^51and shall cut him asunder, and appoint his portion with the hypocrites: there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth.

Matthew 25

25

^1Then shall the kingdom of heaven be likened unto ten virgins, who took their lamps, and went forth to meet the bridegroom. ^2And five of them were foolish, and five were wise. ^3For the foolish, when they took their lamps, took no oil with them: ^4but the wise took oil in their vessels with their lamps. ^5Now while the bridegroom tarried, they all slumbered and slept. ^6But at midnight there is a cry, Behold, the bridegroom! Come ye forth to meet him. ^7Then all those virgins arose, and trimmed their lamps. ^8And the foolish said unto the wise, Give us of your oil; for our lamps are going out. ^9But the wise answered, saying, Peradventure there will not be enough for us and you: go ye rather to them that sell, and buy for yourselves. ^10And while they went away to buy, the bridegroom came; and they that were ready went in with him to the marriage feast: and the door was shut. ^11Afterward came also the other virgins, saying, Lord, Lord, open to us. ^12But he answered and said, Verily I say unto you, I know you not. ^13Watch therefore, for ye know not the day nor the hour.

^14For it is as when a man, going into another country, called his own servants, and delivered unto them his goods. ^15And unto one he gave five talents, to another two, to another one; to each according to his several ability; and he went on his journey. ^16Straightway he that received the five talents went and traded with them, and made other five talents. ^17In like manner he also that received the two gained other two. ^18But he that received the one went away and digged in the earth, and hid his lord's money. ^19Now after a long time the lord of those servants cometh, and maketh a reckoning with them. ^20And he that received the five talents came and brought other five talents, saying, Lord, thou deliveredst unto me five talents: lo, I have gained other five talents. ^21His lord said unto him, Well done, good and faithful servant: thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will set thee over many things; enter thou into the joy of thy lord. ^22And he also that received the two talents came and said, Lord, thou deliveredst unto me two talents: lo, I have gained other two talents. ^23His lord said unto him, Well done, good and faithful servant: thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will set thee over many things; enter thou into the joy of thy lord. ^24And he also that had received the one talent came and said, Lord, I knew thee that thou art a hard man, reaping where thou didst not sow, and gathering where thou didst not scatter; ^25and I was afraid, and went away and hid thy talent in the earth: lo, thou hast thine own. ^26But his lord answered and said unto him, Thou wicked and slothful servant, thou knewest that I reap where I sowed not, and gather where I did not scatter; ^27thou oughtest therefore to have put my money to the bankers, and at my coming I should have received back mine own with interest. ^28Take ye away therefore the talent from him, and give it unto him that hath the ten talents. ^29For unto every one that hath shall be given, and he shall have abundance: but from him that hath not, even that which he hath shall be taken away. ^30And cast ye out the unprofitable servant into the outer darkness: there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth.

^31But when the Son of man shall come in his glory, and all the angels with him, then shall he sit on the throne of his glory: ^32and before him shall be gathered all the nations: and he shall separate them one from another, as the shepherd separateth the sheep from the goats; ^33and he shall set the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on the left. ^34Then shall the King say unto them on his right hand, Come, ye blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world: ^35for I was hungry, and ye gave me to eat; I was thirsty, and ye gave me drink; I was a stranger, and ye took me in; ^36naked, and ye clothed me; I was sick, and ye visited me; I was in prison, and ye came unto me. ^37Then shall the righteous answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungry, and fed thee? or athirst, and gave thee drink? ^38And when saw we thee a stranger, and took thee in? or naked, and clothed thee? ^39And when saw we thee sick, or in prison, and came unto thee? ^40And the King shall answer and say unto them, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye did it unto one of these my brethren, even these least, ye did it unto me. ^41Then shall he say also unto them on the left hand, Depart from me, ye cursed, into the eternal fire which is prepared for the devil and his angels: ^42for I was hungry, and ye did not give me to eat; I was thirsty, and ye gave me no drink; ^43I was a stranger, and ye took me not in; naked, and ye clothed me not; sick, and in prison, and ye visited me not. ^44Then shall they also answer, saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungry, or athirst, or a stranger, or naked, or sick, or in prison, and did not minister unto thee? ^45Then shall he answer them, saying, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye did it not unto one of these least, ye did it not unto me. ^46And these shall go away into eternal punishment: but the righteous into eternal life.

Matthew 26

26

^1And it came to pass, when Jesus had finished all these words, he said unto his disciples, ^2Ye know that after two days the passover cometh, and the Son of man is delivered up to be crucified. ^3Then were gathered together the chief priests, and the elders of the people, unto the court of the high priest, who was called Caiaphas; ^4and they took counsel together that they might take Jesus by subtlety, and kill him. ^5But they said, Not during the feast, lest a tumult arise among people.

^6Now when Jesus was in Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper, ^7there came unto him a woman having an alabaster cruse of exceeding precious ointment, and she poured it upon his head, as he sat at meat. ^8But when the disciples saw it, they had indignation, saying, To what purpose is this waste? ^9For this ointment might have been sold for much, and given to the poor. ^10But Jesus perceiving it said unto them, Why trouble ye the woman? for she hath wrought a good work upon me. ^11For ye have the poor always with you; but me ye have not always. ^12For in that she poured this ointment upon my body, she did it to prepare me for burial. ^13Verily I say unto you, Wheresoever this gospel shall be preached in the whole world, that also which this woman hath done shall be spoken of for a memorial of her.

^14Then one of the twelve, who was called Judas Iscariot, went unto the chief priests, ^15and said, What are ye willing to give me, and I will deliver him unto you? And they weighed unto him thirty pieces of silver. ^16And from that time he sought opportunity to deliver him unto them.

^17Now on the first day of unleavened bread the disciples came to Jesus, saying, Where wilt thou that we make ready for thee to eat the passover? ^18And he said, Go into the city to such a man, and say unto him, The Teacher saith, My time is at hand; I keep the passover at thy house with my disciples. ^19And the disciples did as Jesus appointed them; and they made ready the passover.

^20Now when even was come, he was sitting at meat with the twelve disciples; ^21and as they were eating, he said, Verily I say unto you, that one of you shall betray me. ^22And they were exceeding sorrowful, and began to say unto him every one, Is it I, Lord? ^23And he answered and said, He that dipped his hand with me in the dish, the same shall betray me. ^24The Son of man goeth, even as it is written of him: but woe unto that man through whom the Son of man is betrayed! good were it for that man if he had not been born. ^25And Judas, who betrayed him, answered and said, Is it I, Rabbi? He saith unto him, Thou hast said.

^26And as they were eating, Jesus took bread, and blessed, and brake it; and he gave to the disciples, and said, Take, eat; this is my body. ^27And he took a cup, and gave thanks, and gave to them, saying, Drink ye all of it; ^28for this is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many unto remission of sins. ^29But I say unto you, I shall not drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine, until that day when I drink it new with you in my Father's kingdom.

^30And when they had sung a hymn, they went out unto the mount of Olives.

^31Then saith Jesus unto them, All ye shall be offended in me this night: for it is written, I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock shall be scattered abroad. ^32But after I am raised up, I will go before you into Galilee. ^33But Peter answered and said unto him, If all shall be offended in thee, I will never be offended. ^34Jesus said unto him, Verily I say unto thee, that this night, before the cock crow, thou shalt deny me thrice. ^35Peter saith unto him, Even if I must die with thee, yet will I not deny thee. Likewise also said all the disciples.

^36Then cometh Jesus with them unto a place called Gethsemane, and saith unto his disciples, Sit ye here, while I go yonder and pray. ^37And he took with him Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, and began to be sorrowful and sore troubled. ^38Then saith he unto them, My soul is exceeding sorrowful, even unto death: abide ye here, and watch with me. ^39And he went forward a little, and fell on his face, and prayed, saying, My Father, if it be possible, let this cup pass away from me: nevertheless, not as I will, but as thou wilt. ^40And he cometh unto the disciples, and findeth them sleeping, and saith unto Peter, What, could ye not watch with me one hour? ^41Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation: the spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak. ^42Again a second time he went away, and prayed, saying, My Father, if this cannot pass away, except I drink it, thy will be done. ^43And he came again and found them sleeping, for their eyes were heavy. ^44And he left them again, and went away, and prayed a third time, saying again the same words. ^45Then cometh he to the disciples, and saith unto them, Sleep on now, and take your rest: behold, the hour is at hand, and the Son of man is betrayed into the hands of sinners. ^46Arise, let us be going: behold, he is at hand that betrayeth me.

^47And while he yet spake, lo, Judas, one of the twelve, came, and with him a great multitude with swords and staves, from the chief priest and elders of the people. ^48Now he that betrayed him gave them a sign, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, that is he: take him. ^49And straightway he came to Jesus, and said, Hail, Rabbi; and kissed him. ^50And Jesus said unto him, Friend, do that for which thou art come. Then they came and laid hands on Jesus, and took him. ^51And behold, one of them that were with Jesus stretched out his hand, and drew his sword, and smote the servant of the high priest, and struck off his ear. ^52Then saith Jesus unto him, Put up again thy sword into its place: for all they that take the sword shall perish with the sword. ^53Or thinkest thou that I cannot beseech my Father, and he shall even now send me more than twelve legions of angels? ^54How then should the spans be fulfilled that thus it must be? ^55In that hour said Jesus to the multitudes, Are ye come out as against a robber with swords and staves to seize me? I sat daily in the temple teaching, and ye took me not. ^56But all this is come to pass, that the spans of the prophets might be fulfilled. Then all the disciples left him, and fled.

^57And they that had taken Jesus led him away to the house of Caiaphas the high priest, where the scribes and the elders were gathered together. ^58But Peter followed him afar off, unto the court of the high priest, and entered in, and sat with the officers, to see the end. ^59Now the chief priests and the whole council sought false witness against Jesus, that they might put him to death; ^60and they found it not, though many false witnesses came. But afterward came two, ^61and said, This man said, I am able to destroy the temple of God, and to build it in three days. ^62And the high priest stood up, and said unto him, Answerest thou nothing? what is it which these witness against thee? ^63But Jesus held his peace. And the high priest said unto him, I adjure thee by the living God, that thou tell us whether thou art the Christ, the Son of God. ^64Jesus said unto him, Thou hast said: nevertheless I say unto you, Henceforth ye shall see the Son of man sitting at the right hand of Power, and coming on the clouds of heaven. ^65Then the high priest rent his garments, saying, He hath spoken blasphemy: what further need have we of witnesses? behold, now ye have heard the blasphemy: ^66what think ye? They answered and said, He is worthy of death. ^67Then did they spit in his face and buffet him: and some smote him with the palms of their hands, ^68saying, Prophesy unto us, thou Christ: who is he that struck thee?

^69Now Peter was sitting without in the court: and a maid came unto him, saying, Thou also wast with Jesus the Galilaean. ^70But he denied before them all, saying, I know not what thou sayest. ^71And when he was gone out into the porch, another maid saw him, and saith unto them that were there, This man also was with Jesus of Nazareth. ^72And again he denied with an oath, I know not the man. ^73And after a little while they that stood by came and said to Peter, Of a truth thou also art one of them; for thy speech maketh thee known. ^74Then began he to curse and to swear, I know not the man. And straightway the cock crew. ^75And Peter remembered the word which Jesus had said, Before the cock crow, thou shalt deny me thrice. And he went out, and wept bitterly.

Matthew 27

27

^1Now when morning was come, all the chief priests and the elders of the people took counsel against Jesus to put him to death: ^2and they bound him, and led him away, and delivered him up to Pilate the governor.

^3Then Judas, who betrayed him, when he saw that he was condemned, repented himself, and brought back the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and elders, ^4saying, I have sinned in that I betrayed innocent blood. But they said, What is that to us? see thou to it. ^5And he cast down the pieces of silver into the sanctuary, and departed; and he went away and hanged himself. ^6And the chief priests took the pieces of silver, and said, It is not lawful to put them into the treasury, since it is the price of blood. ^7And they took counsel, and bought with them the potter's field, to bury strangers in. ^8Wherefore that field was called, the field of blood, unto this day. ^9Then was fulfilled that which was spoken through Jeremiah the prophet, saying, And they took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of him that was priced, whom certain of the children of Israel did price; ^10and they gave them for the potter's field, as the Lord appointed me.

^11Now Jesus stood before the governor: and the governor asked him, saying, Art thou the King of the Jews? And Jesus said unto him, Thou sayest. ^12And when he was accused by the chief priests and elders, he answered nothing. ^13Then saith Pilate unto him, Hearest thou not how many things they witness against thee? ^14And he gave him no answer, not even to one word: insomuch that the governor marvelled greatly. ^15Now at the feast the governor was wont to release unto the multitude one prisoner, whom they would. ^16And they had then a notable prisoner, called Barabbas. ^17When therefore they were gathered together, Pilate said unto them, Whom will ye that I release unto you? Barabbas, or Jesus who is called Christ? ^18For he knew that for envy they had delivered him up. ^19And while he was sitting on the judgment-seat, his wife sent unto him, saying, Have thou nothing to do with that righteous man; for I have suffered many things this day in a dream because of him. ^20Now the chief priests and the elders persuaded the multitudes that they should ask for Barabbas, and destroy Jesus. ^21But the governor answered and said unto them, Which of the two will ye that I release unto you? And they said, Barabbas. ^22Pilate saith unto them, What then shall I do unto Jesus who is called Christ? They all say, Let him be crucified. ^23And he said, Why, what evil hath he done? But they cried out exceedingly, saying, Let him be crucified. ^24So when Pilate saw that he prevailed nothing, but rather that a tumult was arising, he took water, and washed his hands before the multitude, saying, I am innocent of the blood of this righteous man; see ye to it. ^25And all the people answered and said, His blood be on us, and on our children. ^26Then released he unto them Barabbas; but Jesus he scourged and delivered to be crucified.

^27Then the soldiers of the governor took Jesus into the Praetorium, and gathered unto him the whole band. ^28And they stripped him, and put on him a scarlet robe. ^29And they platted a crown of thorns and put it upon his head, and a reed in his right hand; and they kneeled down before him, and mocked him, saying, Hail, King of the Jews! ^30And they spat upon him, and took the reed and smote him on the head. ^31And when they had mocked him, they took off from him the robe, and put on him his garments, and led him away to crucify him.

^32And as they came out, they found a man of Cyrene, Simon by name: him they compelled to go with them, that he might bear his cross.

^33And they were come unto a place called Golgotha, that is to say, The place of a skull, ^34they gave him wine to drink mingled with gall: and when he had tasted it, he would not drink. ^35And when they had crucified him, they parted his garments among them, casting lots; ^36and they sat and watched him there. ^37And they set up over his head his accusation written, THIS IS JESUS THE KING OF THE JEWS. ^38Then are there crucified with him two robbers, one on the right hand and one on the left. ^39And they that passed by railed on him, wagging their heads, ^40and saying, Thou that destroyest the temple, and buildest it in three days, save thyself: if thou art the Son of God, come down from the cross. ^41In like manner also the chief priests mocking him, with the scribes and elders, said, ^42He saved others; himself he cannot save. He is the King of Israel; let him now come down from the cross, and we will believe on him. ^43He trusteth on God; let him deliver him now, if he desireth him: for he said, I am the Son of God. ^44And the robbers also that were crucified with him cast upon him the same reproach.

^45Now from the sixth hour there was darkness over all the land until the ninth hour. ^46And about the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, saying, Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani? that is, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? ^47And some of them stood there, when they heard it, said, This man calleth Elijah. ^48And straightway one of them ran, and took a sponge, and filled it with vinegar, and put it on a reed, and gave him to drink. ^49And the rest said, Let be; let us see whether Elijah cometh to save him. ^50And Jesus cried again with a loud voice, and yielded up his spirit. ^51And behold, the veil of the temple was rent in two from the top to the bottom; and the earth did quake; and the rocks were rent; ^52and the tombs were opened; and many bodies of the saints that had fallen asleep were raised; ^53and coming forth out of the tombs after his resurrection they entered into the holy city and appeared unto many. ^54Now the centurion, and they that were with him watching Jesus, when they saw the earthquake, and the things that were done, feared exceedingly, saying, Truly this was the Son of God. ^55And many women were there beholding from afar, who had followed Jesus from Galilee, ministering unto him: ^56among whom was Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of the sons of Zebedee.

^57And when even was come, there came a rich man from Arimathaea, named Joseph, who also himself was Jesus' disciple: ^58this man went to Pilate, and asked for the body of Jesus. Then Pilate commanded it to be given up. ^59And Joseph took the body, and wrapped it in a clean linen cloth, ^60and laid it in his own new tomb, which he had hewn out in the rock: and he rolled a great stone to the door of the tomb, and departed. ^61And Mary Magdalene was there, and the other Mary, sitting over against the sepulchre.

^62Now on the morrow, which is the day after the Preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees were gathered together unto Pilate, ^63saying, Sir, we remember that that deceiver said while he was yet alive, After three days I rise again. ^64Command therefore that the sepulchre be made sure until the third day, lest haply his disciples come and steal him away, and say unto the people, He is risen from the dead: and the last error will be worse than the first. ^65Pilate said unto them, Ye have a guard: go, make it as sure as ye can. ^66So they went, and made the sepulchre sure, sealing the stone, the guard being with them.

Matthew 28

28

^1Now late on the sabbath day, as it began to dawn toward the first day of the week, came Mary Magdalene and the other Mary to see the sepulchre. ^2And behold, there was a great earthquake; for an angel of the Lord descended from heaven, and came and rolled away the stone, and sat upon it. ^3His appearance was as lightning, and his raiment white as snow: ^4and for fear of him the watchers did quake, and became as dead men. ^5And the angel answered and said unto the women, Fear not ye; for I know that ye seek Jesus, who hath been crucified. ^6He is not here; for he is risen, even as he said. Come, see the place where the Lord lay. ^7And go quickly, and tell his disciples, He is risen from the dead; and lo, he goeth before you into Galilee; there shall ye see him: lo, I have told you. ^8And they departed quickly from the tomb with fear and great joy, and ran to bring his disciples word. ^9And behold, Jesus met them, saying, All hail. And they came and took hold of his feet, and worshipped him. ^10Then saith Jesus unto them, Fear not: go tell my brethren that they depart into Galilee, and there shall they see me.

^11Now while they were going, behold, some of the guard came into the city, and told unto the chief priests all the things that were come to pass. ^12And when they were assembled with the elders, and had taken counsel, they gave much money unto the soldiers, ^13saying, Say ye, His disciples came by night, and stole him away while we slept. ^14And if this come to the governor's ears, we will persuade him, and rid you of care. ^15So they took the money, and did as they were taught: and this saying was spread abroad among the Jews, and continueth until this day.

^16But the eleven disciples went into Galilee, unto the mountain where Jesus had appointed them. ^17And when they saw him, they worshipped him; but some doubted. ^18And Jesus came to them and spake unto them, saying, All authority hath been given unto me in heaven and on earth. ^19Go ye therefore, and make disciples of all the nations, baptizing them into the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit: ^20teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I commanded you: and lo, I am with you always, even unto the end of the world.

Micah 2

2

^1Woe to them that devise iniquity and work evil upon their beds! when the morning is light, they practise it, because it is in the power of their hand. ^2And they covet fields, and seize them; and houses, and take them away: and they oppress a man and his house, even a man and his heritage. ^3Therefore thus saith Jehovah: Behold, against this family do I devise an evil, from which ye shall not remove your necks, neither shall ye walk haughtily; for it is an evil time. ^4In that day shall they take up a parable against you, and lament with a doleful lamentation, and say, We are utterly ruined: he changeth the portion of my people: how doth he remove it from me! to the rebellious he divideth our fields. ^5Therefore thou shalt have none that shall cast the line by lot in the assembly of Jehovah. ^6Prophesy ye not, thus they prophesy. They shall not prophesy to these: reproaches shall not depart. ^7Shall it be said, O house of Jacob, Is the Spirit of Jehovah straitened? are these his doings? Do not my words do good to him that walketh uprightly? ^8But of late my people is risen up as an enemy: ye strip the robe from off the garment from them that pass by securely as men averse from war. ^9The women of my people ye cast out from their pleasant houses; from their young children ye take away my glory for ever. ^10Arise ye, and depart; for this is not your resting-place; because of uncleanness that destroyeth, even with a grievous destruction. ^11If a man walking in a spirit of falsehood do lie, saying, I will prophesy unto thee of wine and of strong drink; he shall even be the prophet of this people. ^12I will surely assemble, O Jacob, all of thee; I will surely gather the remnant of Israel; I will put them together as the sheep of Bozrah, as a flock in the midst of their pasture; they shall make great noise by reason of the multitude of men. ^13The breaker is gone up before them: they have broken forth and passed on to the gate, and are gone out thereat; and their king is passed on before them, and Jehovah at the head of them.

Micah 3

3

^1And I said, Hear, I pray you, ye heads of Jacob, and rulers of the house of Israel: is it not for you to know justice? ^2ye who hate the good, and love the evil; who pluck off their skin from off them, and their flesh from off their bones; ^3who also eat the flesh of my people, and flay their skin from off them, and break their bones, and chop them in pieces, as for the pot, and as flesh within the caldron. ^4Then shall they cry unto Jehovah, but he will not answer them; yea, he will hide his face from them at that time, according as they have wrought evil in their doings. ^5Thus saith Jehovah concerning the prophets that make my people to err; that bite with their teeth, and cry, Peace; and whoso putteth not into their mouths, they even prepare war against him: ^6Therefore it shall be night unto you, that ye shall have no vision; and it shall be dark unto you, that ye shall not divine; and the sun shall go down upon the prophets, and the day shall be black over them. ^7And the seers shall be put to shame, and the diviners confounded; yea, they shall all cover their lips; for there is no answer of God. ^8But as for me, I am full of power by the Spirit of Jehovah, and of judgment, and of might, to declare unto Jacob his transgression, and to Israel his sin. ^9Hear this, I pray you, ye heads of the house of Jacob, and rulers of the house of Israel, that abhor justice, and pervert all equity. ^10They build up Zion with blood, and Jerusalem with iniquity. ^11The heads thereof judge for reward, and the priests thereof teach for hire, and the prophets thereof divine for money: yet they lean upon Jehovah, and say, Is not Jehovah in the midst of us? no evil shall come upon us. ^12Therefore shall Zion for your sake be plowed as a field, and Jerusalem shall become heaps, and the mountain of the house as the high places of a forest.

Micah 4

4

^1But in the latter days it shall come to pass, that the mountain of Jehovah's house shall be established on the top of the mountains, and it shall be exalted above the hills; and peoples shall flow unto it. ^2And many nations shall go and say, Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of Jehovah, and to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths. For out of Zion shall go forth the law, and the word of Jehovah from Jerusalem; ^3and he will judge between many peoples, and will decide concerning strong nations afar off: and they shall beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruning-hooks; nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more. ^4But they shall sit every man under his vine and under his fig-tree; and none shall make them afraid: for the mouth of Jehovah of hosts hath spoken it. ^5For all the peoples walk every one in the name of his god; and we will walk in the name of Jehovah our God for ever and ever. ^6In that day, saith Jehovah, will I assemble that which is lame, and I will gather that which is driven away, and that which I have afflicted; ^7and I will make that which was lame a remnant, and that which was cast far off a strong nation: and Jehovah will reign over them in mount Zion from henceforth even for ever. ^8And thou, O tower of the flock, the hill of the daughter of Zion, unto thee shall it come, yea, the former dominion shall come, the kingdom of the daughter of Jerusalem. ^9Now why dost thou cry out aloud? Is there no king in thee, is thy counsellor perished, that pangs have taken hold of thee as of a woman in travail? ^10Be in pain, and labor to bring forth, O daughter of Zion, like a woman in travail; for now shalt thou go forth out of the city, and shalt dwell in the field, and shalt come even unto Babylon: there shalt thou be rescued; there will Jehovah redeem thee from the hand of thine enemies. ^11And now many nations are assembled against thee, that say, Let her be defiled, and let our eye see our desire upon Zion. ^12But they know not the thoughts of Jehovah, neither understand they his counsel; for he hath gathered them as the sheaves to the threshing-floor. ^13Arise and thresh, O daughter of Zion; for I will make thy horn iron, and I will make thy hoofs brass; and thou shalt beat in pieces many peoples: and I will devote their gain unto Jehovah, and their substance unto the Lord of the whole earth.

Micah 5

5

^1Now shalt thou gather thyself in troops, O daughter of troops: he hath laid siege against us; they shall smite the judge of Israel with a rod upon the cheek. ^2But thou, Beth-lehem Ephrathah, which art little to be among the thousands of Judah, out of thee shall one come forth unto me that is to be ruler in Israel; whose goings forth are from of old, from everlasting. ^3Therefore will he give them up, until the time that she who travaileth hath brought forth: then the residue of his brethren shall return unto the children of Israel. ^4And he shall stand, and shall feed his flock in the strength of Jehovah, in the majesty of the name of Jehovah his God: and they shall abide; for now shall he be great unto the ends of the earth. ^5And this man shall be our peace. When the Assyrian shall come into our land, and when he shall tread in our palaces, then shall we raise against him seven shepherds, and eight principal men. ^6And they shall waste the land of Assyria with the sword, and the land of Nimrod in the entrances thereof: and he shall deliver us from the Assyrian, when he cometh into our land, and when he treadeth within our border. ^7And the remnant of Jacob shall be in the midst of many peoples as dew from Jehovah, as showers upon the grass, that tarry not for man, nor wait for the sons of men. ^8And the remnant of Jacob shall be among the nations, in the midst of many peoples, as a lion among the beasts of the forest, as a young lion among the flocks of sheep; who, if he go through, treadeth down and teareth in pieces, and there is none to deliver. ^9Let thy hand be lifted up above thine adversaries, and let all thine enemies be cut off. ^10And it shall come to pass in that day, saith Jehovah, that I will cut off thy horses out of the midst of thee, and will destroy thy chariots: ^11and I will cut off the cities of thy land, and will throw down all thy strongholds. ^12And I will cut off witchcrafts out of thy hand; and thou shalt have no more soothsayers: ^13and I will cut off thy graven images and thy pillars out of the midst of thee; and thou shalt no more worship the work of thy hands; ^14and I will pluck up thine Asherim out of the midst of thee; and I will destroy thy cities. ^15And I will execute vengeance in anger and wrath upon the nations which hearkened not.

Micah 6

6

^1Hear ye now what Jehovah saith: Arise, contend thou before the mountains, and let the hills hear thy voice. ^2Hear, O ye mountains, Jehovah's controversy, and ye enduring foundations of the earth; for Jehovah hath a controversy with his people, and he will contend with Israel. ^3O my people, what have I done unto thee? and wherein have I wearied thee? testify against me. ^4For I brought thee up out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed thee out of the house of bondage; and I sent before thee Moses, Aaron, and Miriam. ^5O my people, remember now what Balak king of Moab devised, and what Balaam the son of Beor answered him; remember from Shittim unto Gilgal, that ye may know the righteous acts of Jehovah. ^6Wherewith shall I come before Jehovah, and bow myself before the high God? shall I come before him with burnt-offerings, with calves a year old? ^7will Jehovah be pleased with thousands of rams, or with ten thousands of rivers of oil? shall I give my first-born for my transgression, the fruit of my body for the sin of my soul? ^8He hath showed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth Jehovah require of thee, but to do justly, and to love kindness, and to walk humbly with thy God? ^9The voice of Jehovah crieth unto the city, and the man of wisdom will see thy name: hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it. ^10Are there yet treasures of wickedness in the house of the wicked, and a scant measure that is abominable? ^11Shall I be pure with wicked balances, and with a bag of deceitful weights? ^12For the rich men thereof are full of violence, and the inhabitants thereof have spoken lies, and their tongue is deceitful in their mouth. ^13Therefore I also have smitten thee with a grievous wound; I have made thee desolate because of thy sins. ^14Thou shalt eat, but not be satisfied; and thy humiliation shall be in the midst of thee: and thou shalt put away, but shalt not save; and that which thou savest will I give up to the sword. ^15Thou shalt sow, but shalt not reap; thou shalt tread the olives, but shalt not anoint thee with oil; and the vintage, but shalt not drink the wine. ^16For the statutes of Omri are kept, and all the works of the house of Ahab, and ye walk in their counsels; that I may make thee a desolation, and the inhabitants thereof a hissing: and ye shall bear the reproach of my people.